<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-boston-subway</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	      <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84024441/1897-03-04/ed-1/?sp=5&q=Boston+Dead+dead+explosion+flame+gas+Gas+Subway
</id>
	      <rel>1</rel>
	      <text>Boston, March 4. An explosion lias just
occurred in the subway excavation at the
corner of Trcraont and Ooylston streets.
Three electric cars that were passing
at the time were wrecked and one ot
them was burned. Several bulldingsin the
vicinity were more or less damaged.
The explosion was caused by escaping
gas.
Among the buildings damaged are the
Hotel Pclliam, the Knickerbocker and
Head buildings and the Masonic Temple.
Window glass in buildings within 200
feet of the scene of the explosion were
shattered.
At least twelve persons were killed.
Four bodies have been removed to un
dertaking' rooms.
Forty-two persons arc at the Emergency
Hospital.
Among the dead are:
Rev. W. A. Slack, professor at Tufts Col
lege. G. I). Bigclow, conductor.
Unknown man and woman.
The injured include James Reardon, John
J. O'Conuor, Thomas F. Ford, Mrs. J. R.
Wilson, Nellie Jackson, Lucy Dolan, F.
W. Tceling, and Mrs. F. A. reck
There seems to be no doubt thatatleast
eight persons were immediately killed.
The explosion came Jutt as the streetcars
were almost in the ceutcr of the space at
the corner.
The first car was In the center when the
explosion came. The whole of the wood
work, which is used as a bridge over the
subway, was lifted into the air, carrying
the first car with it and taking along the
two horses of the second car. The other
Tehlcles were lifted straight into the air,
but came down on the tracks. Instantly
the air was filled with flying debris.
The firat electric car, the one in which
most or the killed were riding, no sooner
reached the track than It broke in hair,
and the whole portion Immediately burst
into flame. Then someone sounded a fire
alarm. This brought a large rescue force
to the scene, and almost immediately calls
were being sent out hurriedly for the am
bulances. It was an awful Eight that met the gaze
of those who were first on the scene. In
the center was the long blazing electric
car. .Close beride this were the bodies ot
the two horses killed instantly, and about
ten, twenty, thirty feet away from where
the woodwork of the car was blazing lay
the dead and wounded people. Those who
wore not injured in the cars on Boylston
6treet were Incapable ot action
at first, and people in the buildings and
stores surrounding did not know what had
occurred, but it did not take them long
to secure their senses, and almost imme
diately there was a rush to the assistance
ot the wounded.
It is stated that there was not a person
on the three cars who was not injured, and
all the wounds received were severe. Im
mediately stores and offices were con
verted into temporary hospitals until am
bulances could arrive. 1 1 was a gruesome
spectacle to see these bodies exposed on
the sidewalks.
Hose carriages were pressed into service
as ambulances, and immediately they were
started on their humane duty or getting the
maimed to the hospitals.
It Is supposed that-one of the dead women
at Jones' undertaking rooms Is Mrs. A. M.
Bates. She was out wlth a sister this
morning and has not returned. The sister
returned home slightly injurcd</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1897-09-19/ed-1/?sp=32&q=BOSTON+Boston+BOSTONS+SUBWAY+subway</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>UNDERGROUND TRAVEL.
T1IK BOSTON SUBWAY PARTLY COM?
PLETED AND IN OPERATION.
A BRI0I1TI.T UOIITED Tl NNW. AFKfU'.PlN?: RAPID
TRANSIT FOR BLECTRIO CARS CONORS
TIO? OV TUB BTREET9 RELIEVBD,
The subway for streetcars In Boston, a pari
of whli h has Ju il b >a op? n? -i for at rvlce. is an
em.???? of more than local Interest The ne
eesslty for some relief t? the i rowded thorough?
fares above it can besl be appre? lat? d, of course,
by H lonlans; but tl?.- Modem Aib.n.s is i?; no
means th.ily cltj In this countr) which is
beset with problems of the same character.
ThofO who :ii" familiar v.iih "!h<- lay of tiie
land" in Bosl? n remember thai Tremont-st. runs
In a ajenerall) north-and-aonth direction and
forms ihe istern boundary of th.- Common.
Ii i-; intersected by Rovlston-st., which consti?
tutes Ihe southern boundary of thai historic
parle On the Boylsl m and Tremonl st edges
of the Common there is a broad promenade.
known as the Mall. The main part of the sub?
ira. li. h Is w Id nough to a? commodate four
tracks, passes under ihe Tremonl st. Mall, and.
niter passing under Park-st, which lies along
the northern side if ine Common, extends mr
will extend, when completed) to Scollay ?Square,
thence eastward to Adams Square, ami finally
up northward again to Hayraarkel Square.
This terminus Is close to the great union rail?
way station .it the North End.
Ft en th.- oin, r of Tri mont and Boylston sts.
there are two extensions, wldn enough f>?r only
a double track. Boylston st. Mall for about '.k"> feet, and then
ascends an Incline through an op? n ul for ,'il*
feel The terminal station for this branch la
situated In th- Public Gardens. The other
branch reaches away to the southward, and. on
nearlng th<- Junction of Bhawmul ave. and Tn
mont-st., forks. A separate two-track incline
leads up into each of those streeta
Including th? Inclines, ihe subway has a total
length of about a mile and a half, und will con?
tain about five miles of track Al present the
branches from th.rn.-r of Boylston and Tre?
monl Bl.-. and th-- main line up to Park-Si. an
In operation. A great >l<-.il o? work has already
been done on the northern portion of the route,
arid it is h? i I thai everything all) be finished
within th> n \t eight months. Hi und wats
broken for the subway in April, 1805, twenty
Bine month- ago.
The depth of this underground passageway Is
1 I f. t. The Width IS L'i feel for I WO T.|. l(S, .11,d
18 feel f.-r f? ur. Al Int rvala of sis r- et, along the
side.-, si--. I posts are b< t up on at.1 foundatl >nB,
and from the tops of those on one side there
r? rn h a? n i to the top ..f o, i th? r
stul roof beams. Where there arc four tracks
there is a c? ntral lia.f posts in the turn I, In
addition to those along the sides, From one
ro i am t.? the n< sl th? re cxl nd an ai h of
ma t.ry. These su< Iv? ai hi f. mil I hi
roof, an covered with coni-rete; ind th?
mat? lal HI th? pace betWi'.-i
the Bides. A waterproof I
i In es iding from I .....a, wat< r that
other? leak n fi ml ill. Th? m i
?onry floor is d, like an Inv? rted ar. h,
an l al ng II ?rural line iher? r in i a dra n At
Int? r\ ala the train a pit, from
which, whem ver the wat? r rises to a
level, the contents arc withdrawn bj auti i il
ally con troll? I 1?. :r,,- pumps
V? ntllatlon Is ff? '.-l by hui i ?l irj ran
establish? d in masonrj it thi or four
pointa along the i ne. The air Is suck l out of
the subway, and forced upward thi ugh the
op nfnga to Ihe level of ihe ?trei-i, ll u dr< I of
Im and? m i ctrlc imi and scores of an
Hghta ai i advanl ig? i al ?ng Ihe in
terl? r. As clectrlelt) i>d for th?
propulsion of the i ara hi? h i il
th? r.- la i. smoke lo a? umulat? i n the -Mings,
and no foul gases to offend the fa i rv?i
Tin-re is no reason why th? pla h ..-1 n I r?
main lean, sweet and bright for years.
AI th? und? rground r irse, the
subway is broaden? I A high Air? fenc? runa
lengthwise In the middle, irallng the two
noi thboui -1 tr u from the tw?i soul hi un I.
The tra- lu of e.i., t, p.ur are Ivided i rial n
gineers call an "island platform." saj feel
wide, and 300 or IfSJ feel long. Ace? i.m tie
had to on? platform from the ??(her onlj b) pro
Ing down a low flight of ita ai i through a
narrow bul brightly Illuminated pas age undei
n- ath, oi i going up i the street and rosslng
iv? r.
The cara v. hi, h run Ihn ugh the tunnel ar- oi
("..i irj li lej cars, but, iik.- many which tra-.
i other rout? In t!:-- i ty, th? y are all con?
trolled by one ror|ioratliin, Ihe West Knd Street
Hallway Company, to which, by the way, the
subwaj la- lieen leased by th? Tran t Commis
i neri 'iii fact partially explains some of the
pri au ?i taken al the stations. Then one
buys a ii ki t In lure h >a riling i.u or Hing a,
rhan? e to do o, are) thi ndui lor on I h? car col
lecta Ihe Ll? kets, Kill fn m th? i tatlon i lat
Is effected Ihrouul lun les, wbi< b a.. >w
a person to pa In onlj ?in dh i ion.
in. id, easy stall rid d n n from Ih I reel
r? the und und statloi 'i i
more than thirty Btej In a (light Th ai
two flights for He northbound tracks, ind two
f ?r the Bouthl ?ui I The h ud of a li
i.; in loa d by a neat oni tory, gla
granite b ill lin Glazed white i?i i. i< and i I? lit)
?,f whit.- paint Impart to ihe station interlora
a fresh and the r> appearance. At present t?..-
BOSTON'S NEW SUBWAY INCLINE IN THE PUBLIC GARDEN.
?nly stations in use underground are at the cor
ner of Boylston and Tremont sts. ami at Park-st
A temporary loop at the latter point permits
the northbound cars to return without switch?
ing. When the subway is completed, however.
there uiii i.ther stations at Si o lay Square,
Adams Square and Hay market Square.
miy an engineer can begin to understand
th.- difficulties of an undertaking lik?- this
Count leas sewers, a ater-plpcs, gasplp? s and tele
phon? -Air.- conduits have been laid close to the
route, and Bom of ih.s,- have been bared dur?
ing the prigresa of the necessary excavation.
When ihelr position was at a higher level than
the r..of ,,f the future subway it was not neces?
sary to do ne re than lo protect them carefully
f.r the lime. Bui if the) were lower than the
roof, and higher than the Boor, the situation
was root, serious. Two great water mains, one
thirty Inches In diameter and the other forty
BOSTONS NEW SUBWAY FOUR-TRACK SUBWAY UNDER TRKMONT-ST.
Inches across, ?ere encountered at that very in
invenlent level, It became necessary to con
utru t siphons, bending down under the subway
and up agiln on the other Bide, in order to ad
ju-t these conflicts of Interest. Kor the happy
solution of all th.-:- difficulties great credit is
,'-j to th? t'ity Commission Intrusted with the
work, to their 'hlef ngli.r, and, in some meas?
ure, t. the engine, rs of the West End Company,
An Incidental l j: I mi orlant f. ature of tlie
plan of construction Is the avoidance of grade
i rossinirs. In the four-track passageway the
Iloylston-st. ears have the two inside tracks,
and the Tremont-st and Bhawmut-ave. ears use
the two outer ones in common. Accordingly,
at th" southeastern corner of the Common, the
westernmost track (southnound) is carried down
Under the two central ones, by a special one
track tunrnl which soon emerges With another
one-track tunnel carrying th>- up-track. At a
point still further south a similar plan Is pur
sued in th.- separating of the Bhawmut-ave. and
Tremont-st. cars
Tie- cipa. Ity of the subway is ninety cars
per mit,ute. Inasmui h as th" facilities thus af?
forded :ir.- Buppli mentary to th.me already af
forded on Tremont-st., and an- not a substitute
for the latter, a distinct increase In the number
of punes, as well as freedom from blockades,
bas been secured.
RJtlUYBRAVIVO POSTAI* CARDS.
i From The Boston Transcript.
An advertisement has appeared in some of the
daily papers In which a cosh payment has been
offered for uneancelled printed postal cards. It
seems that many business houses have occasion
j to have a large number of postal cards printed
to advertise some special line of goods or for
the use of some travelling man. For some rea?
son or other the conditions may change, so that
perhaps only half of the cards are use?), being
or m'.cd, Lbey can nut be used in any other way,,
j and the result is that in nine CSSSS out of ten
they are consigned to the waste basket, a? the
Government does not red. em uncancelled postal
cards an it does stamped envelopes.
A process has been discovered by which all of
the printed matter may be removed from the
card, leaving it in the same condition as when
bought at the poatofBcn. A charge of one-half
cent per card is- made for this work; or, in other
words, a man sends five hundred carda to be
"made over." The man who does the work
charges f?SO for his services, ami tin- u.?tomer
save? $1* ."?0, as the printed cards were of no uas
to him.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn95079490/1897-10-23/ed-1/?sp=7&q=BOSTON+SUBWAY</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE BOSTON SUBWAY
SATISFACTORY SOLUTION OF THE
STREET CAR PROBLEM.
Contention of Trafllc In tli? Iluny Streets
of the Uub Relieved by Underground
Trolley Lines?Tunnels Tlmt Am Light,
Clean uud Attractive.
It is now possible to cross Tromont
street, Boston, at any point opposite tho
Common and at any time of day without
loss of life or limb. Tho new subway has
brought about tho change.
It 1 s an old tradition that tho fathers of
Boston, when thoy laid out tho city, let
the. streets follow the winding cow paths.
At any rate, the streets ius thoy exist today
urc very crooked and must of them aro
very narrow. This was all right in Revo?
lutionary times, but when the city grow
miles beyond tho Common und spread it?
self out to tho south and west; when busi?
ness centered itself along tbu lower ends
of Washington and Trentont streets, and
when dozens of street car tracks usurped
tho narrow roadways, then the Bostonlans
wished their ancestors bud not stuck so
closely to the cow paths.
Probably no other city on the continent,
was ever so badly allllctcd with a conges?
tion of trnllic as tho Hub haslieon for
many yea: Some of tho most important
street ear linen skirt tho south and east,
cornets ol the Common on Boylston mid
Tremont streets. When I he chango was
made hum hoc. epov.vr to trolley, matters
grew worse. Then tho poles and the tan?
gle of overhead wires made that historic.
breathing spot look liko a pieco of dingy,
green billiard cloth which had become fray?
ed and tuttered around the edges. So after
much wrangling in tho legislature and
courts it w;ls decided tu build the subway
and put the trolley cars underground.
A large portion of the work bus already
lieen accomplished and Boston is delight?
ed with the result. The first thing a Hus?
ton man asks a visitor from Now York,
Chicago or elsewhere is:
"Been through tho subway yet'/ Let's
see?you huven't one in your place, have
you?"
It is, in fact, a triumph of engineering
anil well worth a visit. Then! arc throe
open cut.s where tho trolley curs enter the
subway. One Is out on Tremont street
whore Shawmut avenue comes in. Hero
the tracks from each of those jmorough
fares dive into the tunnel. Another is In
the Public gardens, where the cars com?
ing down Boylston street take tho under?
ground tlip. The third is at tho northerly
end of the subway, just beyond-Hay mar?
ket square and in front of the new Union
terminal railroad station into which the
Fitchburg, Hoston und Maine, Eastern
und other roads run. Theru is u. loop hern
DOSTON'S NEW SUBWAY INCLINE IN THE Plin
LIC ns most of the t rolley lines inako it their
terminus, and, the subway being four
tracked, they disgorge their passengers
and take the back track up town.
Including the inclines or open onto, tho
subway has a total length of 1 miles and
will contain about live miles of track. At
present the branch down Boylston street
along the Common side and the main line
down Tremont to Park street are in oper?
ation. The Shawmut avenue branch and
tho northerly end of the main lino will be
finished within the next eight months.
Ground was broken for the subway in
April, 18115. The sum appropriated was
$7,ii(?0,000 and, wonderful to relate, tho
transit commissioners say that it is proba?
ble the cost will bo about $1,000,000 less
than that sum.
No groat difficulties have been encoun?
tered thus far in digging this big liplo In
the ground. Of course there were count?
less sewers, water pipes, gas pipes, electric
wire conduits and the like und some -III
inch water mains at an inconvenient level
proved rather hnrxl to handle, but n? un?
expected conditions arose to delay tho
work. The main trunk of the subway
runs under the wide walk or mall on tho
east side of the Common, anil when the
excavations were being made the bones of
hundreds of old Puritans were disturbed.
This raised a bowl of righteous Indigna?
tion,and the sncredness of the long forgot
burying ground was harped upon for
weeks. Hut the commissioners quieted
the reverent patriots by collecting nil tho
bones and roiuterrlng them in the holy
ground of the Common, with a nice monu?
ment to mark the spot.
The tleepest jioint of tho subway is on
Boylston street, where the south bound
t racks are laid lit) feet lielow the surface,
but the average depth is 14 feet. The tun?
nel itself is a giant bore with ribs of steel
mid casings! of cement, asphalt, concrete
and masonry. The roof is a series of
arches und the floor Is concave, with
drains at the bottom. As tho drnins are
below the level of the sewers, jilts have
been established at Intervals, and when
thev are filled with water automatic elec?
trical pumps are started, which empty
them Into tho sewers above.
Perhaps yon imagine that Boston's sub?
way is a tlark, damp, ill smelling place. It
is nothing of the sort. The entrances to
the stations aro handsome structures of
stone, with glass roofs. The only fault, to
be found with them is that thev remind
cs?blc. It makes food shortened
it i3 uahcaltb.ru! and filled with
icd by every medical r.::d culi- B
1
vegetable oil is nutritive, digest-
i
coil. Itisnu
:d with or fried
armful results.
md yoll^w tins,with
u((nM-/ililii( urc.il??
way. lladounlyby
1 PAN Y,
Montreal. ^?-?n?? _^ff* fa
you or an olo Urccinn tomi)?ft" least that
is what I thought of the first time I saw
one. Put then you go down an easy (light
of wide stone steps to n cheerful, brilliant?
ly lighted station. Everything Isdazzllug
ly white. The bricks lining the entrance
art? of glazed white porcelain, the mason?
ry arches are painted white and the iron
pillars and supports arc covered with im?
maculate white; enamel. Incandescent and
are lights Hash everywhere, and the vista
nhead through tho stretches of the subway
is far from u dingy one. It. Is about tho
cleanest und neatest holu In tho ground in
existence and no doubt will be kept so.
Already lifo tralllo on Tromont and Duyl
ston streets has been much decreased, ami
when tl;e subway is fully completed Bos?
ton foil: may get about their town with
comparative ease und safety.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030272/1897-12-15/ed-1/?sp=3&q=BOSTON+Boston+SUBWAY+subway</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>'BOSTON'S UNUSED SUBWAY.
ft) H' VMDBnOltOVSD TBAXBITA TAILURE
j jjv oxvU x. rjtA otice.
Ij aYeople Reniie ta L'se It. Jot as Thfir Wonld
.1' the Hot la tbo Cronna Transit rropwed
J'v fbr Wew .rk Only Keren Per Cent, ef the
M Total Tronic Credited ta the flatmar The
j rreniable rnney TraDI o Lost to It Entirely
Jf Vat tba Condlllem Are nl Farorablr
BbS. Beaten Want, an Klevatrd nallraad Hon,
'sflf "H Before any farther attempt la mado to com'
i V Bait tbli eltr to the building of the proposed
jH underground system of rapid tranalt it would
H be well for every ono Interested to learn somo-
ll thing of the experience which Boston Is now
I lusTlng with Its subway. Boston's subway Is
li'H New York's proposed underground railroad In
L S miniature, excopt that It was constructed for
I H the use of the trolley car lines Instead of being
I V equipped with cars, motors, and power of Its
I H own, and mnnlnir two sets of trains one express
tf( I and one local.
The Boston subway short. That part now
jkVM tense Is less than ft mile In length, and the
KS farts which are under construction or proposed
R M Would add only about another mile to the tun
Hk wr Bet, There lr, perhaps, no finer specimen of
Jl&B passenger tunnel work any whero In the world,
aBfYS n ls doubtful -f anymore perfect tunnel
HtjH could Deconstructed.
B9p The tunnel runs under Tremont street, and
HHk Its extensions are to go under Cornhlll, Han
JJ. oxer street, and Washington streot, passing
i right through the denso business and shopping
districts, and thus securing every advantage
I that a road might have If It ran through Broad-
jf Tray, Fourteenth street and Twenty-third street,
i and part of Sixth avenue. And yet. In the face
j ef all these advantages, three months' experi
ence has shown that the Boston subway is not
popular, that people will not go Into It ex-
cept when they have to, and that the subway Is
lv a failure, save so far as It was a necosslty to re-
i'i Have the congestion of traffic on the street.
V XEED OF TUB BUDWAT.
A Bostonlans are proud of the subway. They
ri take strangers to see It, just as they take them
h to see Bunker IIIll Monument; make them ride
vM the length of It back and forth, and call alien
s' I tlon to all its fine foatures and then they keep
I away from it themsolves. Just as thoydofrom
if the monument. That this result ls of tntorest
I V to New Yorkers there can be no doubt. Tho
building of tbo subway growoutof a publloneed
Tfhloh was as absolute and pressing as the need
v ef this city for some addition to Its trafllo
in. facilities.
Hien, about ten years ago. the West End
oet Railway Company began to transform tho
horso car lines of Boston Into electric trot
lines the narrow streets In tho heart of
iton were already choked with tho dally rush
vehicles. Boston has to-day tho most ex
stve and comprehensive electrlo car system
the world. The added cars which wero re
red for tho now service fairly filled
i streets of the little central city
ere they were all concentrated. These
lines eorvo a suburban population of
trly a million persons, and it is possible to
;e a car for any part of the territory covered
.hoot going more thai a quarter of a mllo In
i city. Under a special act of the Lcglsla
e the Boston Transit Commission was ap
nted to devise a suitable means to relieve the
Station.
THE OrERATIVB COWTnAOT.
fader this commission tho subway wns
nned and is being built. Tho city of Boston
s for it and leases it to tho West End Street
llway Company for twenty years at an an
il rental which is not to be less than 4Ts per
it. upon the net cost of the tunnel, or more
,n .Ts per cent, upon tho sum of $7,000,000,
he tunnol should cost so much, and tho com
ly agrees to pay. in llou of interest, a toll of
nts for each car that passes through the
way. In caso the aggregate of tolls should
:eed the interest charges. The railroad com
ly cares for it, lights it, ventilates it, ana
ips It free from wator. i
fork was bosun on the subway on March 28,
13, and on Sept. 1 of this rear the first scc
o was put Into use. A second socllon was put
o use on Sept. 30. The main part of tbo sub
y now in use lies usdor Tremont street, bo
sen Park street and Boylst:n street. This
lion 'Is 1,700 feet long and contains four
cks. At both ends aro stations, built
nmodlously under ground and approached
m the surface by wide, easy stair
ye. wulch are protected by small or
mental stone buildings. At the BoyI
in street station the tunnel divides into
o two-tracked sections. Ono of these con
ues under Tremont street for about 1,200
it, whon its comes to tho surfaco and empties
cars upon the tracks in Tremont street and
awmut avenue, which hero diverge. The
ler branch turns sharply to the wostward,
asunder the edge of tho famous Common, to
Public Oarden beyond Ohnrles street, where
comes to tho surfaco, 1,200 foet from the
ylston streot station, and its cars goon tholr
y down Boylston street,
man standahd or coxsTitucnos.
The tunnel Is kept almost as light as day
im end to end. At the stations It ls lined on
sides with enamelled white brick. Through
t its length and on tho codings at tho
itlons It Is pnlnted white. At tlio su
ns and through the tunnol electric
hts aro hung In abundance, and to make
re that these shall not all fall at any ono tlnio
5y are divided nnd fed by two scparato clr
Its of wire, resides these lights, fixed In the
itnel, are the lights In tho passing cars, which
kept lit In making the tunnel passage. As
oorthreocarsaro passing In each direction
ery minute almost all the tliuo, their lights
me would keep it fairly well illuminated.
People doclare that they found the tunnel ro
ishlngly cool during the warm woather In Sep
nber Just after it was oponed, and In cold
lather they find It warm. No winds penetrato
and the moraont a porson gets to tho stairs at
itatlon he Is out of rench of storms. Only ono
jrce of discomfort has yet developed In tho
e of the tunnel, and that. It U belloved,
11 be remedied. This was, for the tlmo
lasted, a very groat trouble. It occurred
it month, when there had been a sudden
ange of 25 or 30 degrees in temperature,
oweathorhad been cold for thrco or four
ys, and the ground and tho Inside of tho tun
Ibadgotchillod until It was pretty nenrly as
Id under ground as on the surface. Thcncume
isoln tlio general teniperaturo of 23 or 30
grees. Tbo warm air. drawn Into tho tunnol
the ventllnting fans, struck against the
lllod roof and sides, and Immediately every
log began to weep. The cold roof and sides of
e tunnel condensed tho moisture In the
irraer air, and In a short tlmo the
jole Interior glistened with molsturu.
the stations tho condition was worst nnd pro
ced much discomfort. Here the air entered,
dof course gavo tin the greater part of its
ilsture. Most of tho moisture collected on tho
ling nnd dripped dnujion thn waiting passen
rs. People who had loft pleasant neathar
stairs found themselves exposed to trick
m streams below. It wns so bad that tbo
llroad company sot men to work scrnp
K down the roofs and Bides with riihbcr
urezers to gut rid of tho moisture. Even
this troiiblo cannot bo cured, tbo mil
sd officials do not believe that It would prove
serious consequence, bcciuso thero aro not
aro than thrco or four duj s In a year when
angrs of tetnpernturo uro wldo enough to
oduco tho drip.
REFL'SALOr THE run MO TO I'BK IT.
rho portion of (ho Bubnnyi use nt tlio pros
tllmo Is open fortrnvel from OoYlocl; A. M.
12 midnight cturlni; cwli day of tlio Muck.
lorenro at present 1,302 trips per duy being
n through ttio subway.
Vet hero Is the Bignilleaut fact; n study of tint
lly travel In tho Hiibnn-.. hour by hour and
y by day for months, Khiincd conclusive!)-, In
o judgment or tho,o who arc mont closely cou
nted, that the sub.va) U nut piipulnr.nm! that
Vf porsons tuo It, except w hen thev hnotn.
'esldcnt Littlo declares that this is aiiuuli
oro serious mutter than It would upniar to tliu
Initiated,
j THE KAKOV TIIAKKIO AVOIIIH IT,
B "In tho rush hours," he said, recently, In ills
jBA cussing tho matter, "I hit people in list tnke
HI every means of coiio)nnco that I here is at
t I hand. In these hours they Dock Into tlio sub-
Fii way as freely us they do In tliu ears i mining on
K, the surface, and during these hours nn carry
eH'-l about as many In the subway as It U possible
tJi for us to handle Iheront tboprnsotit time,"
Mf Then Mr. Little made a ntntument of which
iKmt. every street railway must reioi;nUo the truth,
lyK'l!, and which should bo inrrfiilly lonn.dered by
I M I.', every capitalist who maybe Invited to becomo
H I interested in building and operating the pio-
IbH posed rapid transit line In this city, provided tho
scheme ever gets so far as inviting contracts,
Thlsrushbourtraftlc,"Mr.Llttlocontlnued,
HkLSF "Is, however, not the business which wo mako
mv' tar money out of. If we had nothing but this
ntmi y other strlotly business traffic, it would
m
UK
b?id.1l!!,eH!.tA?i1B,lko Win business. Boring
nil tho middle part of earn day wo should bo
iu'inlf.,lSttsri!w "na (rotting nothing for
doing It. The fancy trnfUo 1s what wo want
and rely upon tho poople who ride bocauso Itls
V..VH nt to o, not bocauso they have to.
M? nTa. lhe People, our statistics show, who
will not go Into tho.subway. Wo know Just
how mnny persona tako tho cars In thn subwar.
becnuso wo sell tickets there beforo the peoplo
go upon tho station platforms, and these tickets
nro i-pllectcrl In tliocnrs. The sales of subway
car tlckcta show that thn tunnol gets a fixed
portion of the general trafllo, but docs not get Us
share of tho fluctuations,
Dlfll.tKK OF TIIF. 8UIIWAY IK ntiUItKS.
Wo carry nearly 200,000.000 pass-liners
every yoar. In September wo tarried 18.310,
(MX) passengers. Tho loop to tho Public Garden
from tho Park streot station was tho only ono
inon through tho subway during that month.
Tho atibwny trrtvel then wan 0.0 per cent, of
our wholo travel. In November, with tho Tre
mont streot and Shnwmul avenue toop open,
theMilnvnytraUIo reached 7.1 per cent, of tho
vtliolo,
"Sw His ft curious fact that although our
total number of passengers was Increased 111
October by 238,000 over the September figures,
tho number carried In tho subway was Increased
by only 7.000. Thfct great general tncronse was
nlmo-it entirely marto up of tho sort of fancy
riding 1 spoko of. Theio aro the peoplo who
Jump on n car nnd rldo downtown, ostensibly
to buy a spool of thrond or a skein of silk or
ynrn. hut really bocauso tho car Is handy and
the rldo pleasant. Theso pooplo won't go Into
the subway. If for no othor reason than becnuso
thoy won't walk down tho stairs.
"Tho steady trafllo which the tables show wo
can count upon ls shown In this table of a day's
sales of tickets on Oct. 1,"
Mr. Llttlo produced this tablet
rABSENOEns CARRIED IN BCBWAY OCT. 1, 1B07.
lloun. four.
a. M. r.
Oto 7. ill 7 4 to B S,0(IB
7 to t !A oto fl 3,408
8 to 0 S14 A to 7 l.nil
UtolO otlU 7 to S OIH
10 to 11 870 Hto V 096
11 to II! l.OUfi Oto'.O DID
r, M. lOtoll 44",
ito i l.nnintou: 247
1 to S I.K25
Oto 3 1,090 Total IS.SU7
ato 4 l.Kocl
AVOIDED EVEN MOKE IN STORMY WEATIIER.
One thing to be seen from theso Ilguros," Mr.
Llttlo added, Is that tho sulmny, although It
runs pistn number of the principal theatres,
does not get any appreciable quantiij- of that
strictly fancy riding, tho people going homo
from tbo theatres, any more than It gets the
sboppors.
On rainy days ono would suppose that tho
subway would get n bigger proportion of trafllo
than in flno weather; but this ls not true. I
mot Mr. Dalton. ono of tho Transit Commission,
the other day when It wns mining, at tho en
trance to tho Park street station.
'"Isn't this chnrnilngl' he exclaimed as he
got In out of the storm.
"I admitted th-it It was; but when I camoto
look over tha tables of daily receipts and com
pare thom with the total tralllo I found that
although tho general trafllo had fallen off less
than 0 per cent, because of tbo rainy dny, tho
subway traffic had lost 30 per cent. This Is the
rooro significant from tho fact that one
half the former number of cars nro now oft tho
streets above."
A reference to tho dally tablos showed how
tho travel In the subway fell off In unpleasant
weather. On Nor. 2, when tho usual dally
Irrffllc was 22,000 or 23,000 persons, only
14.000 went through tho subway. On Nov. 2a
tho number roll to 13,000, while tho next dny It
roso to 24,000. On Sundays, when tho tratllc
on nil parts of tho system ls fancy riding prin
cipally, tho number of passongers who go
through tbo subway falls as low as 0,000.
FACT8 FOR NEW YORK TO 1-0NDER,
These aro tho facta. If It wcro possible to
build tbo long tunnel proposed for this city nnd
mal.o all parts of It ns perfect ns tho Boston
subway, which is at least doubtful, what would
be thn effect of an oqual Indisposition of Now
Yorkers to using it upon tho chances of Its pay
ing I Tho proposed road would have enough to
contend with through tho location of its main
linos out of tho way of tho short-ride local
business, out of which alone profit ls to
be made; but If the fancy traffic avoided It, ns
It avoids the lloston subway, tho result would
bo ruinous, Tho contractors would find them
selves with no ono to carry except tho people
who wanted to ride to Harlem and far above
or to Klngsbrldge, all for fire cents, and. what
ever forfeit they had to make, they would soon
abandon tho lino for thn city to operate at a loss.
CACHES OF rUPLIC PREJUDICE.
Why the peoplo avoid tho subway Is a ques
tion much discussed. Perhaps as good nn ex
planation ns anr Is to bo found in a conversa
tion which took place between Tun Sun re
porter who gathered these fncts nnd the pretty
&lrl who Owns the news stnnd at one of Boston's
est hotels.
"Ilavo you beon through the subway yet I"
ho asked enthusiastically.
"Yes," the reporter nnswored.
"I have just been through It, Isn't It grand!"
she exclaimed.
"l)o you go through it of ten I" asked tho re
porter curiously.
"Ob, no!" Bho answered. "I think It's beau
tiful, so light, and dry, and comfort bio: but I
always take a surfaco car. I think I hate to
walk up the stairs, although I am not lazy. I
walk clear out to ltoxbury and back almost
ever' day, and have lost slxteon pounds by
doing so, but, somehow, I don't llko to go up and
down stairs In tho subway."
It ls probably something more than this thnt
deters people from going underground even In a
tunnel bo well lighted. It is well known thnt
the underground roads In London do not pay,
nnd this ls duo largely to tho lack of tho fnncy
trafflc, such as overflows surface lines and ele
vated roads In New York. Ask a Londoner If
he uses tho underground roads in his own city
much, and IiIb answer Is almost suro to bo:
"Oh, yes, but only when lhavo to."
NOW BOSTON WANTS AN ELEVATED ROAD.
That Boston has awakened to the fact that
subways arc not n good thing whero they can be
avoided. Is clear from the character of tho very
latest move now on foot there. This ls to build
elevated railroads from tho ends of the subway,
nnd thus, in thoopen air, enrry tho cars out be
yond the thickly built-UD sections to Rnx
bury, Cambridge, Cbarlestown, and be
jond. This plan ls to be carried out ns
soon as tho Stato Railroad Commission agrees
to a lease of the West End road's lines to the
new elevated railroad company.
</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82016413/1901-07-24/ed-1/?sp=6&q=Boston+subway</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Riding Astride Makes Little
Headway Among Ladies
There Is a rumor that the bean-cat-,
Ing, blue-blooded Boston dames have
mounted a new bobby. They rldo
astride. Not the bobby, but the horse.
They think this Is a good time to be
gin, says the New York Sun. Since
the Boston subway uus completed, a
large part of the population spends Its
time underground, riding back and
forth through the tunnel and exclaim
ing: "Wo did It!
This has Increased the above-ground
Inhabitants to so small a number that
It's a good time to oercomo public
opinion, because there's so little of It
to overcome. Consequently thd Boston
women refeired to t:nn seized the
chance to establish the new fad In rid
ing. They Know that by the tlmo the
people get tired ut looking nt their hole
In the ground, bloomers will nave be
come a pait of thfl Boston eieed of B's.
Its growing. Already It Includes Bos
ton bens, Boston bays, Boston blue
blood and Boston has bleus,
Within a few wck& the same rumor
has broken out nearer home. Newspa
per paragraphs have declared that New
York women, too, are going to aban
don the side puddle, aud takn to di
vided skirts. Doctors uho have been
consulted sigh and Bay they only wish
tuc rumor would come true. They do
what they tan to push It along. They
prescribe tiding nstilde, and say It Is.
tho only healthful and safe way for
anybody to tide. But tbij tity that
It'R ono of the presctltplons which New
iork women u.iu o tar declined to
take.
And yet theto Is a pcislstent rumor
In tho all' that women huvo been seen
riding nstilde ocn In tho paik. Tho
regular pom emeu have it certain repu-1
tatlnn for blindness, but there ts no
particular reason why it paik polite-!
mnn fahuuld have trouble with his ryes.
nil uujii iu Hiinw u mciu are any
visions cf namzons In. dUlilcd skirts
flitting nlonj; tho bridle paths there
cummer daja. Several polltemea were, I
tlteiefure, approached on tho subject.
"Ilev I seen anny vtiamcn rliiln' I
nulliridc lately? said one. "No I nin't.
They was t,u thiec actresses done It
a few yea is ago, but I ain't never seen
no lady u-doln" It."
At the riding academies the rumor
fared quite, as badly.
"No,1' said ono of the German tiding
masters, "ve aind god no ladles rtdln'
asdrlde In our agademy."
"Say, you ride better than you talk,"
put In another one. "Sits his English
sort of sideways, doesn't ho?" us the
German went off. "No, there's not a
single lady, nor a married one either,
riding astride In our academy. And I
don't think you'll And one In any of
tbo cither academies. They don't want
to hero in New York."
"Do they rldo that way In tho coun
try?" "I don't know. We had ono woman
who wanted to lenrn to ride astride,
She took a few lessons, but never went
nny farther than that."
"They rldo nstrldo In England. Do
you think that If It becomes tho uni
versal stylo over thoro New York
women will follow It?"
"I don't know. I'm not In tha
prophesying business. Women are
sticklers for style. They'd rldo on
their heads If It were the fashion. All 1
know 1b that we haven't seen any signs
of this new fad so far. Wo have a fow
HIHk HX:K,'iVm I IV
ilWlMBft Vr.3 A-Lfc-SI
GUNHRAL. LUDINGTON HERE.
H readier Ocneral M. I. Ludlngton,
Quartermaster llcneral of the Army
was about town this morning accom
panied by Quartermaster Major Rob
Inton. The Quartermaster General ts
Rteatly Impressed with Honolulu nnd
cnnsldeis the city a place of great Im
portance to the army transport ser
vice. Honolulu will loim a part of the
report of the general on his return to
Washington. He leaves In the Grant
for the Philippines win re he will re
main about a month, returning to the
States by way of New Yorl.
The bark Albert sailed for this port
from San Francisco on the 14th In:'..
She has quite a number of passengers,
nmong them being Mrs. Turner, wife
of the first mate.
little girls riding astrldo because the
doctors have ordered It; but no grown
up women."
At the new academy the head master
took the Inquiry very calmly.
"Well," ho said, "wo haven't nny
ladles riding astride, but we have a
good many little girls. Tbo women are
not likely to, rldo astride In the city,
at any rato not for tho present. There
are too many roughs. But they mav
ride that wuy In the country."
"Do they now?"
"I don't know of any that do. Still
Ihey may havo picked It up this winter
In the South.".
"Will theso little girls who are learn
ing to rldo astride be willing to change
to a side-saddle later? Won't they pre
fer tho easier and safer way of riding
nstrldc?"
"Oh, It's just ns comfortable for them
to ride with a side-saddle. Indeed. I'm
told It gives them a better grip of the
horse."
"If that is truo, that riding sideways
Is Just as easy, safe and comfortable,
and gives ana a better grip of the horse,
I suppose you would like to ride that
way yourself?"
"Well well no, I wouldn't. You
sec 1 think there's somebody waiting
for me," and tho master made his cs-i-ape.
"Of course," laughed a bystander,
"you'ro nut going to cntcli'tho academy
people encouraging women to ildo
astride. It k so much insler to rldo
that way that It would cut Into tie
number of lessuns teirlbly. At least
they think it wuuld. I don't helljvo It
myself. 1 think ten time!, as many
women would learn to tide and that It
would bo a good Oilng nil around."
Buffalo Bill offeied to wager tho ro
poller that In ten yiars tiom now
there won't bo one si ie-baddlu In a
thousand, lie sayM tho KngllBh worueti
want to inako It tuc fashion, anil th'.l
vhen it coa.es ta thllisa cquijtliuu. Uu
lat,llsh uct the fashion fur tho woild.
in spite, however, or Col. Co.iv
wager and of the minora which
to bo getting lather thick, tho jcotilu
who rldo bay that ao far tbeio aie no
signs of thu sldfi-eaddlo going to thu
shelf.
It Is worth lemcmberlng, luwevw,
that Just before the bicycle Jumped into
fashionable favor there were plenty ot
seucres who said that fashiouubiK
women would never touch It. It v.'Jt
the same thing with tho short sklit .'or
street wenr.
"It Is a queer thing," said a WQiunti,
"that In certain fashions society fol
lows tho masses. It's ulte ull right.
Society women don't want tj make
themselves conspicuous nnd uxptiw
themselves to unpleasant comment. So
they sit quietly buck and wait until I ho
thing has lost Its novelty und every
body has got on nil tho sarcastic, epi
grammatic gags he can think of and
wants a chanco to say smart things on
tho other sldo. Then tho society woman
adopts tha fail and everything Is lovely.
"Perhaps tno riding astrldo will tti'ii
out that way. As for thcro being any
danger of unpleasant experiences,
that's nonsense. I'va Been wnmn riding
abtrldo In tho Chicago parks and pco
pie scarcely looked twlca at them. And
I must say that the women rodo so well
that they could better atTord to be
looked at than tho women who rodo In
the old-fashioned way."
$g Feels Like
An Auger
This Is ona lypo ol hideous headache. There are miny
oiler klndj. each having Us particular variety of middl
ing tcrtert or dull, stupefying throb. Headachea belon?
to :ho past because Cessler's Magic Headache Wafers are
of the f reicr.t.
It vou smoke lao much, or drink too much,
or eel too
too late, or
uchc from
20 minutes
Mr. Mu Center. Ph. C. It.lwuVee. Wli. L</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1903-06-21/ed-1/?sp=42&q=BOSTON+subway</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE MARCH OF IMPROVEMENT IS FAST OBLITERATING MANY OF BOSTONS MOST FAMOUS OLD LANDMARKS
OLD STATIC HOUSE, BOSTON.
To be transformed Into a tunnel station for the subway
BOSTON IMPROVEMENTS.
Historic Landmarks and Crooked
Streets Disappearing.
Boston, June 20.— Within three years the
crooks and turnings and devious wanderings of
Boston's most honored highways and byways
will be nothing more than a memory of the past,
and many of her ancient landmarks will be
wiped out or so altered as to be unrecognizable
to the oldest inhabitant. Slowly and surely the
ancient thoroughfares are being widened,
straightened and bent into the rulerlike lines oC
i rosscut New- York. Philadelphia and Chicago.
Boston is undergoing a transformation below
arid aloft that would cause Benjamin Franklin.
John Hancock, "Warren and Paul Revere *.o rub
their eyes and stare in amazement. Million dol
lar buildings by the dozen, elevated roads, tun
nels and streetcar lines beneath the streets and
under the harbor, swamps and mud Hats filled
for piers and excavated for docks that ac
':;iinodate giant steamers these are the things
they would see.
Along State-st., beneath the spot where the
Boston Massacre occurred, and beneath the his
toric old State House, a tunnel is eating its way
from under the harbor to Scollay Square to con
nect with the present subway by means of
(lights of stairs and elevators, and thence out
side to the busy world. The old Slat- House
itself is to be transformed into a tunnel station
connecting with a subway line also. The re
modelled building will soon be crowded with
people hurrying back and forth, intent on busi
ness, with never a thought of its old associa
tions. Little do they think, as they hurry past
where tunnel workmen are digsing seventy feet
beneath, of what has happened In that quaint
old edifice. On this site the first State House
was built in 1G57. Destroyed by fire in 1711. it
was rebuilt In 1712, and rebuilt again in 1747,
when destroyed a second time. The building
has been in turn Town House, Courthouse. Prov
ince House, State House and City Hall. <>n the
NEW-YORK TRIBUNE ILLUSTRATED SUPPLEMENT.
PAIIK STREET CHUUCR, "RRIMSTONE CORNER," BOSTONT.
It is to make way for a skyscraper.
first floor in the early days was the merchants*
walk, or exchange.
During the Stamp Act excitement the stamped
clearances were burned in front of its doors.
The British troops were quartered within the
building in 17'J.S, and the Boston Massacre oc
curred about fifty feet away on March 1770.
The next day Samuel Adams stood in the coun
cil chamber and made his successful demand
upon the royal representatives fur the immedi
ate removal of the British troops from Boston.
In this same room Generals Clinton, Howe and
Gage held a council of war just before the bat
tle of Bunker Hill. In 17N'J, at the western end
of the State House, Washington reviewed the
great procession in his honor on the occasion of
his last visit to Boston. Here, also, in lSi>s,
William Lloyd Garrison found refuge from a
mob which had broken up an anti-slavery meet
ing, and threatened his life.
The Park-st. station of the present subway
handles I!7,course of its trolley traffic, but the number of
passengers who will pass through the old State
House station will far exceed this number.
The march "f progress does not stop here,
however. Down Washington-st., to connect with
the tunnel and present subway, will be another
subway, this a double one for elevated trains
after they leave tli" surface at the Broadway
extension. It will pass beneath the Old South
Church, the Old Corner Bookstore and other well
known landmarks. Through the tower of the
»lil South Church, which juts out into Washing
ton-st., it is planned to cut an arcade, in the
g< neral scheme of widening and straightening
Washington-st. Surrounding the Old South
Church on three sides, a new $1,000,000 office
building eleven stories high is going up rapidly.
The Old South Church has been called the
'Sanctuary of Freedom." The ground on which
it stands was formerly the site of Governor
John Winthrop's home, where he died in
Itri'.t. The land was afterward owned by Mine.
Mary Norton, wife of the Rev. John Norton,
who gave it in trust "forever, for the erecting of
a h"use for their assembling themselves to
gether publkjuely to worship God." The first
meeting house was a small cedar building, built
IB 16701 where Benjamin Franklin was baptized.
The present structure was built in I. When
the British occupied the town they desecrated
the place by using it as a riding school and cav
alry drill hall. In 187»J the "Old South Preserva
tion Committee" was formed to buy it for a loan
museum, at a cost of $4r,0.000. and saved it from
being torn down.
Further down toward the old North End a
syndicate has bought the old Hancock Tavern,
in Corn Court, and upon its site, with the ad
joining lots.'will build another eleven story office
building. Tenants in the Hancock Tavern have
already received their notice to more.
As long ago as 1(334 Samuel Coles k-pt a tav
ern on this spot, and he had in WMi for his
guests Governor Vane and the Indian Mian</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84020274/1904-05-08/ed-1/?sp=57&q=New+subway+York</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>Biggest Ttunmim!! m tine WrM
Fred'K. Boyd Sfeveimsoini ili2
J! 1 !Jrf aaaHaaH Anr:f I i I U'llPiSL
Ai-wSf aaaaaaHaaaaaaH aaaaaaUattiaCttaaaaH --i&jz&g' .ik vlU
x aaH& B 'aBrafeaaH ;W -J
amHBlH vaa aaar?aK.uaaaBm ,jMR;vr X
Haaaaavy-avaaaaam &UR aYaV&mw
aaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaas saPMr aaaaaW,
awawawawawawawawawan Sffi" SraaY
aaaaaaaaaaaaaj ir!3LjCaaaaavC
MHBHHHHH Kf
HHh,"'PmS
Alexander President FHnjxL. Hb9R
E. '1 Rapid (BaBfe.K
yK. Transit aHaaVaaLafl
.Pmvoard AaaaaEPaVHIH
aaKiv v LamA MBHBHHH
n..l- ru.w.. xt IBK" JH J Au,;u,t Delmont.
John D. McDonald. I aaaaaaaaaaMtt lH J
-w-i 1 UA. KVB 3 The Financier
i nu vuninicigr I Hp.
3 aaaaaYa' aaaav J
alaawawawaYa
VaYaYaYaYaYaYaYaYay x
A LITTLE more than
four vcars ago John
B. McDonald, a
New York' contractor,
sat in the banking house
of August Belmont on
Nassau street. He had
in his hand a contract
for building the New York
underground railroad on
a bid of S35.ooo.ooo. Pre
vious to this the rapid
transit commissioners
had been uji and down
"The Street searching
for a man strong enough
financially and daring
enough speculatively to
Kick such a colrssal en
terprise. At lest it w.n
a spectacular propositi in
The citv had driven a hard ba-gam.
the multi-million-iires sniffed at it
The Manhattan Elevated and the Metropolitan
Street Railway Company turned it down.
So it was with other financiers.
One after another shook his held.
When the subway was mentioned they suddenly
remembered that it was their busy day.
From all along the line of money kings came the
same answer: "It is putting goxl dollars into a
hole All save one.
"I'll think it-over," said Belmont.
Forty-eight hours 'later lie sent for the con
tractor. "I'll go into it." said the Nassiu street banker.
That is the financial story of the building of the
greatest underground railroad in the world. August
Belmont risked his entire fortune on a business cnture
tliat some of the biggest capitalists of America feared
to undertake.
"How did you hive the nerve to go into it, Bel
mont?" asked a friend the other day.
I think I am a good deal like a" little dog tliat I
used to own while at Harvard." said Belmont. "He
wasn't much on the fight, but if another dog tackled
"William Barclay Parsons, Tlie Engineer
him he would get hold f a hind leg and stick. I liad
faith in this thing and I had faith in McDonald. I got
my leg hold, and I hung on
After a few months more of waiting, the
underground railroad will be complete. Today its
success is assured It is acknowledged to be the
greatest financial undertaking and the most remark
able engineering feat in history It is more than a
I'cal achievement. It is national, yes, international,
in its scojie, for it lias revolutionized the rapid
transit problem of the great cities of the world.
In a nutshell, here is
this vast rapid transit
system
Extending from the
Battery at the southern
extremity of Man
hattan island to Bailey
avenue and 230th street
on the west side in a long
sweep of thirteen and a
half miles of four, three
and two tracks, and forty
eight miles of single
track; from 100th street
and Broadway under Cen
tral park, to the eiist,
under the Harlem river to
Bronx park and iSind
street, a distance of seven
miles, or seventeen and a
half miles of single track.
This is the Manhattan division which the contractor
is about to turn over to the oerating comiuny
To Brooklyn another great system is liemg pushed
rapidly toward completion. It leaves the main line
in Manliattnn at the foot of Whitehall street, near
Battery park, and plunging under the East river,
enters Brooklyn at the fool of Joralemnn street,
running with two and three-track systems to Atlantic
avenue, a distance of two and three-tenths miles.
Thus, spreading out from the heart of the metroji
olis. like a gigantic spider-web. are more than sixty
five miles of single tracks, covering a distance of
twenty-five miles of sjiacc to be traveled by 'trains.
Mere figures arc inadequate to express the extent
of this system. Never in the history of the world lias
there lieen such a subway as this. The oldest tunnel
of which mankind lias knowledge was built three
thousand years .-go by a king of Babvlon It ran
under the Euphrates nvcr. connecting the r-vd
palace with the temple of Bel us It was a sh.. -w-hole
in the ground comvired to this great undertaking
of New York. Compared to it the famous catacombs
of Rome are a series of rabbit burrows. In 1S03
when the Simplon tunnel, which pierced under the
Alps and connected Switzerland with Italy was begun
a JPJMTTan MM 1 111 .t -s--r
aaaaaaaaaaEaaaaaaaaaEaaaaaaaaaaaValaaaa Jaaaaaaaai aaaaaaPaaaaaaaaaaaaaHaW- aaaaaaaaaVa aaair
raVAKaaaTaaaaSaaaV .VtL
slVB BAaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaaalalaaaaa
Group of Capitalists, "Whose Combined Rating "Was Estimated at Five Billion Dollars, to Whom Was Accorded the First Trip Through the New
Sub-wax- .Among Those Present Were August Belmont, George Gould. Jacob H. Scruff. Clarence Mac Kay. James Stillman. John D. K.ochefe11er. Jr.,
Andrew Freedman, James Speyer. Valentine Snyder, Perry Ddmont, 'William 11. Moore. Daniel Laroonl, Cornelius Vanderbilt und George Cromwell</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88085947/1904-10-27/ed-1/?sp=1&q=NEW+OPENED+SUBWAY+YORK</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>NEW YORK SUBWAY IS
OPENED BY M'CLELLAN
NEW YORK, Oct. 27.—The Rapid
Transit railroad, the subway, as It
Is popularly known, nnd the most
colossal undertaking of its kind in
the worlds history, whs formally
opened today with imposing cere
saonies. The exercises took place
under the joint auspices of the Inter
borough company and the board of
aldermen. In City Hull park, where
the great downtown terminal is lo
cated and where the first spadeful
of earth was turned, the principal
ceremonies of the day took place
shortly before noon. The park and
citl hall were lavishly decorated.
Bishop Pottter opened the cere
monies with prayer and was followed
by an address by Alexander E. Orr,
president of the rapid transit com
mission, who turned the subway over
to the city. Mayor McClellan accept
ed the tiust, and then turned the road
over to August Belmont, president of
the Interborough company, who also
made a brief address. Archbishop
Farley closed the ceremonies.
At 1 o'clock the first train was
started over the road, operated by
Mayor McClellan in person. Hands
of music were stationed at all the
principal stops along the route. In
cluded among the passengers on the
first train were the city officials, of
ficials of the Interborough company,
a large party of distinguished engi
neers and other invited guests.
Promptly at midnight tonight the
road will be opened to the general
public. That part of the road that
will be operated for the present In-
It is to tight Jeunnot Bros, that
the Spokane Grocers' association has
been Incorporated "to foster a per
manent social feeling" among the
grocers.
The grocers' trust has been making
an illegal tight In using the boycott.
The members knew this and they
knew also that every member of the
trust was liable personally to the
courts for the acts of the organiza
tion.
In order to relieve the Individual
grocers from the fear of being com
pelled to pay damages in ease any
boycotted firm or grocer instituted
suit the trust has been incorporated.
Of the men who are the Incorpor
ators. C F. Blegler runs a trust gro
cery at |MI Second avenue, ft ft.
Andersons trust grocery is at 301
llogan street; P. Nelson offers gro
ceries at trust prices at 01730 Divis
ion street; John Gilford Son have
trust goods for sale ut 1730 liroad
way; Eliza N. t'ory is the secretary
of the association of trust grocers.
It win be noticed that tho big gro
cers arc not showing up in the of
ficial positions of the trust associa
tion. The "little fellows' have been
forced into those dangerous positions.
They will stand personal responsibil
ity, but the big grocers will put up
the money for the trust fights.
As an Incorporated body the trust
grocers nr* not now Individually re
sponslble for the law-breaking meth
ods of the boycott. This is the rea
son the Spokane Grocers' association
was Incorporated.
The Press believes the greedy oc
topus which Is formed to grind still
harder the workingman and his tam
lly should be checked.
W. W. JACOBS, A PLAT
WRIGHT AND HU-
SECOND YEAR. NO. 295. PBICE: ONR CENT.
dudes the whole of the main line
from City Hall park to the Harlem
river on the upper west side. It is
expected to have the entire west side
line opened to- traffic within a month
or so nnd also the east side branch
to the Bronx.
The great subway opened today
consists of It miles of railroad under
the city's teeming streets. The actual
work of construction has taken Just
four years and the cost has exceeded
150.000,000. When the entire system
is completed it will enable one to
travel from the limits of Brooklyn
to the northernmost end of Manhat
tan entirely underground.
A dazzling array of facts and fig
ures tell the story of the building
of the mammoth underground road.
For instance, more than 8,000,000
cubic yards of dirt and rock were
blasted Hnd dug from the streets of
the crowded city. To tear away the
rock voo.ooo pounds of dynamite were
used. Eleven thousand men were em
ployed In the work and of this num
ber several hundred lost their lives
through accidents, premature ex
plosions, cave-Ins und falling rock.
It Is estimated that the road will
carry 115,000,000 passengers a year.
The fare Is 5 cents. When the ex
tension to Brooklyn, under the East
river, has been completed It is esti
mated that the road will carry 200,-
UOO.OOO passt-nxers year.
Express trains will run through
the subway at the rate of a mile a
minute for the benefit of the long
hauls from the Bronx to the busiest
sections of the city below Fourteenth
Englishmen like to laugh as
heartily as their American brothers
when the Joke Is of their kind, and
Jacobs knows how to provide fun i
that is International. He gained his
knowledge of river life and charac
ter on the wharf ut Wapping, where
he spent his leisure hours as a boy.
Mr. Jacobs Is a Londoner born and
bred, and until the last few years
has stuck pretty closely to a city
life. He was educated at private
schools and only live years ago gave
up his appointment in the savings
l»ank department in the general post
office, which he had held since 1883.
lie is 41 years old. but he looks
such a boy, with his clean-shaven
I
face, mm figure end t¥r£si*j»~' tssrt
old ladles In omnibuses still otter
1 hiss ehooolates as to a youth of la,
Mr. Jacobs confesses that he hates to.
work, be put from I
one ceil
street. Local trains will top at all
of the underground stations, every
half dozen blocks along the route.
The tunnel is ventilated by a system
of electric fans and illuminated the
entire route by In candescent lights.
A trip through the greet tunnel is
all that is necessary to convince one
of its entire security. White enamel'
ed bricks wall up the sides to a
bricked arch overhead. Everything
else is of stone and steel, and heavy
plate glass at the stations to let the
light In from the street overhead. It
would seem impossible for a disaster
to occur where everything Is as new
nnd strong and perfect, apparently,
as It is within the power of man to
contrive. The pneumatic block sys
tem Is pronounced by experts to be
the most wonderful thing of its kind
In the world and it Is calculated to
make collisions Impossible.
The cars have steel bottoms, cop
per sheathed sides, and there is very
little wood in their construction. The
lighting system Is entirely separate
from the power plant that will move
the trains by means of the third rail.
The route of the main line is up
Fourth avenue to Forty-second street,
then up Broadway until One Hundred
and Fourth street Is reached. There
is branches into two sections. The
first continues straight out Broad
way to Kingsbrldge, a distance of
more than 14 miles from Battery
park.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87060004/1905-01-19/ed-1/?sp=4&q=BOSTON+Boston+SUBWAY+subway</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>ANOTHER BOSTON SUBWAY
Eat Ilpnlon Tunnel Junt Openti
IllliiM Under Itnrbor
Boston the pioneer city of America
In subway construction now boasts a
subway Maid to be the greatest single
boring yet completed under the enter
of a river or harbor It Is tho EnSt
Boston tiinnl extending from tile
zing UA8T JtOSTON TUNNEL
city proper under the harbor to
Maverick square East Boston It Is
the second subway to be opened In
Boston wns begun In 1000 has cost
3000000 and has Just been turned
over to tint Boston EIu rated Rallwny
company for operation It Id about
one ones twofifth miles In length and
has an exterior diameter of nearly
thirty feet thoilgli the thickness of
the walls bring Its Interior diameter
down to about twentyfour feet
The East Boston tunnel nets to n
depth of more than ninety feet below
tho waters of Boston harbor through
n blue day sediment It Is fov the
use of regulntlpn trolley cars which
come to the surface at the suburban
end of tilt passage nnd continue their
Journeys over tliestrce trucks Kven
trashy the tuba Vlll be connected di
rectly with the present Ruiwny In Ba
tons congested dlflUlct</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84023296/1906-06-09/ed-1/?sp=1&q=bomb+Bomb+Boston+explosions+FIRE+subway</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>FIRE IN SUBWAY.
Lives Impcrilled in Boslon's
Underground Railway.
Terrlflc Exploslona Caused by 8hort
Clrcultlng of Heavlly Charoea uiec
trlc vyirea Hundreds of Men and
Women Thrown Into Panlc Three
Persons Injured.
Boston A dull, low ronr, llko tho
blast of n chnrge of dynnmlte under
tona of grnnlte, nnd clouda ot black,
Blckenlng smoko belchlng fortli,
threw hundreds of men nnd women
into a panic nnd paralyzed trnfflc ln
the subwny nt the Boylston street
statlon at 5.30 o'clock, Wednesday af-
ternqpn
No one know the trouble. Elevatcd
road employes and offlclals were allke
confused, and fearful of what mlght
come next, fla tho smoko raphlly fllleil
tho stntloim at Boylston and Park
streets, nnd passengers wers rushed
from tlie cars to the surfacc.
Tralnmen nnd statlon pollce at
tempted to call the flrd departmont
and found tho telephones so charged
wlth clectrlclty as to be useless.
Mnny of the women reachlng the
subway by the Boylston street cars
were overcomo by the smoko, falnted,
nnd had to be dragged to the surfnce.
Several becanio hysterlcal and woro
controlled wlth much dimculty, the
danger belng constant of Bomeono
falllng from tho platforms overcome
by tho smoko and becomlng electro
cuted upon the deadly thlrd rall.
Tralnmaster Benjamln wns the flrst
offlclal to reach the Boylston street
statlon and to brlng some sort of or-
der out of tho cliaos. Enterlng the
subway along the llne of the north
bound cars he made hla way some 100
feet to the south of tlie statlon and
found the cause of the trouble.
The feed cables for the thlrd rall,
runnlng between the ralla and en
closed ln four-inch wooden box con
dults, were found grouuded and
throwlng off flashes of electrlclty,
whlch llluminnted the subway for
tnany hundreds of feet. The electrl
clty had jumped to other cables run
nlng parallel, and even charged the
wnlla of the subway. Ten powerful
cables felt the lnftuence of the crosn
nnd were cracklng nnd throwlng off
flames and flashes of llght, threaten
Ing death to any who cnme near.
Tho wooden box condtilt, black and
greasy and very Inflammable, was
burnlng rapldly. A north bound traln
whlch had passed over the spot got
nflro nnd wna inillod bnnk lo Waont
street, hlnzlng flercely underneath.
Tlie terrlfled passengers were hnnied
ntt nt Plpnsnnt Rtreet nnd tlie flro be-
nnivth tho. Kttn"gulshed by'road
employes before serlous damage was
done.
Three persons were hurt, nnd all of
them were on the surface. The nccl
dents whlch caused thelr Injurles were
the dlrect result of the trouble In tbo
subway. The Injured wero all near
the Pleasant street entrance to tho
Biibwny and were hurt by the explo
sions in three mnnholes at tliat polnt.
Tralnmaster Benjamln ordered all
tralns Into statlons, and then the cnr-
rent on the thlrd rall and feed cables
was shut off.
Chlef Mullcn and the flre depart
ment hod been notlfled before tho
power was shut off and entered tho
nubway nt the Boylston street sta
tlon, although there was great danger
for anyone, however famlllar ylth the
subway, to enter ln tlie dense smoke
whlch flllcd every foot of space be
tween the walls.
As Chlef Mullen's men toucbed the
walls thoy felt a shock at once. The
brass nozzle of the chemlcal hose
Ihey carrled became charged, and wlth
electrlclty runnlng up thelr arms the
men hcsltated for a mlnute for orders
from thelr chlef.
rlsk It," shouted Chlef Mull
en, and he dashed Into the smoko
filled subway. Hla men followed close
behlnd, thelr hands on the shoulders
of the men In front. A few darlng
newspaper men brought up the rear.
Half an hour was consumed ln put
llng out the flames whlch had fol
lowed nlong the box condults nearly
300 ynrds.
Both Chlef Mullen and Aaslstant
Chlef Brady termed It one of the
most dangerous flres they were ever
called upon to hnndle, not from lts In
tenslty but for the dangers of electro
cutlon that surrounded them and the
thlckness of the smoke.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84020358/1897-02-11/ed-1/seq-5/#date1=1756&index=1&rows=20&words=Boston+BOSTON+SUBWAY+subway</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>BOSTON'S FAMOUS SUBWAY
CHIEF EXUlXliKK CAHSOX 3BI.IS
HOW IT IS COXSTIIVC1HD,
Lecture Before Engineers' Club Feature
of the Kuglnoeiiiig Work on the Subway
Subways In Other Cities.
An exceedingly Interesting and valu
able lecture was given last evening In
North Sheffield hall by Howard A. Car
son, member of the American Society
of Civil Engineers and chief engineer
of the famous Boston subway. The
lecture was given, under the auspic&i
of the Engineers' club and was largelj
attended by citizens as well as stu
dents. Professor DuBols Introduced Mr. Car
son, who spoke on "Subways in Bos
ton, London and Elsewhere." The lec
ture was illustrated by stereopticon
views of the Boston subway and also
of some of the European subways
which Mr. Carson has visited.
The lecturer at the commencement
explained why the Boston subway was
built. "The DODulatlon of Boston 130
years ago was less than 22,000; 100 years
ao about 26,000; In 1830, in the remem
brance of many, about 82,000, while to
day the city has about 600,000. The
population of Boston doubles In about
thirty-five years.
"The use o the streets for travel In
creases faster In proportion than the
population of the city. In 1896 167,000,000
persona were carried by the street rail
ways. While the population doubles
only in twenty-flve years, travel on the
street railways doubles In about ten
years.
"The streets are no wider now than
they were one hundred years ago, and
they are not able to do the work they
are needed to do. If streets can't do
the work required of them the natural
thing to do is to build them wider or
make new streets, but the cost is too
great for this, costing perhaps $100 a
foot. If you can't Wld or.broaden the
old streets you must do the way a per
son does when a house la overcrowded
and has not land to build new by add
ing stories to the old. In the case of a
street you have to decide between an
elevatedway or a subway.
"The mere cost of erecting an elevat
ed road is only about one-half or one
third of that of a eubway, but the dam
age which has to be paid to adjacent
property owners makes the cost of the
two systems about the same. As to the
convenience and comfort of the two
methods, different persons are likely to
hold different views."
Mr. Carson then explained an elevat
ed road which Is being constructed in
Germany, where the cars are suspended
from the track Instead of running on
the raila. '
"The Boston subway is being built
under some of the most traveled streets
of the city. . For most of the distance it
is to have two tracks, but at points
there are four tracks where the cars
can run back without naming to the
end of the line. At the northern termi
nus there is an incline where the cars
i can come to the surface. Stations for
passengers are placed at convenient
distances, usually one In about 1,000
feet.
"The retaining walls of the subway
are of granite and concrete, mostly of
concrete. There are two forms of con
struction employed in the roof, one
made of steel and concrete and the oth
er the brick arch. . .
"The subway is about twenty-four
feet in width at the Incline, where there
are two tracks, and about sixteen feet
high. In the middle of the subway is a
drain, the side wa!! of which, are of
brick with open Joints, so that thfe wa
ter can eaeily find its way Into It, and
the top is covered over with flags eas
ily removed if the drain needs inspec
tion or repair.
"At the passenger stations there are
two stairways, each fifteen feet In
width. It was not Intended at first to
use elevators at all, but It may be
thought desirable to adopt them at
some stations later on.
'In the work of construction many
pipes were encountered which had to
be removed or passed under. The work
is being so performed as to cause the
least possible hindrance to travel on
the streets. In the daytime one-third
of the street is occupied for the. plant
and material used for the work, and
the other two-thirds Is left for travel.
At night about two-thirds of the street
is occupied in the work.
'Bridges are built over the excava
tions on a level with the street, so that
one passing over them will hardly no
tice the fact. The work Is done by
what is known as the slice method, by
which ten or a dozen sections are being
excavated at the same time, no two be
ing adjoining.
'There are eight fans placed at ap
propriate Intervals to ventilate the tun
nel, each fan being seven feet in diam
eter. It was feared by some that the
excavations would weaken the founda
tions of some of the high buildings, but
the work has so far advanced now that
there is seen to be no danger."
Mr. Carson olosed his lecture with a
rapid description of subways in Buda
pest, Paris, London and Glasgow, and
also a description of the use of the
shield In tunnelling.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84020274/1904-05-08/ed-1/seq-58/#date1=1756&index=2&rows=20&words=Boston+Subway</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>SUNDAY MAGAZINE for MAY 8, 1904
fT . .. i WIWm .... -.- i, iQHHttHHHttrrr ,-.. - ' -:-:.: 1
rWtTH vHC MH
V Hit
Vk-l- S.
rr4r.Eiiiii!tisi
Hif
sm;
rBH
irvrja V-r r
sS&SfcP?
.? " 5T --'- -rvPBP
SS5M???!rfS
3ftZLtCCiCTairiiSrJ
?.-? ifTrt J,iir"
KKi-v5I
i-.'r- T ws.&.is-v y
In This Hole the Subway Intersects the
Cellar of a SKyscraper Since Erected
it was accounted the greatest engineering
wonder of the orld Yet if one could add
the famou St. (loth in! tunnel to the
Simplon, and to them the Mount Cenis
tunnel and then splice on the Like
Fucino tunnel for good measure thus
uniting the four longest tunnels on our
planet he -would liarc the length of the
underground railways of Xew York.
Or, let us take the longest tunnels and
subways in America:
Baltimore and Ohio tunnel 7 miles
Hoosac 'tunnel 4 34 miles
Boston subw r '- 2 12 miles
Cascade tunnel 2 12 miles
Bowlder tunnel 2 miles
Ivanhoe tunnel 2 miles
Sarma tunnel 1 mile
Total 21 34 miles
The combined lengths of these seven great tunnels
is a mile short of the total length of the Manhattan
and Brooklyn divisions of the Xew York subway.
The largest single contract in the history of civili
zation was entered into for the purpose of constructing
this wonderful system of transportation. When it is
known that 1.700,22s cubic yards of earth and 021, 1S2
cubic yards of rock have Ix-en excavated, 36S,6o6
cubic yards of rock tunneled, ijo.oSS tons of steel,
ij.Soj tons of cast iron and 1S.510 cubic yards of
bnck used in the work, to say nothing of the hundreds
and hundreds of thousands of cubic yards of water
proofing and concrete and stone anil the 300,000
linear feet of steel tracks and the hundreds of thousands
of tons of other material one realizes that a vast
undertaking lias lecn in progress. But its very vast
ness makes it incomprehensible.
If we took the earth and the rock that came from
this appalling bole in the ground and loaded them into
carts stretched out in a straight line, 'we should have a
procession reaching from Xew York to San Fran
cisco and back again by the way of Xew
Orleans a distance of 7.573 miles.
Che difficulties of the work have lccn
unparalleled. The authorities say that it
is the most remarkable engineering feat
on record Fifteen miles of sewers had to
be taken up and relaid many of them
almost as big as the subway itself. There
were miles and miles of gas mains and
water pijcs and conduits that twined them
selves in and out and crossed and re
crossed the path of the underground rail
way like a labyrinth. There were elevated
railways and surface railways that had to
be undermined, but so bolstered up by arti
ficial construction that the daily transpor
tation and traffic of the great city was not
disturbed. Blocksand blocks of busy Broad
way in the upper part of the city were hol
lowed out like a flute. Tunnels were fear
lessly bored under lower Broadway, reaching
almost to the very foundations of the big
skyscrapers and brushing against the walls
of Trinity church, while above the rumble of
the electric cars and the rattle cf the carts
never ceased. It costs twenty thousand dollars to con
struct an average mile of steam railroad It cost a mil
lion dollars a mile to dig out and blast out this subway.
But despite the cost and despite the mechanical difficul-
vHBHf
Engineers Solving o Sewer Problem
ties the first great part of the work has been finished.
Yet it is only the beginning of the underground
railroad system of Xew York. .Under the supervision
of the rapid transit commissioners three other mam
moth underground projects are lieing carried forward.
One is the tunnel of the Pennsylvania railroad, which
is to extend from Weehawken, Xew Jersey, under
the Hudson river, below- the surface of Manhattan
along 31st, 32nd and 33rd streets, and under the East
river to Long Island City on Long island, a distance
of four and one-fifth miles, and a total length of main
tracks of twenty-two and one-fifth miles.
A few weeks ago a tunnel under the Hudson river
begun as far back as 1S74 connecting Holxjken,
Xew Jersey, with Xew York, was completed by the
LfOinigjesft Tuurainiels ir& ftUae Worlr3
Xew York Rapid Transit 22 45 miles
Metropolitan Underground. I-onilcm 13 miles
Simplon, Switzerland 12 miles
St. Gothard. Switzerland 9 14 miles
Paris Underground - :..S 12 miles
Mont Cents. 'Switzerland .....7 12 miles
Baltimore, B. & O ...7 miles
Arlburg. Austria 6 miles
"Tup-penny Tube." London . 3 34 miles
Hoosac. Massachusetts ".. 4 34 miles
Berlin Underground 4 12 miles
Liverpool and Birkenhead.- 4 12 miles
Boston Subway 2 12 miles
Cascade. Great Northern Railroad 2 12 miles
Xew York Central '. 2 miles
Budapest, Austria 2 miles
Bowlder. Montana 2 miles
Ivanhoe, Colorado 2 miles
Sarnia, Canada 1 mile
Xew York & Jersey Railroad Company. It has a
length of one and three-quarters miles and runs from
the ferry in Hoboken to Eighth avenue and West toth
street in Xew York. By July. 1905, it will be fully sfor a system that is astounding in its possibilities.
Whero Elevated. Surface and Subway
Lines Cross
equipped with electric trains on the same
plan as that adopted by the underground
railroad.
Work has been already legun by the
Hudson & Manhattan Railroad Company
(the members of which are practically the
same men who compose the Xew York &
Jersey Railroad Company) on a tunnel
which is to run under the Hudson river
from Courtlandt and Church streets, Xew
York, to the Pennsylvania, Jersey Central
and the Erie railway stations in Jersey City.
It will also connect with the Xew York sub
way at Dey street and Broadway. It will
have a length of one and one-lialf miles, and
will be equipped with electric trains which will
be running in three vcars. Both these tunnels
to the Xew Jersey shore are to have twin tules
one tor cacti track. 1 lie trains that arc to he
operated through them will connect with the railroads
of X'ew Jersey.
In a few months the underground terminal facilities
of the X'ew York Central & Hudson River railroad
will be completed. Direct connection will be made
with all the outlying towns within a radius of one
hundred miles, to the Grand Union station on 42nd
street, by means of electric trains.
Thus, with all these roads stretching out into the
country in every direction, a new stream of suburban
transportation will Ixs opened.
"In the next ten years I expect to sec Xew York
honeycombed with great tunnel lines," said John B.
McDonald, the subway contractor. ".The tunnels to
Washington heights and Kings Bridge and The Bronx,
the tunnel to Brooklyn, the tunnel from Weehawken
across Manhattan to Long Island City, the tunnel from
Hoboken, and the tunnel from Jersey City are the
merest beginning. I believe tint within a few years
it will be possible to go between any two points in
the greater city by the underground system."
"I have plans forspending one hundred million dollars
in extending rapid transit facilities in
Greater Xew York within the near future."
said William Barclay Parsons, the chief
engineer of the rapid transit railroad
commissioners. "Even this great sum will
not provide for adequate accommodation
for the rapidly increasing transportation
The entire Manhattan elevated system lias,
on extra occasions, carried as many as nine
hundred thousand passengers a day. In
round numlers it will average for a year
two hundred and forty millions. The
underground will carry more than that; but
with all the increase in facilities we shall
fall short of what we ought to do. This
is based on the calculation that Xew York
is increasing in population at the rate of
two hundred thousand a year, and that
every man, woman and child averages four
hundred and fifteen street car trips annually.
According to these figures the city's popula
tion will have increased by one million
in five years, and the additional fares to
be handled bv the transportation com
panies will be four hundred and fifteen
millions annually."
So this subway great work that it is is only
the beginning; but it has opened the wav</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86086481/1902-08-31/ed-1/seq-14/#date1=1756&index=4&rows=20&words=Boston+subway</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>ANSWERED
Mr. Gaston and Mr. Hamlin Tell
How They Stand in Relation to
Subway and Franchise Regu
lations
REPLIES SENT TO
PUBLIC FRANCHISE LEAGUE
Each Takes up the Questions
Propounded and Defines Terse
ly What His Attitude Is To
ward Each Proposition That
League Submitted
In view of the contests in the Legis
lature during the past three years over
subway legislation, and the importance
of franchise questions as issued in the
coming state campaign, the Public
Franchise League of Boston recently
asked each of the candidates for the
Democratic nomination for governor to
define his position in relation to them.
Identical questions were propounded to
both candidates. Replies as given be
low have been received from both Mr.
Hamlin and Mr. Gaston.
The following Is the letter to Mr. Gas
ton:
"Boston. Mass., Aug. 16, 1902.
“William A. Gaston. Esq..
"Dear Sir: —In your letter, yesterday
made public, announcing your candida
cy for the Democratic nomination for
governor of Massachusetts, you say you
"believe that the people are entitled to
a statement of my (your) views on mat
ters which may be at issue in the cam
paign.’’
"Among the important issues in this
year’s state campaign are those of pub
lic franchises, public control of public
service corporations, the prevention of
the improper influencing of legislation
on the part of corporations by the dis
tribution of patronage in the form of
employment at the solicitation of mem
bers of the Legislature, and municipal
and town governments.
"Accordingly in response to your
statement, the Public Franchise League
respectfully invites you to define your
position on the following questions:
“1. Until the passage of the Boston
subway bills it has been customary in
this commonwealth to grant franchises
for the use of streets and public lands
to public service corporations, for the
purpose of supplying public utilities like
gas, electricity, water and transporta- ;
tion. without requiring any compensa
tion to bp paid to towns and munici
palities for the use of such public prop
erty.
“Wp ask. therefore, are you in favor
of following in the future the precedent
of the Boston subway bills and requir
ing equitable compensation for the use
of the public ways by all public ser
vice corporations?
“2. When franchises are granted to
corporations, without requiring pay
ment in money for the use of public
streets and property, with the expecta
tion that compensation \vill be paid in
lower fares, diminished cost of util
ity or improved service, as the case may
be, this end has b?ea defeated in that
almost all great public service corpora
tions in thp country capitalized these
privileges either by an increase of cap
ital stock nr by absorption of the cor
poration into new and greater combi
nations of capital. Thus the public has
been obliged to pay interest on the
value of franchise rights which were a
free gift intended for the benefit of the
people.
“We ask. therefore, are you in favor
of forbidding the capitalization of the
value of public franchises under what
ever guise it is sought to be brought
about?
“3. When public franchises are
granted irrevocable or leased for long
terms to corporations which are creat
ed to administer the public utilities for
the public benefit, these corporations
become independent to a very great
extent of public control. Thus, among
other evils, the public utility or service
tends to become inadequate or exces
sively costly to the user.
"We ask. therefore, whether (a) you
favor making, when feasible, all fran
chises revocable, and (b) whether you
favor short term leases when fran
chises are granted for a term of years.
“4. We call your attention to the fact
that one* of the baneful ways in which
corporations influence legislation is by
distribution of patronage in the form
of employment in the service of the
corporations. Thus the spoils system
has been transferred from the service
of the state and municipality to the
service of the great public service cor
porations.
"We ask, therefore, whether if elect
ed'you would favor prohibiting by law
the appointment to service by public
service corporations, at the solicitation
of members of municipal, town and
state governments, and also the solicit
ing of such employment by members of
such governments.
“5. One of the most efficient ways of
retaining a check by the people upon
their representatives in the Legisla
ture and restraining the power of the
corporations is through the referendum.
This is only the retention of the prin
ciple of town government.
"We ask. therefore, whether you are
in favor of the referendum in important
measures that grant valuable rights to
. I
Spencer Trask & Co*
Members New York Stock Exchange
BANKERS.
27 a 29 Pine St., New York.
INSURANCE
STATE MUTUAL LIFE
ASSURANCE COMPANY
OF WORCESTER
Insurance tn force Jan. 1,1902.487.424,149.00
Assets Jan. 1, 1902 19.553.009.71
Liabilities Jan 1. ISO 2 17,582.954.49
Surplus Jan. 1. 1902 2.021.552.22
Telephone 655-3
WORCESTER MUTUAL FIRE INSURANCE
COMPANY, No. 377 Main Street, insures
Dwellings. Barns. Furniture, etc. Procure
policy direct or ask your j^surau'.e agent or
broker for a "Worcester" policy.
FIRE INSURANCE written on furniture
dwellings, stocks and buildings. James
H. Howland. 717 State Mutual Building.
Telephone 295-5.
individuals or corporations specially
when such grants affect local inter
ests. Very respectfully,
"PUBLIC FRANCHISE LEAGUE,
(Signed) "Edward R. Warren.
"Chairman Executive Committee.
(Signed) "Morton Prince.
"Secretary.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045396/1913-04-06/ed-1/seq-51/#date1=1756&index=7&rows=20&words=Boston+subway+subways</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>W THE SALT LAK15 TltiBUNlO, SUNJJAr MOJ&S L Of, APJAIL 6, 1913, w
htfic Experiments fVMWl MmWMW II
. temperature the I
4 i- 37 JL fpf? The Air Taken in Mid-Ocean Con- The Near Presence of Factories Air Taken at Broadway and For- Even New York Subway Air, fgi
& 'IfnnlttHflt faCtOrS pSt SnH tL pIJ1 Laine& .Mo,re O'S0 and Lesa Car- Produced No Appreciable Contami- ty-tecond Street, New York, Showed Taken in the Rush Hours, Showed ifj!
1 IJlipUS lU1- JL UtW a oSvOn bon Dioxide Than Any Other Air, nation Because of the Rapid DifFu- Only One-tenth of One Per Cent Leas No Decrease of Oxygen That Would jg'
It ' m yn nil Sxf v0o fe C??4 but Stm Not Sufficient to Hare an sivo Power of the Air. Oxygen Than Ocean Air. Cause Illness by Itself Alone. ffift,
. More Oxygen Than N. Y. Subway Air Important Effect on Life. -Si i
rjg, ordinary conceptions or the bud
A jjg of city air and the goodness
J of seashore and mountain air Lave
jjjn completely upset by science. A
x-j0&shy interesting series of experi
ments on the composition of air just com
;i&d at the Nutrition laboratory of the
&rnsgie Institution in Boston proves tills.
Wfat ma&7 J 11 11118 DQen helloved
lit even a slight change in altitude made
t pt deal of difference in the air we
feflie, and there are few people who
wnot supposed that the air in a crowd
'ii'dtr jimn and on the peak of a moun
would bo widely different, the latter
'jjng vastly more of the llfe-glvlne
Jjjgen iian the former. But an extended
litigation by the scientists of the Car
I jigie Institution shows that there Is no
MWt amount of difference between the
1'jfoporllon of oxygen and nitrogen In sam
I jfes of air collected on the Atlantic Ocean,
Kjotha top of Pike's Peak, in the crowded
I; (treete of congested Boston and in the
'Spleasant New York City Bubway.
I. Air in the streets of a crowded city
Bless for some occasional Teason there la
rfciroeljr any alr-ourrent shows only the
JEjMest perceptible difference In oxygen
Jldo from that of the- ocean or of the
Boualain, In rooms, of course, and In
doeed passages such as the subways,
fee is a slightly, a very slightly larger
'dunge. During the "rush" hour of a New
Jerk City subway, the air (outside the car,
rfcourBB), shows a fall of three-tenths of
Lbs per cent in oxygen and a rise of al
pittt exactly the same amount of poison
ftt carbon dioxide. This, so far bb health
i considered, Is practically negligible,
f The air on Pike's Peak contained only
ktefrfortieth of one per cent more oxygen
ifljn the subway,
i
t The experiments at the laboratory were
fkrrled out by Director Francis G. Bene
ijlcl and his assistants. The work in
' I The main study of the comparative
OTgen content of uncontaminated out
lioor air under all conditions as to wind
tlilrecllon and strength, temperature, cloud
formation, barometer and weather, includ
es rain, enow, fog and mist.
2. An examination of samples of air
collected on the North Atlantic Ooean be-
treen Montreal and Liverpool and between
jflsaoa and Boston.
3. Anaylses of air from the top of
'"Pitta Peat,
'J L Analyses of air taken in the crowded
itfreela of Boston.
6. Analyses of air taken in the Boston
Cua New York subways,
ae moEt numerous analyses wero
?5?JL BamPle of air taken near the
f.H Laboratory in Boston. The fao
W aJBtrlot lay on one side of the labora
liv a PDWerhouse on another side,
1.W0 feet away, in order to make nllow
Pfcvf! J?.r tileae factors samples were
fcptr wind in all directions-.
Tlie results showed an astonishingly
small variation In the deterioration of tho
air by carbon dioxide. With the wind blow
ing from the country the air contained
20.920 per cent oxygen, and 0.029 per cent
carbon dioxide. "With the wind from tho
factory district It was 20.910 per cen(
oxygen aud 0.030 per cent carbon dioxide,
The results of analyses of air taken
near the laboratory showed no material
fluctuation In oxygen percentage during
a period extending from April 15, 1911, to
January 80, 1912. This constancy was
maintained in spite of all possible altera
tions in weather conditions, changes in
barometer, thermometer, humidity and
wind direction and strength. The experi
ments wore made before, during and after
the vegetative season.
The average result of 232 analyses
showed 0.031 per cent of carbon dioxide
and 20.938 per cent of oxygen. The analy
aes of air oollocted over the ocean at two
different times of the year and on tho top
of Pike's Peak gave essentially similar
results.
The investigators reacbed this very
Important conclusion from tho air around
the laboratory:
"SVhtle the combustion of fuel and the
vital processes of men and animals result
In a looal increase In oarbon dioxide, and
decrease in oxygen on tho one hand and
vegetable growth Tosults In a decrease in
carbon dioxide and increase In oxygen on
the other, the extraordinary rapidity with
which tho local variations hi the compo
sition of the air are equalized hvaecentu
ated by the observations on street air,
which show but the slightest trace of an
oxygen deficit in the most crowded cen
tres."
Five samples of air wore gathered, all
the way across the Atlantlo Ocean from I
Montreal to Liverpool. Tho results showed
an average of 20.936 per cent oxygen and
0.018 per cent carbon dioxide.
Tho oxygon oontent In this case Is re
markably high and the carbon dioxide
content correspondingly low. In one sam
ple thore was only 0.008 of oarbon dioxide
in the air.
Fifteen samples of air from the top a!
Pike's Peak wero analyzed. They showed
that there was less oxygen In tho air than
at sea and more carbon dioxide, but the
differences were not sufficient to have an
important effect on life. The explanation
of the effoctB of sea and mountain air on
persons must bo sought elsewhere than in
the composition of the air.
The Pike's Peak air showed an average
of 20.927 per cent oxygen and 0.029 car
bon dioxide.
Two samples of air were taken from
the Boston subway at the Park street sta
tion, The samples wore taken immediate
ly after the rush hours were ended and
when the oxygen content of the air in the
subway might he expected to be at a mini
mum. , ,,
Tho result showed an extraordinarily
fe$uV j00&; rW0$fr
rs- i k
slight decrease in oxygen ana lucrease in
carbon dioxide. A fall of approximately
0.03 per cent In oxygon was accompanied
by a rlso of 0.032 per cent in tho carbon
dioxide. Tho proportions of tho two gases
were:
ipptfi ymlmm
The Man on the Left Taking tho Mountain Fresh
Air Cure Is Benefited Chiefly by the Effects of tho
Cold, Wind and Sunshine on His Body and Not by
the Air. He Could Obtain the Same Benefits by
Climbing Up the Fire-Escapes of the New York
Tenement nouse on the Right.
First sample, carbon dioxide, 0.06-1 per
court; oxygen, 20.903 per cent.
Second sample, carbon dioxide. 0.0G5
per cent; oxygon, 20.897 per cent
It should bo remembered that tho aver
age composition of the air near tho labora
tory was carbon dioxide, 0.031; oxygen,
20.952 per cent.
Tho investigators wore surprised to
find ho circulation of air In the subway
so good and the diffusive power of the air
bo extended that the Inoreaso In the
amount of poisonous gas was almost
negligible.
Two specimens of air were
then obtained from the subway
In New York. The results dif
fered in nowlBo from those
found in the Boston subway, and
showed an Increase 'In carbon
dioxide and .decrease In oxygen
much less than ono would have
expected. The results in this
case were as follows:
First sample, taken at Grand
Central subway station, carbon
dioxide, 0.061 per cent.; oxygen,
20.000 per cent.
Second sample, taken between
One Hundred and Tenth and
Ninety-Blxth streets, carbon diox
ide, 0.071 per cent; oxygen,
20.087 per cent
This appears to Indicate that
the air is somewhat worse above
Ninety-sixth street than at the
Grand Central station, but the
difference is not very serious.
The Investigators state that
their experiments have a par
ticular value aa showing that a
decrease In oxygen 13 regularly
accompanied by an approximate
increase In carbon dioxide.
"While the measurement of
carbon dioxide has been taken aa
an index of good or bad ventila
tion, the fact that the proportion
of oxygen 1b actually lowered by
an increase in the carbon dioxide
hnp never been before demon
strated," any these scientists.
"As a result of this 6tudj', how
ever, Wcnowlng both the constancy
of oxygen In outdoor air aud the
sources of carbon dioxide produc
tion, and knowing also that with
the carbon dloxldo production
there must likewise be an oxygen
consumption, wo can safely stato
that for every one-hundredth per
cent, of increase in carbou diox
ide there will be approximately
one-hundredth por cent decrease
in oxygen."
Air collected in Washington
street, between Summer and Avon
streets, the most crowded part
of Boston, showed 20.030 of oxy
gen and 0.031 of carbon dioxide.
Information gathered from other scien
tists showed ttiat tho air was slightly
richer In oxygen near the poleB than at
tho equntor. The ordinary air on the
earth's surface contains approximately
four-fifths nitrogon and one-flfth oxygon.
The rarer gases, such as argon and kryp
ton, are disregarded in this estimate, be
cause thero Is so littlo of them.
As oxygen is heavier than nitrogen, it
is believed that there is a deficiency of
oxygen at great heights. This is supported
by the fact that tho air during several cold
waves shows a deficiency of oxygen. These
waves are supposed to bo caused by the
descent of the air from great elevations.
The apparatus used was invented by Dr. l
Klas Spnden, of Stockholm, and an lm- jffiftf
proved form of it was specially con- ',fvt
etructed for this laboratory, in this ap- . if5
paratus potassium pyrogallato is used 'um
to absorb the oxygen, and potassium hy- .
droxlde to absorb the carbon dioxide. After ft Jt
'the carbon dioxlile is absorbed tho con- jj i
trnction in volume shows the proportion ImJ
of that substance in the air, then the - C ft
oxygen is absorbed and the further con- $ S
traction in volume is measured and shows ft It
the amount of that substance in the air. .j ft
One Important lesson taught by the ex- f.
perlmonts was the extraordinary rapidity L U
with which -the air diffuses Itself in the 91
neighborhood of factories which pour out ,"' 1
all day long clouds of .poisonous vapors. j;
The comparative density of the Bmoke and y
air being different, violent air-currents are 'fffl
set up about the mouth of the chimney and
then rapidly scatter the fumes and render J'kEi
them as harmless as possible. It is almost j4tc
impossible under ordinary weather condi- 4
tlona to find any appreciable change In ''hN
the air content at a distance of half a mile 'i,
from these centres of harmfulness. " '-'.Wi
When It is realized that oxygen Is the ' ".iSj
most important factor In human life, it is
a matter for extreme gratification to find fj
that bo little danger accrues from over- ft
crowding In tho citlos. It is made evident ' "fc'ff
that the ill conditions of city slums are C) M
not due so much to the bad air in the ' S flj
streets, but to tho actual ventilation of the Y'W
homes, to the lack of sunlight, and to food '$31
which lacks the right powers of nourish- h
ment These are matters that tenement WOfti
laws can reach, and Nature will take care "H'W
of tho rest. Not only is air a "good mixer," I'i't" "
but its adaptability ensures this side of the Hi' ft1
well-being of man, all over the globe, and ":;U )-st)
even the crowded city quarter receives the Vs' Aji
benefit.
It Is known that the amounts of carbon $ -'If
dioxldo shown by these experiments to b '"ST
present in tho air of the most crowded ll" jpl
city streets and even In the subways are 1
not sufficient to bo injurious to human V H
life. -; "( if:
To what then are we to attribute the V M
feeble health we find in city dwellers as ',v,ij
compared with those who live In the coun- '!T'" s
try and are equally well fed? How are we
to explain the great benefits that are Bhown
when a person goes from tho city to the T J
seashore or tho mountains?
The explanation that tho city dweller's ffiiff
trouble is due lo working In a sunless, '
overheated, evenly wanned and windless ' fh,
building. If ho wero continuously exposed ','-vJ.
to the city air ho would bo almost as well - ,iH '"-
as at tho mountains or the seashore. ,V
In Illustration of this it is pointed out IVi
that policemen and others who lead an
open air life in the citlos are fully as ro- 'i'jfTj
bust as any class of country men. fX J,!
Theso facts are encouraging to the city ' m I
worker who suffers from tuberculosis-, ' K'll
anaemia or any of tho diseases associated ? o
with city life and sedentary occupation. III
They appear to prove that he can obtain ' j(
relief if he can get enough open air In ,r$ i
the city and that thero is no need for f
him to abandon his livelihood and face i t
starvation by going away to some diHtant I y
part of tho world in order to get fresh air. '.!'L?j J. ,
The roofs of our most crowded tene- frf; '
ment houses should furnish a health re- ;L'!
soi't practically as beneficial aB the f'foii1
Adlrondncks or the ueashore. J i</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83007465/1906-08-11/ed-1/seq-7/#date1=1756&index=11&rows=20&words=Boston+Subway</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>In this house the poet, wrote
most ol his gems, among them,"
"The Children's Hour." In this
poem occur these lines:
"Fiona my study I seo in the lamplight
Descending the brond hull stair
<lrave Alice and laughing Allegro
And Edith with golden hair."
"Crave Alice, still unmarried,
owns and occupies tho house and
on either side of her now live,
Allegra, now Mrs Dana and
Edith, now Mrs. Thorpe.
The Tonmine Hotel, Public
Library, Trinity, the church ol
Phillips Brooks, the Art Museum
and Boston Conservatory of Music
aro some of the fine public
uildings of Boston. Boston's
Subway cars honey comb the
city. Surface and elevated cars
are also in evidence. Boston is
' not the rampant negro loving,
South hating hot bed L exn?rtn#i
to find it. The people are more
like Southern people than New
Yorkers or PhiladelnhianR. The
streets are narrow and crooked
but full of people hurrying here
and there and everywhere. </text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-early-electric-cars</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88064454/1891-10-31/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Carriage+carriage+electric+Electric</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Building an Electric C'arriage.
A novelty among vehlieles in this
country, an electric carriage, is now
beinig conistrucllted at the faet'rv of
IM. W. Qutinlan, in Brookline. Mass.,
front plans drawn front a photograph
of a similar carriage in nresent use in
London. The battery contains thirty.
two cells,aoid is jplaced in the rear end
of the body of 4ileo carriage. The
motor, which is of foreign manutfao
ture, rests between the hitd springs,
where it is attached to the body by
two hinge clasps in such a manner as
to allow it to swing when the motion
of the carriage is irregular, although
this swing is regulated by a connect
ing rod. The driving shfts of the
miotor extetd on eithcir side ibeyond
lthe sprinigs, and are fitted wilh cog
wheel attachittents which coninect by
atln endless chlati with larger cogwheels
on the inner side of the rear wheels.
Thie steering apparatus is on the left
side of the carriage platform. In case
of accildent to the amotor, shafts can be
litted to the c:u'riage, and horses at.
tached. When comnileted, tie whole
carriage will weighl about 2500
pouttds. All tlhe electrical work is
tlone by the loltiier-Cabot Cotl,:ny*.
-New York ''Tribune.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84024546/1891-12-09/ed-1/?sp=12&q=carriage+electrical</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>SCRAPS OF SCIENCE.
Odd Pieces of Mechanism Evolved
by Meditative Brains.
ELECTRICITY TLAYS ITS PACT.
Carriages and Fans Are Iropelled Yitll
out Animal Energy.
PAVEMENTS MADE FROM OAK AND ICON
An electrical carriage has been shipped to
Chicago from Des Moines, Iowa. It may
arrive to-day, and as soon as its storage bat
teries can be charged it will be sent spin
ning alont; the boulevards. It was built for
ordinary usage and it is said to have carried
12 people at a speed ot 14 miles an hour
and can run continuously for 13 hours be
fore the energy is exhausted. The motor
ued is rated at four-horse power, and
has an armature of the Siemens type with
special-wound coils. The prominent feature
of the carriage is the storage cells, 24 in
number placed in three sets of eight each.
The weight is said to be but 32 pounds per
cell audio yield three-horse power hours of
energy per cell.
The carriage ha a special gearing and a
ball and socket motion to the axle, while a
peculiar hub device allows for any obstacles
encountered. The motor is carried by a
framework underneath the body of the car
riage and is geared to the rear axle. The
steering device is attached to the front uf
the axle and is controlled bv a handwheel in
the front of the carriage. It is said to be
so delicate in action that the course of the
chicle can be altered bv a slight touch.
The switch for throwing the motor in and
out ot circuit is moved by the foot of the
one in charge. This carriage is said to have
ascended grades or 17 per cent without
severe strains.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn90059522/1892-08-11/ed-1/?sp=5&q=electricity+Electricity+Morrison+wagon+Wagons+William</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>GOOD BYE, HORSES I
Wagons May Now Be Run by
Electricity.
Chicago, Aug, 10.— A novelty in the
way of a wagon propelled by electricity
was seen on the streets of Chicago yes
terday. Some time ago President J. B.
McDonald, of the American Battery
company, purchased several patents
from William Morrison, of Dcs Moines.
Among other things was a park wagon
equipped with a small three-horse-power
motor and twenty-four-cell storage bat
tery. Yesterday Mr. McDonald fitted
the wagon with new batteries and gave
it a trial. With five persons in the
wagon it left the barn on Monroe
street and traveled to the company's
office. The run was made in twenty
two minutes, which was considered a
satisfactory, considering that the wagon
was delayed at a bridge and that fre
quent stops were, made on account of
the crowds in the streets down town.
It is calculated that the wagon can
make ten miles an hour easily with the
present motor and can climb any bill in
the city.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1895-12-03/ed-1/?sp=10&q=carriage+carriages+Company+company+electric+Electric+electricity+Morris+Salom+Wagon+wagon+wagons
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The Starrte*?.
"On the evening before the race eleven
competitors declared they would start, but
the next morning when the motocycles were
:ent on their tifty-four-mile run only six
wagons hael appeared at Jackson Park and
midway plaisance. These were:
"5 Duryea Motor Wagon Company,
Springfield, Mass., gasoline.
"7?De la Vergne Refrigerating Machine
Company, Now York, gasoline.
"18?Morris Salom, Philadelphia, elec
tric.
"18?M. Mueller Co., Decatur, ill., gas
oline.
"?!?R. H. Macy Company, New York,
gasoline.
"25?Sturges Electric Motocycle, Chicago,
electric.
"The owners of the electric wagons did
not start out with the idea of winning the
race. They were unable to arrange for sup
ply stations at different places along the
route and consequently could not get enough
power to run over the route to Evanston and
back. Dut they Intended to show that their
electric wagons could travel under all con
ditions us well as the gasoline motor ma
chines, anel they considered their test proved
the practicability of electricity for horseless
carriages.
"The three wagons which distanced all
competitors?the Duryea, Mueller anel the
Macy?were all ?f German make, with some
American improvements. They carried Im
proved Btnz motors, the Mueller wagon be
ing Imported direct from Mannheim, Ger
many. The De la \rergne wagon, which won
the first prl7o In the Paris-Bordeaux race
lest June, also carried a* Benz motor, but
this falleil to drive the vehicle through the
deep snow at a satisfactory rate, and it
droppetl out of tho rage early."
Story of the liuryea Wajgon.
As already stated lie The Star, the Duryea
wagon won. The following is the story of
the Duryea's trip from Chicago to Evans
ton and back, as told, by A. W. White, Its
umpire:
"We left tho barn at 7:15 a.m. and went
with our own power to the starting point.
At 8:15 tbe start was made and we ran
without a stop to the corner of Erie antl
Rush streets. Here we broke our steering
gear ty running over a high crossing cov
ered with snow. A wait of fifty-five minutes
ensued. From this point we ran to Evans
ton without a stop, arriving there at 12*33
o'clock. On the return we were delayed four
minutes In Chicago avenue, Evanston, by a
sleigh that had tipped over In the street.
Cortlnuing, we got Into the wrong road on
account of the absence of a sign at the
corner of Lawrence avenue and Clark street.
We ran down Clark to Diversey street be
fore discovering cur mistake. Then we
went up Diversey to Lincoln avenue and on
Lincoln avenue to Roscoe street, where we
resumed the correct route. I estimate the
extra distance traversed at two miles, ap
proximate. While on Diversey near Clark
we broke our 'sparker,' and spent fifty-five
minutes repairing it. At 3:10 we resumed
the journey.
"We wore delayed fifteen minutes at
Drake avenue and Central Park boulevard
to adjust the machinery and to take fuel.
Another delay of four minutes occurred at
the Fort Wayne crossing of SRth street
boulevard. The delay at the second relay
was ten minutes. Numerous slight delays
of a minute or so I have not mentioned.
"Three and one-half gallons of gasoline
and nineteen gallons of water were con
sumed. No power outside the vehicle was
tsed. I estimate that enough power was
used to run the motor 190 miles over smooth
rof.ds. We finished at 7:18 and ran back to
10th street with our own power. Our cor
rected time was seven hours and fifty-three
minutes."</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1896-02-02/ed-1/?sp=25&q=Carriage+carriage+carriages+electric+Electric+electrical+electricity+Horseless+horseless+Morris+Salom+wagon
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The Horseless Carriage.
It is not outside the realm of possibility
that in the century soon to dawn the
horseless carriage may be as familiar on
the public highway as the bicycle is to
day; as familiar, in fact, as the family con
veyance of the period. Of course' good
roads are a prime requisite for the success
of the motocycle, but good roads are
bound to come, and it is to be hoped that
the agitation for them that has been set
on foot all over this country will not be
void of desirable, results even before tha
MUELLER MOTOCYCLE.
[Reproduced from the Cosmopolitan.]
clnse of the present century. Good
smoothly paved roads being a ccrtninty of
realization at no very remote date, "the j
i prospects of the horseless carriage seem to
j be quite flattering, if the judgment of the
fiiendsof the new invention" can bo relied!
upon. They contend that the horse may j
bo dispensed with and the highest measure
|of speed and comfort attained over j
smoothy paved boulevards in a vehicle pro
pelled by mechanical power. It is worth i
while to take a look at some of these up
to-date vehicles.
The "PJlectrqbat 1 is the original name
given by Morris Salom of Philadelphia j
to the first electric wagon constructed in i
that city. It was ihe joint work of a me-
chanical engineer and an electrician. The
i wagon was run hundreds of miles over
the streets of Philadelphia without seri- j
i ous mishap. Its tot.il weight, including
I the battery, is 4250 pounds, and the max;- j
mum mileage on one charge of electricity
la from h'fty to one hundred, according to j
speed and grades, the maximum speed at- j
tamable being- fifteen miles an hour.
Charles A. Duryea of Peoria, 111., ha 3
successfully applied the gasoline motor to
horselessvehici.es. The Duryea motor re
sembles an ordinary, heavily buih buggy,
weighs 700 pounds,* and has ball-bearings
An Electrobat.
[Reproduced from the Cosmopolitan.]
and rubber-tired wheels. It has an inge
nious mechanism for steering and changing
the speed without a moment's loss at time.
The cost of running this carriage is one
fourth of- a cent a mile, and a supply of
gasoline can be carried sufficient to nm
the machine 150 miles. Upon goo* roads
a SDeed of twenty miles is claimed.
There are numerous rivals for popularity
in the motocycle world. The Mueller
patent, for instance, recently won a prize
in a contest for economy of operation,
coming in a close seconci'to the Dnryea
machine. In order to stimulate invention
and do what they can to hasten the com
ing of the age of the marvelous carriage
the publishers of the Cosmopolitan, from
which publication the illustrations of
motocycles on this page are taken, offer
premiums amounting to $3000. These
premiums are to be awarded to motor
carriages presenting the greatest number
of points of excellence as exhibited in a
trial trip to be made from the New York
office of the Cosmopolitan on the 30th of
May to the Cosmopolitan building at
Irvington, and thence back to tbe starting
point.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1897-12-05/ed-1/?sp=25&q=cab+electric+electricity+New+New-York+vehicle+Vehicle+vehicles
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>CHEAPER THAN HOUSES.
HORSELBS8 CARRIAGES Do MORI WORK
AND COST LESS MONEY.
THK niNVKNIKNCK HAK'?IN'. FROM
Tin: RKGlL.Mt BLaVCTRIC WIRE??THE
NEW VEHICUM ?it l*OCTOBg
There are young nn^n In N<\v-Y?rk who can
remember when tin? only telephone lina in th??
city connected a r????m in Tht? Triltime Building
with th? American institute. People used In
come t? that room anil listen to other? talk. Blng
or whistle al the other end of the lino, and ex?
clamations of wonder and surprise were beard
whenever the Imperfect instrument was >x
aniine?!. The telephone wan l?M>k?d upon at Hint
tlm?? a scli-ntlflc t?>>, and in much th?? same
?Kht as the motor vehicle is regarded by many
people at this time. Hut the telephon?? has 1???- j
come a necessity, and, In the same way, many
people predict that tho boraeleee carriage win
Oeaae to be looked upon aa a novel plaything
and take Its place among the neoe?Itlesi.
In some parts of Europe the horseless vehicles
have become popular and comparatively cheap,
and, the novelty having worn off, they are em
ployed in a practical way. In New-York the
horseless cnrrlage has not y?-t become popular,
and the vehicles which are seen OB the Btreet? I
are for the most part the property of cab com-
panics, by whom they are rented to the people
win? wish tfacts that the few mot??r vehicles which have
been sold to private individuals have niv-n eat?
isf.i. lion, that th?? c ?st off maintaining th?'ni la
?mall and that the Btreeta ??f New-Tor?, are
gradually being Improved ao that the vehicles
will run without Jolting, make tn.inufa ?turer?
lielii-v.? thai Hier?? ?a ill Boon be a boom in tliut
direction.
c. .1. Harrington, superintendent of the Elec?
tric Vehicle Company, said thai bla ion?, m
h recently ordered one hundred additional
canias;???, and thai there would b? room in their
place to stop? and take -care of a number ??f
vehicle? f??i other people.
?Jt costs much less to keep a homeless wagon
than an ordinary outfit," be said, and it enn do
mur.? work. Th?? horse, if driven more mile? on
one ?lay than hexertion, will be worthlesa the nexl day, while
the iunior wagon can be recharged when its
electric supply is exhausted ?ml go right ahead
?gain. w>? shall ask $1 for every twenty-flve
mii- charge, and will also receive a amount
for taking cai?? vehicle and keeping ,t
cie.u? and in repair. Th?? coat of running the
vehicle will depend <>n the number <>f miles."
Among the few peopl?? in N? w-V??rk who drive
motor vehicles an? (?livr II Belmont and
W. E. Busby. Mr Belmont'a turnout created
some excitement at Newport last summer, and
was on?? of the sights of tli?? pia???. Mr. Dusby
guillas his boraeleee vehicle along Riverside
Drlv?? nearly every day It? builder, Andrew I,
UuV.r, sai?! that it show???! n?> m??r?? wear than
an ordinary vehicle which ha?l travelled half aa
many mil? s. This carriage is kept in Mr. BUS
by'? stabl??, w 1???p? its motor is supplied through
th.? regular Edison current at the regular reten.
The bill for chartiifiK it the fust month It ran
was $1035, and it tan six bjndred miles In that
time. The av?rai,'!? cost for electricity la two
??cuts a mile, but th?? price would be considerably
less if the own-T of the vehicle had his own
electric plan, Tins faci baa been dem?r*natrated
by J. R, Whiting, ol Stamford, Conn., who has
an electric generator for lighting his house, Hla
horselesa vehicle I? charged by tins generator,
an?l this brings tli?? coal down to l?*ss than one
????ni a mile,
br Will:.m, H Hutehlnsofi ?ff Brooklyn, has
ordered horseless stanhope phai ton, and he
will one off tin? pioneers ot his profession In
the use off tins style off vehicle. Bui tbe great?
est addition? in ti??? line will probably l?? m the
ahape ot business wagons. an ordei under way now lor a delivery wagon
for a large depart meni More a osi of I-.',?*??'!,
and if Ihe vehfcle provea satlefactory the con
csrn will take iifty more. The wagons will make
twenty-five miles a day and can be run at the I
rete of i.vo power of not more lhan ">n cents day Aside
from 'osi ?if Storage and repairs, the ???t ?>r
maintaining ??ii?? ?>f these delivery wagons a yenr
waa placed at th?? following figure by Mr. Rlker:
?nteres! on Investment.flRfJ
800 working ?lays al "ill centi. lull
Total *SHl
Tnis i? leas than it would to draw ih?? vehlcl?</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026853/1897-12-22/ed-1/?sp=7&q=CABS+cabs+Electric+ELECTRIC+vehicle+vehicles
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>ELECTRIC CABS IN NEW YORK.
Homeless Vehicles Hare Become a Fix*
tare In the Biff City.
Electric cabs, hansoms and broughams
are a sucoesB in New York, so
ELECTRIC HANSOM USED IN NEW YOBK.
much of a success that the company
operating them has just given out an
order for 100 new vehicles. Daring
Jane, the first moath of their operation,
a total number of 632 calls were
received, averaging between thirty-Wb
and twelve per day, carrying 1680 passengers
4603 miles at rates similar to
the horse-cab system, and each month
sinoe that time has seen a steady increase
in the service.
The best resalts obtained from these
vehicles show that about -1.25 horsepower
is supplied for a propulsion of
2000 pounds over ordinarily level roads
at a speed of ten miles an hour. This
consumption of power is a trifle over
two and one-third times that of similar
work on rails, which indicates that the
equipment of the battery is carefully
-ii _ f xi J
adapted to trie total weigni 01 tue vemcle
and just sufficient for practical
traveling capacity. The maximum
weight of a battery for a hansom weighing
3000 pounds is 1200 pounds for a
distance of twenty-five miles at the
maximum speed of twelve miles or at
an average speed of six miles.
i
|B|||g^gg|gg^.
IB
m
irrniiw?i|
H
YORK.
by Kmpp at the World's Fair at Chicago,
oould resist a shot from It.
A vehiole to travel twice this distance
could readily be built, but it
would need to be twice its weight in
order to accommodate twioe the bat
tery equipment, xnis type 01 venicie
is constructed -with the view of a speed
of from six to twelve miles 'an hour,
but a vehicle can be built to approximate
thirty miles an hour, although it
would necessarily be made as a raoing
apparatus and not fit for street work.
Two one-and-one-half horse-power
motors, weighing 172$ pounds each,
ore found sufficient for a hansom, and
are Operated at a maximum speed of
1350 revolutions per minute.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn90059523/1899-02-05/ed-1/?sp=18&q=car+carriage+carriages+cars+electric+electrical+electricity+horseless+vehicle+vehicles
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE day of the horse is passing
away. Already the practical de
monetlzation of the faithful!
equine might be said to be taking!
place, and before another cen- J
tury shall have elapsed he may have be
come a zoological curiosity. His yen- j
erable bones will be seen mounted and I
on exhibition in museums. The small
boy ot the twentieth century will won
der what sort of animal Equus cabal
lus really was and will marvel at the
Ca< t that he was once harnessed and
made to haul heavy loads.
The beginning: of the end was in sight
when electricity first supplanted the
horse as a means of propulsion for
street cars. Then the bicycle came,
sprang at once into popular favor and
rendered still more limited the' uses of
our once essential quadruped.
But now stili greater changes are
taking place. The introduction of the
automobile on streets of American cit
ies is slowly but surely driving out the
old fashioned hansom and the two horse
orougham, and now even the lorrie team
and the long overworked draft horse
are to become "things that were."
The recent formation of a company in
New York city with a capital of some
$100,000,000 to exploit compressed air as
a motive power for all trucking and
carting business in Greater New York
shows still again how surely the reign j
of the horse is passing away. He will
of course continue, for a time at least,
to remain the pet and the trained speed
ing animal of the wealthy in the city
and the helpful friend of the more hum
ble farmer in the country. But as time
goes on and urban population becomes
more and more dense it will be seen, to
be even more necessary in order to ob
viate congestion of traffic in city streets
and to maintain a proper degree of san
itation and cleanliness to allow only
self propelling- vehicles on the public
streets of our towns and cities.
The outcome of this will be a vast
Improvement in the condition and
smoothness of all city streets, the abo
lition of the objectionable cobblestone
is paving material and the elimination
of the ear piercing noises which now
make a pandemonium of the average
metropolitan thoroughfare.
It is true, motor vehicles for pleasure,
traffic and business purposes have been
somewhat slow of adoption in this coun
try. The horse has held his own here
with remarkable pertinacity, for it has
been in European cities, and particular
ly in Paris, that the automobile indus
try has flourished to the greatest ex
tent. The principal reason why Ameri
cans have been in no undue haste to
sulopt motor carriages re the fact that
mechanically these have not hitherto
been sufficiently developed to render
them acceptable for general use. The
motive power employed in most of them
has been unsatisfactory because of lack
of efficiency in some cases and extrava
gant expense of operation in others.
But American brains and American en
ergy have been at work on the problem
for the last few years, with the result
that the objections referred to have
been practically removed.
The general public, as a rule, has not
the opportunity of seeing the gradual
;:!:ti laborious approach to perfection of
any important mechanical invention.
This same general public is usually as
tounded at the miraculous appearance
i some new wonder, while the men
who have been laboring for years to
bring about this apparent mechanical
miracle foresaw the inevitable long be
fore the busy world had thought of such
a ihing. For some time now jokes have
been made about the passing of the
horse, but until the last year or so it
was never really thought that the pe
riod of equine usefulness had so nearly
approached its close.
It was vaguely felt that changes
might come about in time, for the idea
of mechanical instead of animal trac
tion power is as old as the history of
human thought itself. Even Homer
himself describes the god Vulcan as be
ing engaged upon the construction of
a great hall on wheels, which he de
.-cubes as "self moving and wonderful,"
and Juno is made to command Vulcan
to create tripods which shall run by
!v<>s. thus rendering better serv
!ce to the gods in their meetings on
Mount Olympus.
in the thirteenth century the English
philosopher Roger Bacon wrote in one
of his works. "They will make carriages
which will run with the greatest imag
inable swiftness without any harnessed
whatever."
The earliest horseless carriage which is
preserved today is one now on exhibition
in Paris at the Conservatoire dcs Artes
et Metiers. This machine was invented
by Cugnot in 1769 and was made to op
erate by steam, the energy of which
was applied through two perpendicular
piston tubes. The principal reason per- j
haps why the French steam automobile
was not brought to a state of compara
tive perfection during the last century
was the beginning of the revolution.
The turbulence which accompanied that
event naturally turned men's minds
from .peaceful and civilizing pursuits to I
thoughts of warfare and the deposing of 1
NUGGETS FROM EVERYWHERE.
Senator Simon of Oregon has been
taking banjo lessons. "Are you improv
ing?" some one asked him recently.
"J'.wh'T tl*it or the neighbors are get
ting inure used to it," he replied.
f>n ,in occasion a bishop was consol
iriK a costermonger for the loss of his
I j l l to son. The poor fellow was rocking
tf. and fro in his distress. He suddenly
!'.'.kf fi -,it i]i<: bishop and, with tears
running down his cheeks, said, "D'ye
tliink I could c;et the young beggar
ituffd?"
The late Senator Morrill, though he
monarchs. But it was in all likelihood
from the Cugnot steam carriage that i
Stephenson indirectly obtained his idea j
for a locomotive on rails.
j At the Exposition Universelle in Paris
I in 187S a steam automobile was exhibit-
I ed very like that of Cugnot, the only
j difference being that the frame of. the
j more modern vehicle was built after the
J plan of a common road carriage and not
jas a velocipede. This automobile, how- I
ever, was not a very satisfactory ma- j
chine, and it was not until 12 years later
that MM. Serpollet and Archdeacon in- i
vented a steam automobile, with which j
they journeyed from Paris to L.yons in
ten days. In 1894 the automobile first
gave promise of actual adaptability for j
general transportation and traction j
purposes. In that year the editor of the
Petit Journal organized the first auto
mobile race, which was run from Paris j
to Rouen. In this contest the steam
horseless carriage, while proving itself
cumbersome, noisy and uncouth in ap
pearance, showed itself superior to its
electrical and gasoline propelled rivals
of that time. The following year an
other race was run, this time from Paris
to Bordeaux and return, but in this test
it was the electrical carriage that prov
ed itself the superior machine.
Up to this time the construction of
these carriages had been conducted
along the ugly lines of a buggy or four
wheeled cart instead of seeking an in
dividuality for themselves through de
j signs more fitting to their peculiar qual
ities. Today, however, it might be said
that they have evolved an individuality
of their own. Automobile mechanics is
an art the nicety of which is only un
derstood by those who are of the pro
fession.
But one of the great difficulties that
still face the constructors of horseless
carriages is the problem of expense. A
Parisian made automobile victoria, for
instance, costs some $800 and an auto
mobile tricycle $300. The heavier car
riages are proportionately expensive.
This costliness of manufacture, how
ever, is a drawback that time will put
right,- just as has been the case with
the bicycle. But while the initial outlay
for an automobile Is still very large this
is more than compensated for by the in
significant extent of operating expenses,
the fuel for the petroleum propelled ye-
hides costing merely 1% cents per hour.
The development of the automobile as
a thing of beauty will take place only
when its place is assured and its use is
general, when people of means and
fashion will begin to demand certain
characteristics of design and finish to
differentiate their carriages from the
vehicles of the livery and the cab stand.
There are a number of New York la-
probably took up less space in The
Congressional Record than any of his
colleagues, always made a speech early
in the session and sent a copy bound
in Russia leather to every senator and
a paper bound copy to every voter In
Vermont.
Congressman Elect John L. Burnett
of Alabama, who will probably be the
smallest man in the next house, is an
able lawyer. When he first appeared
before the supreme court of Alabama
to argue a case, he stood up behind a
high bench on which lawyers were ac
-1
THE ST. PAUL GLOBE SUNDAY FEBRUARY 5, 1809.
dies who have their own private auto
mobiles and may be seen any day
speeding noiselessly along the more
fashionable streets of that city. It takes
some skill and experience to operate
one of these powerful horseless car
riages, for, after all, they are mere lo
comotives and not unconnected with
danger in the hands of the inexperi
enced. In Paris the authorities require
each operator of an automobile to pass
a practical examination, after which
he is given a certificate of efficiency.
The local history of Paris, neverthe
less, .for the past two years has been
lively enough with runaways, collisions,
upsets and explosions of a more or less
serious nature. New York has also had
its list of little accidents.
There is one thing that the motor car
riage demands, and that is good roads.
We are already indebted to the bicycle
for an improvement in the condition of
our highways, but when the automobile
comes into general use both the great
unthinking public and governmental
bodies will become impressed with' the
necessity for a better class of roadmak
ing. As things now are, the United
States stands lowest on the list of ad
vanced countries in the matter of good
highways. Another advantage of the
use of the horseless vehicle will be that
our streets will be found more health-
customed to lay their books and pa
pers. "May it please the court," be
gan the diminutive counsel, when the
chief justice broke in, "Mr. Burnett, it
is the custom of lawyers to rise while
addressing this court."
jOn a recently bitterly cold night
Speaker Reed had occasion to ride on a
street car the conductor of which neg
ligently left the door open, to the great
discomfort of the passengers. Mr. Reed
beckoned to the railway official and
when the latter came inside asked,
"Why have you got your collar turned
up, my friend?" "It's mighty cold," re
sponded the conductor, "and I want to
keep warm." "So do the rest of us,"
ful and cleaner than is now possible.
j Stabling will no longer be necessary in
cities, and there will be more room on
j city streets. The wearing noise of traf
fie will be hushed, and pneumatic tires
and silent generators *or storage batter
ies will do away with the roar of wheels
j and the rattle of horses' feet. In our
country, fortunately, there is no legis
lation and no popular prejudice against
I the automobile, as in England, for in
stance, where only a little over a year
i ago prohibitory legislation with regard
to the use of such carriages in London
was repealed. Until this action was
taken it was necessary that all horse
less carriages should be preceded by a
man on foot or on horseback bearing a
I red flag as a warning of the approach
of the terrible engine of destruction.
Animal power has ever been capri
cious and uncertain, while machinery is
j reliable and always sure. An automo
bile does not require continual atten-
tion, as does an animal. While not in
use the automobile entails no operating
expenses, and all that can be charged
to its idleness is the interest on the
original outlay for its purchase. Nor
will it grow old and die, like a horse.
When its day's work is done, it can be
run into a shed and stand there until
once more called upon to do service.
So long as it remaijis one of the deep
rooted characteristics of man, the most
restless of all animals, to be in the
place where he is not he will see to it
that his means of transportation are as
expedient, inexpensive and comfortable
as circumstances will permit. It has
taken him some time to reach the age
of the automobile, but it might be said
that such an age has at last arrived.
The passing of the horse furnishes
food for much profound thought and
reflection. It is a farreaching question, j
affecting almost all kinds and condi
tions of men. What will become of the
smith who hitherto eked out his frugal
existence in the wayside village under
the spreading chestnut tree? What will
become of the hay and feed man who
has so long and so profitably catered to
the inner wants of our old time equine
friend? What will become of the farm
er and his hay crop and his field of
oats? What will become of the costly
livery stable and the harness maker and
the veterinary surgeon?
It is no easy matter to figure out the
Immediate or even the ultimate im
provement in the general condition of
affairs which will result from the adop-
observed the speaker. "Suppose you
shut the door!" It is needless to add
that the passengers were comfortable
during the remainder of the trip.
A characteristic of the late William
Black was his ignorance of his own
books, and it was very difficult to get
him to talk about his novels. It seem
ed that as soon as the proof sheets were
returned to the printers Mr. Black for
got all about his own creations, "in
talking to my husband the other day,"
Mrs. Black once said fto a visitor, "I
suddenly remembered an anecdote in
one of his novels which illustrated what
I was saying. Mr. Black laughed hearti
ly at the story and then turned eagerly
lion of the horseless carriage, when it
is borne in mind that many disturbing
elements enter into the problem. Al
ready there has been a great falling oft
in the production ef horses and a depre
ciation in the value of horseflesh, which
i has filled the farmer and the horse
breeder with apprehension. But, for
tunately, these questions have the habit
jof settling and adjusting themselves.
j When it is remembered that there are
j now millions of acres of land devoted to
the growing of crops for horse food
alone, which in time may and must be
I devoted to the production of food for
I the human beings who are engaged in
the manufacture of the very machines
that are displacing the horse, the prob
lem is not so intricate and the outlook
is not so dark as it at first seems.
The poor old cab horse has always
had his drawbacks as a working ma
chine, and even with an animal en
dowed with all the noble attributes of
I the horse the question of economics can
not be kept out of the calculation. It
costs at least 60 cents a day to keep the
ordinary steed that travels up and down
a city's streets, and if he chances to be
a cab horse and times are good he will
I travel about 25 miles, on an average, on
that amount of nourishment. But he re
j quires at least eight hours' sleep and
rest, to say nothing of an occasional
day off as a result of colic, which leaves
I him a working capacity of 16 hours.
Most of the time, however, he spends in
j loafing around on street corners and
dreamily digesting his 60 cents' worth
of oats and hay.
It is commonly supposed that all cab
horses live about 100 years, but this is
one of those popular errors which have
no actual foundation in fact. His ten
ure of life averages, appearances to the
contrary, about 15 years, and at 60 cents
a day His feed in that time will amount
to only $3,275, for which, if he has
led an industrious, sober and unpam
pered life, he covers some 109,500 miles.
This newfangled automobile that is
elbowing its four footed rival off the
streets of the city, on the other hand,
will travel the same distance for about
$1,000, expended in fuel or electricity,
and while doing so will never have to
be sent to the blacksmith shop to be
shod, the average cost of repairs being
no more than that for the ordinary car
riage hauled by horses.
A French writer who has made a
study of the horseless carriage a spe
cialty has been figuring out its ultimata
to me, 'But where did you hear so good
a story?' My husband wouldn't be
lieve it was in one of his own books
until I found it for him."
Senator Frye of Maine says that
while in Paris he needed a hair cut, so
he studied carefully the necessary por
tion of his "French Conversation Book"
and did his best to make the barber
understand. "I don't understand Dutch,"
said the person addressed. "Do you
speak English?"
A good story is told by Rudyard Kip
ling at his own expense. During his
stay in Wiltshire, England, one sum
mer he met little Dorothy Drew, Mr.
Gladstone's granddaughter, and, being
possibilities and prophesying as to its
future.
He forecasts that the size of the auto
mobile, while not yet greatly differing
from the ordinary one or two horse
wagon, will increase in time to an enor
mous extent and that its weight may
even reach a Vegister of thousands of
tons. The liveryman will be replaced
by the dispenser of coal, electricity and
1 petroleum, and instead of water troughs
1 along the principal highways there will
be seen innumerable electric storage de
pots.
This French prophet attempts to
straighten out the economic knot by
1 forecasting that the horse will in time
become a delectable and much sought
after feod animal. He holds that a life
of leisure will restore the proper amount
of succulence to the flesh of the now
overworked quadruped, and that a time
will come when horse steaks will be
served at all restaurants and their con
sumption will be looked upon as a mat
ter of course. This Parisian prophet also
foresees the traveling shop and the itin
erant theater. An immense automobile
will carry along both actors, scenery and j
playhouse. On the upper floors of the
great wheeled building will be the
apartments of the company, who will
not have to pack and unpack their be
longings each day.
A train de luxe will become the fash
ionable means by which pleasure out
ings will be taken, and summer travel
ing will no longer be done on dusty and
crowded railway trains. A circuit court
will move from town to town in full
session on wheels, and even funeral
processions will consist of a number of
automobiles linked together like a train
of cars.
All this sounds more or less like a
page from a fairy tale book or the idle
dream of a mere visionary. It repre
sents, nevertheless, something far more
substantial, for it is the conviction of a
farseeing and scholarly French scien
tist, who has had the opportunity of
studying the different inventions which
are slowly but surely being brought to a
state of perfection in his own country,
which may well be called the birthplace
and the home of the horseless carriage.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87062245/1902-02-02/ed-1/?sp=26&q=Automobile+automobile+AUTOMOBILE+automobiles+electric+electrical
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE BALLAD OF THE AUTOMOBILE
Oat of the woods and Into the stress ot Gotham marts there
came
Young Timothy Hay and began straightway to dicker with
Life for fame
And he cared no whit on thrones to sit or at shrines of art
to kneel
One aim alone before him shone to possess an automobile
He had a scheme like an opium dream constructed on
Midas plan
To wake up the world as it never was woke since Its slow
old life began
By the wheels in his head and the wheels on his feet he
conned the busy I atcs
And slid along the road to wealth as one on roller skates
He bought his treasure and mounted the seat and gazed
across the land
And felt with Joy t he marveloue toy obey his untried hand
And when he yaw 1 he ehauffeor wait to take him all about
He said I know what I want to do and you mayB well
get out
The chauffeur lit with alacrity ho had seen such things
before
And the automobl le on its silent wheel sptd like the days
of yore
And lest in dream s sat Timothy until cf a sudden he
Became aware that his agile charge vas trying to climb a
tree
Now what he said as he felt of his head I should not like
to say
No bicscle skates or electric car had treated him that way
0 he sat him dovv n beside the rocd to sec what the mat
ter might be
The machine mus t be out ct order he ijoth theres
nothing the ma Iter with me
He set the siecrliis rod nor-nor-cast and physicked tho
running gear
And what he did to the gasolene tank It doth not jet ap
pear
And the hair of the horrified cows rose up as they gazul
across tho fence
Tor the air was bluo with the slzzing smoke and language
most intense
Then he hoisted the vreck on it3 limping wheels and man
aged to make it go
Though its progress was somewhat erratic and tircd llko
and slow
And people gave It nil of the road when they saw It com
ing by
Till it reached the brow of a little hill and started out
to lly
Ho pounded the brake and he cried Cecl Haw but it did
not understand
And It turned unlimited somersaults across the startled
land
But though he was tumbled upside dovn in a most unseemly
way
Nobody saw a conviction of sin shaken cut of Timothy Hay
He picked himself and the automobile frcifl the mud of the
roadside ditch
And ihc state of the two was such that jou could hardly
tell which from which
And he said It Is all this darnel machine as cti can
plainly see
For all my tinkering did no good and terc3 nothing the
matter with me l
c
There came a buzz frcm the Lattcred Tiling a he climbed
to his seat once mure
And he rose on the wings of a purple cloud and a dull and
smothered roar
For whether it wa3 that the insult biiimned its passions
Mtter cup
Or what was the matter nobody knows but that automobile
blew up
A reeking smell of gasolene went forth and smote the
sky
The automobile and Timothy went on to the by and by
They were subdivided so thoroughly that not till the next
days rain
Did aught descend that was recognized as relics of the
twain
Now while to run an automobile Is a Joyous thii to do
The joy is done and no more it is fun when the sutomoblle
runs vou
And its btst to know where the rivets go and every cog
and wheel
Unless you intend your tour to extend to heaven per auto
mobile</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1907-12-11/ed-1/?sp=9&q=CARRIAGE+electric+Electric+electrical+electricity+Vehicle
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>#/7 AVTO FAILURE.
X. J. Vehicle Concern, $20,000,000
Capital, in Receiver*' Hands.,.
Judge Cross, of the United States Circuit Court
at his home in Elizabeth. N. J.. yesterday, ap
pointed Halsey M. Barrett, of Ftioomfield. N. .1
and Henry W. Mucklesa receivers for the Electric
Vehicle Company, a J3f>.oon,ono New Jeraey oorpont
tion. with a plant at Hartford. Conn. The re
ceivers are bonded for FJOO/OO each. The Hartford
Rubber Works Company, which his a claim <-f
$11,785 60. was the petitioner. Inability to get
ready cash is said to be the cause of the Electric
Vehicle Company's trouble.
Juris* Cross adjudged the company to be in
solvent because it had defaulted in the payment
of 52,600,000 of 6 per cent gold bonds which ma
tured on November 1. The indebtedness consists
of these bonds, secured by mortgage on property
of the company held by the Morton Trust Com
pany, of New York: notes aggregating $899.r».l SO
and accounts payable amounting to EM.?!*) 3:2.
The assets are. placed at $14,054. 432 48. Of this only
$12,000 Is In cash, Die rest consisting of the plant,
patents, stock, accounts payable, etc.
Judge Ward, in the United States Circuit Court
here, also appointed Halsey M. Barrett a receiver
and William S. Montgomery, of this city, receiver
of the property of the Klectric Vehicle Company.
The bond of the receivers here was fixed jointly
at $25,000.
"Moody's Manual" for 1907 gives M. J. Budlons
as president of the Electric Vehicle Company,
Walter G. Henderson as treasurer, H. W. Kyte as
secretary and assistant treasurer, and the directors
these three men and H. 11. Vreeland, Grant B.
Schley, jr., M. Gavin, 2d,' Albert Taylor and W.
O. Knudson. There have recently been several
changes in this list, Messrs. Vreeland and Schley
being no longer directors and Mr. Henderson hav
ing' succeeded as president Mr. Budlong, who is
now president of the Association of Licensed Auto
mobile Manufacturers of America. The Electric
Vehicle Company is the owner of the "SeJden
patent," the basic patent on gasolene automobiles,
on which it receives royalties from the manufact
urers who axe members of the Association of
Licensed Automobile Manufacturers.
Isaac L. Rice, now president of the Consolidated
Railway Lighting and Refrigerating Company, tho
Klectric Boat Company, the Casein Company of
America, and several other corporations, was the
organizer of the Electric Vehicle Company, whicli
lias $11,000,000 common stock, of which 510,450,000- is
outstanding, and $9,000,000 8 per cent cumulative
preferred stock, of which $8,145,000 has been issued.
In 1899 the Whitney-Ryan-Wtdcncr-Dolan syndicate
acquired a large interest in the company, and in
December, 1900, George H. Day. of Hartford, repre
senting the Pope Interests, became president. The
board of directors at that time included, in addition
to Mr. Day, Colonel A. A. Pope. Martin Moloney.
Isaac L. Rice and personal representatives or
Messrs. Whitney and Ryan.
Of the stock of the Electric Vehicle Company.
$3,152,800 preferred and $3,212,300 common, in addi
tion to $340,000- bonds, are owned by the Electric
Storage Battery Company, of which Herbert Uoyd
is president. Grant B. Schley is r.rst vice-president.
XV. G. Henderson, now head of the Electric Vehi
cle Company, is secretary, and treasurer, and
Thomas Dolan, Rudolph Ellis, Herbert Lloyd,
George D. Widcr.cr. P. A. B. Widener, Anthony
N. -Brady,- 11. P. Whitney. ft H- 'Vreeland and
Grant B. Schley are directors/"</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn86072160/1925-01-12/ed-1/?sp=1&st=text</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>WASHINGTON, Jaq. 12—Calvin
Coolidge and Charles O. Dawes were
elected president and vice president
respectively today.
The electors for whom the Amerl-
voters directly cast their ballots
last November, met In the respective
states, canvassed the popular vote,
and in accordance with the consti
tution. cat t their ballots for presi
dent and vice president.
This vote of the electors will be
certified to the president of the sen
ate by each of the 48 state meetings
and will be opened at a joint ses
sion of the senate and house Feb
ruary 18.
ing that the man apparently
had been stunned by the force of the
explosion, and succumbed to the
smoke and flames l>efore th* Station
No. 2 fire force, answering the alarm
turned In by Justice Henry Brennan,
could bring them under control.
boundaries of Arizona, irrespective
of the state's Wishes in the matter.
Arizona is the only state of the
seven interested that hns not ratified
the river compact. The governor
recommended un appropriation of
8100,000 for the services of counsel,
engineers and economists to deter
mine Arizona's legal status in the
controversy.
He nlsm recommended the adoption
of a depositors* bank guarantee law.
a rigid blue sky law. revision of
the stat* game laws and the estab
lishment of u president preferential
primary.
On Streits or at Newstands, 5 cents
Del’ve.-ed by Carrier 75 cents a month
Ginger," which bore the mark of
a local drug firm, some thirty car
tridges of .32 calibre, and a large
amount of Iron filings. Recon
st ruction of the bomb disclosed it
had been composed es three sections,
one containing the iron and car
trldges. another powder and tho
third picric acid. The latter agent
is believed to have ignited the pow
der. Police declared that the ma
chine had been manufactured by an
expert.
The explosion occurred a few mln-
SENATORIAL COURTESY LOST
AS STORMY PETRELS RATTLE
ON FLOOR OF LEGISLATURE
By ROBERT T. SMALL.
(Copyright. 1925, Casper Tribune.)
WASHINGTON. Jan. 12 —Where
Is the senatorial courtesy of yester
year? There Is about as much left
of It as there would be at a meet
Ing of a lot of strange bulldogs.
Courtesy has been replaced by curt
ness and consideration has given
way to condemnation. Senators rise
In their places these days and talk
about each other and at each other
in a manner which some of the old
John lutnga*, proprietor of the
shop, was with Danglis when the
blast came. Hurled toward the
front of the building, he was beating
blindly against the wall In a futile
effort to find the exit when Judge
Brennan, who had hurried to the
door, shouted to attract his attention
and succeeded in guiding him to the
open air. He was hurried to the
Lincoln street hospital badly
bruised and burned, but It is be
lleved recover.
The force of the explosion shat
tered the glass and brick fa<-ade of
the building like piecrust, bulged the
wall of the adjoining Rockaway res
tuarant, crumbled tlie ornamenta'
g'aea in the lobby of the Gladstone
on the ether side, and showered
glass and masonry for a score of
yards. George Papps, proprietor of
the Rockaway, was cut and bruised
and John Poulos, who was parsing
the T. and 1., suffered superficial
cuts from flying glass. Several pat
rons in the Rockaway were hurled
to h* floor but escaped anything
worse than a bad (right.
A colunmn of smoke and flame
billowing up at the moment of the
blast sent guests in the Gladstone
racing to elevator* and fire escapes
On* elevator Jammed between
floors, creating a near panic. Most
of the resident;! eventually scram
bled down the ladders to safety. Th*
hotel was saturated with smoke, but
thanks to its fireproof construction
no serious damage resulted.
Langas was able give no defi
nite account of how th* gas liecame
Ignited He had h**n warned earlier
in Ui* evening by Mr. Papps and by
A. L. Rose, who operates the tailor
shop tq the north of the ROckawa
and was part owner of the dovaetat
ed shoe repairing establishment
that gas wan escaping Into the build
(Continued on Page Eight)
utes after ten o’clock yesterday
morning, an hour when Chief of
Police Daniel J. OBrien, Captain of
Detectives Duncan Matheson and
Wollce Captain William Quinn are
generally arriving for their regular
Sunday conference. The men, how
ever, were late yesterday and did
not arrive until after the explosion.
This freak of fate probably saved
their lives, they said today, because
the bomb was placed only a few feet
from the office where they hold
their weekly conferences.
folk* «ay is reminiscent of a gather
ing of flsh wives.
It Is all a reminder of the pleas
ant times that are to b* had hero
In Washington between now and the
fourth of March. The tqgjper of the
senate is such that it is bmall won
d*r President Coolidge doesn’t want
un extra session of that body on
his hands all summer. The presi
dent thinks the country needs a
rest. He knows it does.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85038485/1925-01-12/ed-1/?sp=1&st=text
</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>Hundreds Unable To Find
Seats In New Audi
torium
FIRST METHODIST
ALSO IS PACKED
Rev. Gid Higginbotham
Preaches At Extra
Meeting
Hundreds were turned away
Sunday night at the municipal
auditorium, where 'John Brown,
evangelist, began the second week
yf his revival campaign.
Fully an hour before the services
started great throngs commenced
noving toward the building, and by
7:20, ten minutes before the choir
opened its first hymn, every seat in
;he house was taken.
Besides this number, scores who
slipped through the entrance before the
capacity mark was reached, etood
throughout the meeting. With the
number seated on the speaker s plat
form it was estimated that the gath
ering totaled around 7,000.
Rev. Mr. Brown, sensing the overflow
early in the evening, ordered a special
sermon at the First Methodist church
where the Rev. Gid Higginbotham, one
of the Brown party, substituted for the
evangelist. Several hundred attended
this service.
Most df the crowd apparently came
in automobiles for the {jars parked on
Lhe blocks around the theater extended
as far as Fifth avenue, Eighteenth
and Twenty-fourth streets. It was the
largest body that has appeared at the
auditorium since it was built, attesting
Lhe prediction by Mr. Brown that Bir
mingham is verging upon the greatest
religious revival in its history.
•‘Repent’* Is Ills Theme
Mr. Brown’s sermon, as has been his
•ustom many times previous, was leveled
at the churches. He took for his sub
ject an old-fashioned plea for repent
ance, and his chant “Repent—repent
repent” beat as waves upon the ears
of his auditors.
In his pleadings for repentance Mr.
Brown selected for his attack tongues
and “dirty” money. He asserted the
tongues of scandal-mongers are a men
ace to any community through theii
disruption of character; tha tongue*
pf the suggest ivo story-teller n danger
ous threat upon morals, andared no man could hope to gain en
trance to heaven who died holding
“dirty” money.
“The time of Christ’s second cominig
is at hanad,” the evangelist said, "ant
whether you be “pre-millennary” 01
“post-millennary” you should prepare tc
meet your God. Any day He will come.’
Mr. Brown stated that the prepara
tion must first come through the
church; through the church from the
the home; and through the home froxr
the individual. “And the time for
churches to begin their preparation i*
now,” he said.
Lambaste Scandal Mongers
In an offensive against scandal
monging tongues Mr. Brown at times
reached passionate heights of oratory
that swayed his audience. Again when
he broke into an Indictment of “dirty
money audible sighs ran through the
crowd. While speaking upon the latter
subject, he became particularly bitter.
“Any man who has taken dirty money
and makes no honest effort to return
It Is as sure to reach hell as I am to
meet my Master on the Judgment Day,*1
he said. “I would prefer tp be penniless
and retain my soul.
“A man who Is in debt should try
conscientiously to pay what he owes.
If he religiously tries, he will receive
Divine aid.”
Mr. Brown said that Birmingham waa
entering upon the greatest religious re
vival in its history and he pleaded
with church members to put their
“house in order" and “straighten their
paths” to meet this epoch. He asserted
that the world had never been in a
greater need of religion and that the
golden opportunity to act now awaits
Lhe churches.
After reading from the third chapter
of 8t. Matthew, the minister chose parts
of verses two and three as his text:
"Repent ye, for the kingdom of heaven
Is at hand”; and “Prepare ye the way of
the Lord. Make His paths straight. He
declared that “repentance” has never
been a popular or acceptable doctrine.
The evangelist stated that John the
{Continued On Page Two)
Shiek Of Black,
In Garb Of Blue,
Now Drab In Jail
/T\E LAWD helps dem whut
helps demselves” had- Ions
been a favorite sermon topic
with Rev. Elder Love, negro, of
Selma.
He treated the subject with aplomb
throwing In just enough threats of'
hell-fire and damnation to keep his
audience resting uneasily on the eldge
of their seats.
Rev. Love had been booked to carry
his message befors a large gather
ing at the St. James A. M. K.
church Sunday evening. Feeling the
import of the mission he had dressed
with scrupulous care. He wore a
light blue suit, a light blue coat, a
light blue hat. and a necktie that
corresponded it, too, was light
blue. Several of the congregation
commented to each other regarding
the sartorial splendor of Rev. Love’s
attire but none took a greater genuine
interest that Houston Pickett. 1321
Seventh avenue. Pickett took one
glance at the Rev. Love, draped
artistically upon the platform, and
left hurriedly.
Fifteen minutes later when the min
later was preparing to unload the
second chapter of his scathing de
nunciations he was Interrupted and
called to. the rear of the church. The
congregation waited restlessly sev
eral minutes for his return and then
appeased their religious appetites by
singing hymns.
While this was transpiring Rev.
Love, minus all of his clothing ex
cept a pair of badly worn shoes, was
languishing morosely in a cell at the
Jail. Houston Pickett, meantime,
strutted into the calcimine glare of
darktown Eighteenth street featur
ing a light blue suit, a Itght blue coat,
a light blue hat. and a necktie that
defied argument regarding its light
blue tendencies.
To police, they declared. It appeared
that the Rev. Mr. Love had adhered
oo rigidly to his texL^, t
7
CABINET CRISIS
STIRS GERMANY;
REVOLT RUMORED
Reports Of Incipient Rev
I olution Emanate From
Unrest
REDS SEE CHANCE v
TO EXPLODE BOMB
Monarchist Politicians
Believe Time Is Ripe
For Dictatorship
(Leaned Wire to Age-Herald.)
BLR LIN, Jan. 11.—President Ebert
In contemplating nominating a dicta*
tor to govern Germany, according to
the “Montag Font.” If Ebert should
adopt thin procedure he would pro
rogue the relehntag and send it home.
The president han given considera
tion to this most drastic step because
German politicians have been unable
to form a cabinet.
BERLIN, Jan. 11.—Vague ru
mors of a threatened revolution are
keeping over Germany. For more
than a month the leading middle
party politicians have been endeav
oring to form a cabinet. No cabinet
has b$en formed, and Germany is
getting restless. If the farce con
tinues for another fortnight, there
are reports that both the com
munists and monarchists would like
to take advantage of the popular
dissatisfaction with a “Putsch.”
The hints of revolution are vague
and may be groundless, but the mere
fact of their circulation tends to dis
turb the economic recovery that began
with the adoption of the Dawes plan.
Reds See Opportunity
Some monarchist and semi-monarchist
politicians would like to experiment
with a dictatorship. Meantime, the
reds think the time is opportune to
stir up the proletariat. The commun
ists however, are more inclined to bide
their time, hoping that If the elements
of the right attempt a coup, they may
receive a stupendous setback which
will make the abortive Kapp revolu
tion appear as nothing in comparison.
Contrasted to these extreme cliques,
the average German wants peace and
the order that deserted Germany along
with the otherwise unlamented Honen
zoUerns. Because Germans do y®®-™
for order, many observers suggest that
a monarchist coup at this time, with
its pVomlse of a return to “the old days
When everything was In order, might
attract considerable sympathy.
Nation Frets
The unending and farcial efforts of
the politicians to build a cab.net from
the material afforded by the elections
in December are fretting Germany.
Chancellor Marx having
Finance Minister Luther now is
toying with the cabinet business, al
though he has not been given an offi
cial mandate by President ®bert to
form a ministry. Ebert Informally
asked Luther to form »ometlyii»* tha.t
might he called a cabinet and paraded
for public inspection.
Luther's chances are doubtful, al
though the nituation la in a flux and
has been for month, making state
ments as to the future almost guess
work. To outsiders, the fact that a
month’s efforts have failed to produce
a cabinet appear ridiculous, but It has
its unfortunate side since the national
restlessness may result seriously.
INDUSTRY, MADE FOR MAN
Dr. D. .1. Kram hays Human Perso
nality 1. Life'. Ore.te.t Thing
CHICAGO. Jan. 11.—Man was not
mads for industry, but industry was
made for man and human personality
is the greatest thing in human life.
Dr. Davlfi Jones Evans, pastor of the
First Baptist church, Kansas City, Mo.,
tonight told the Sunday Evening club
here. Christ, the speaker said, ignored
organized effort and paid little atten
tion to constitutional government.
‘‘His chief concern was with persons,
he said, “and the rescuing of man from
the tolls of tradition. He declared that
man was above even the Sabbath and
presented to the world the greatest ideal
we have of human society. Plato’s re
public was a "hoble example of Greek
thinking, Moores Utopia was a great
example of English thinking and "look
ing backward" is a fine example of
American thinking, but Christ presents
the Kingdom of Heaven, which is the
highest example of universal thinking
that we know of.”
Dr. Ernest Freeman Tittle stated that
evolution rightly understood Is a sup
port for religious faith.
“The man who wrote the story of
creation,” Dr. Tittle said, “never
lokoed through a telescope or a micro
scope. He was not writing it to secure
a doctor’s degree at the University of
Chicago, yet In spite of the unscientific
age in which he wrote, he would prob
ably start the story the same, if he 1
lived now with all the latest knowledge I
at his command.
ARCTICS. OS. HEARD
Norfolk Fob Plrki Up Explorer’s Tale
Of Distress
NORFOLK, Vo., Jou. 11.—The voice
of on explorer, his ship Imprisoned In
the frosen wastes of the Arctic, was
picked up here by an amatur radio fan
lost night and while neither the name
of the speaker nor the name of his ship
could be gotten because of periodical
stotio interference, enough o{ the far
away monologue was caught to reveal j
o connected story of weird adventure j
and privation.
The speaker appeared to be shouting 1
at the top of his voice. He declared
he was 3,000 miles away from home.
the temperature was 70 below zero, j
food was running low and the crew of
the frozen-in ship were killing walruses
and utilizing other crude foods obtained
from Eskimos to eke out their ex
istence.
SLAYER OF FIVE TO DIE
Ben Burchfield's Execution Is bet For
Wednesday 1
NASHVILLE, Tenn.. Jan. 11.—Ben
Burchfield of Bristol, convicted slayer
of five persons, will be executed in the
electric chair Wednesday unless it cah
be proved before that time by his at
torneys that Burchfield is mentally de-
fective, Governor Austin Peay decided
today.
Burchfield was convicted of killing
his wife, his child and three of his
wife's relatives in November, 1922, and j
of burning the house to oover the crime, i
An appeal was taken to the supreme
court, but before it could be consid
ered, the defense entered a plea of
present insanity. This plea waa dis
approved by a commission of experts,
and the court then affirmed the judg
ment.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82014519/1925-01-12/ed-1/?sp=1&st=text</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>Kansas City. Mo.. Jan. 12 Four
men early today seized Nathan A.
Bellis, 21. manager of a drug store.
while he was driving home, ana
forced him to return to the store
and open a vault from which they
stole $12,000 In cash, Bellis reported
to the police. The robbers escaped.
Give As Their Reason
That Reduction Has
Not Been Put In Force
In All The Cotton
Plants In The City.
Other Factories. Resume
Operations After Long:
Shutdown Textile Coun
cil Had Approved Cuts.
Fall River, Mass., Jan. 12. Three
hundred weavers employed la the Da
vie Mill here walked out this morn
ing in protest against a wage reduc
tion of ten per cent accepted by the
textile council last week. They gave
as reason for their action that the
reduction had not been enforced in
all mills in the city.
Give Their Reasons.
Spokesmen for the weavers said
that the ten per cent wage cut had
not become effective at the Parker
and Lincoln Mills, which are en
gaged in simHar work. Treasurer Is
rael Brayton of the Lincoln Mill said
that the reduction had been made
at that plant but that confusion had
arisen because the rate of pay varies
with th$ grade of goods manufactur
ed. The Barnard Manufacturing
Company reported thpt its weavers
objected to the reduction, but the
situation at other mills was quiet.
Work Resumed.
Flint Mill No. 2 resumed work to
day after a shutdown of fourteen
weeks, giving employment to about
200 persons. The Pocasset Mill which
had been running full time for sev
eral weeks was complelled to shut
down because of a break in the pow
er plant. This mill employs 600.
Tho SeacOnnet, Chace, Stafford, Ark-
wright and American Linen Kills,
which have been idle for several
months, failed to j-eopcu'with ho"e
dticed wage s'calo and ho increase of
employment whs reported at any eft
tho other plants, production was es
timated at C5 per cent of normal.
The wage cut was proposed by the
Fall River Manufacturers associa
tion and accepted by the textilo coun
ell, representing the six principal
unions of operatives. Unions affili
ated with the United Textile Work
ers of America have not accepted It.
A similar wage cut, proposed by the
New Bedford Cotton Manufacturers'
association to become effective next
Monday will be voted on this week
by the textile unions of that city.
WOMAN SCREAMS AS ADTO
RUSHES TOWARD HARTFORD
Windshield Shattered by Knob as
Pedestrians Hear Her Shout,
"Let Me Out."
The frantij screams of a woman
in an automobile as it sped along
Hartford avenue about 11 o'clock
lant night, and the crashing of the
windshield of the machine by a
doorknob thrown from within, start,
led residents of that section of the
city and a telephone call was sen!
in to police headquarters rcportins
the Incident. Louis Kirshnli of To
Monroe street, who called the police,
said that the woman wa,s sereaminj!
"Let me out, let me out," but appar
ently to no avail as the machine kep'
speeding along and was soon out o'
sight.
When passing in front
of 1I2
Hartford avenue the windshield wa.
broken on the machine, according Iff
tha report mado by Kirshnit, th'
missile used being a handle from oil'
of the doors on the machine.
The police immediately notified
the Hartford and Weft Hartford po
lice to be on the lookout for the ma
chine, and Sergeant George C. El
linger and Policeman Thomas C
Do'.an sot out in the police scrvic
car In an effort to locate the aut"
No further news has been learned o
the tar or its occupants.
PROF. WILSON DIES
He Was Head of the Vlil of Join
naliMii at Sjrniuc University
Was 41 Year of Age.
Syracuse. N". Y., Jan. 12. Proles
or George C. Wilunn, 41, head of th
college of Journalism, Syracuse uiv
vcrsity, today died after a few week;
;l!n's 01 heart ailments.
Professor Wileon directed the pul
llcity in connection with the recei
minion dollar drive of the untvcrsl:
and at its successful conclusion b
came ill. He quickly returned t
-lutv. however, and continued teach
i ing until the hoi! lay recess
taken. He was a graduate ot Tat
and was a teacher of English In pul
lie schools and at Syracuse unlverslt
before being given the chair in th
college ot journalism in 191$.
INSTANTLY RIIXKD
Bed Bank, N. J Jan. 12. Mi
Martha C. Behren, 2S, of Asbur
Park, was killed nearly instant1
when she wa thrown Into a telt
phone pole from an automobile
It also struck a pole on the road.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn82015313/1925-01-12/ed-1/?sp=1&st=text</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>CLEVELAND HAS
SOLVED CITY
TROUBLES
Party Organizations Have Been Eliminated and the City
Manager Plan Substituted —No More Election
Squabbles and Petty Political Fights—New Gov
ernment Based on Common Sense,
By FELIX F. BRUNER,
Editor The Indianapolis Times
CLEVELAND, Ohio, Jan. 12.—Cleveland has solved the
city government problem with which Indianapolis still is
struggling. It has done away with party organization in the
operation of the affairs of the city and has put them on the com
mon-sense basis used by other large business institutions.
While'the plan is admittedly not perfect—as no govern
mental plan ever was—citizens of this city are sure that it is far
superior to the old party system under which Cleveland suffered
as mueh as Indianapolis now is suffering. 9
The plan has done away with the party elections—which
never had any place in city government —and has made effi
ciency and ability the characteristics of city management. It
has done away with party conventions, such as the spectacle In
dianapolis will witness Friday; and it has done away with con
tinuous fights for party leadership, such as the one that now is
being waged in the Marion county courts and such as the ones
that will inevitably follow.
City Manager Plan
The Cleveland plan is THE CITY MANAGER PLAN OF
GOVERNMENT.
This plan is simple and is based on COMMON SENSE and
not political expediency.
The plan is that under which large business corporations
operate and it was adopted by large business corporations be
cause it is the BEST plan.
Briefly, Cleveland is governed by a manager and a board of
directors. The manager is employed by the board of directors.
The board is elected by the people of Cleveland in a non
partisan election. It is known as the city council.
So far as the administrative and legislative branches of the
government are concerned, the city councilmen are the only
elective officials.
A City Council
In Cleveland, the council consists of twenty-five members,
each of whom receives SI,BOO a year. This council elects a city
manager, who is executive head of the institution. He selects
department heads. There are no boards in Cleveland, such as
the board of safety, board of works, park board and board of
health in Indianapolis. These departments, and others are
looked after by department heads, just as they would be looked
after in any other business institution.
Cleveland pays its city manager $25,000 a year. The job is
a big job for a big man and necessarily must carry a compara
tively big salary, just as the head of any other corporation the
size of Cleveland or of Indianapolis would receive a big salary.
The Cleveland manager—at the present time he is W. R.
Hopkins, a native of Cleveland and a man of wide experience—
names these department heads
x LAW DIRECTOR, corresponding to the Indianapolis
corporation counsel.
PUBLIC SERVICE DIRECTOR, corresponding to the
Indianapolis board of wbrks.
Safety Director
PUBLIC SAFETY DIRECTOR, corresponding to the'
Indianapolis board of public safety.
DIRECTOR OF PUBLIC UTILITIES, who is the head
of municipally owned utilities, of which Indianapolis at this
time has none.
FINANCE DIRECTOR, corresponding to the Indian
apolis city comptroller.
WELFARE DIRECTOR, corresponding to the Indian
apolis board of health.
DIRECTOR OF PUBLIC PROPERTY AND PARKS,
who has duties similar to those of the Indianapolis park
board and who, in addition, is the custodian of all public
buildings and grounds, a duty divided in Indianapolis
among several departments.
TRACTION COMMISSIONER, who represents the City
in its relationship with transportation‘systems. The Ohio
public service commission has no control over local trans
portation systems as has the Indiana commission.
Under the Cleveland plan, the city council initiates public
policies, just as a board of directors initiates the policies of a
corporation, and the city manager, with his department heads
and their subordinates, carry them out.
In addition, Cleveland has a mayor, who is a member of the
council. He has very few powers, his principal job being that of
custodian of the “gates of the city.” He is referred to here as
the city’s glad-hand expert, the city manager confining his time
and energies to the city government,
Who Wants the
Things You
No Longer Need?
Used, but too useful to
throw away, describes
the state of many pieces
of furniture in the av
erage home.
If yoh would like to re
place some such items
now while sales are on
in the stores, yau con do
so without talcing a total
loss on the old ones.
Times Want Ads are the
little hustlers looking for
just snch Jobs. They And
ihe Indianapolis limes
COMPLETE WIRE SERVICE OP THE UNITED PRESS Jft. WORLD'S GREATEST EVENING PRESS ASSOCIATION</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87055779/1925-01-12/ed-1/?sp=1</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>BOB SLEDDER DIES
IN MARYLAND MISHAP
By Associated Press:
BALTIMORE. Jan. 11.—Lynn F.
Gruber, 22 years old, a divinity stu
dent of Western Maryland college,
was killed and six others suffered
injuries ranging from fractured
thighs and legs to bruises and con
tusions, when the hob sled which
Gruber was steering at Westminster
collided with an automobile late
last night. v</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-gregory-rasputin</id>
    <results>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1912-02-25/ed-1/?sp=22&q=Gregory+Rasputin+russian+czar+peasant+romanoff+alexis+guseva+yusupov+heliodorus+trufanoff+monk
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>RASPUTIN CONTROLS CZAR;
DOUMA FEARS ASTROLOGER
Kis Influence Over Nicholas Said to Menace Welfare
of Russia.
Jl Beware of
v.- After that,
sirnl-
iiic-tions cl
h Doiuna
he Ic-oiJe
M Petersburg Fel
the vear nineteen tve
all Is dark
Sucii was the dread prophecv
oger clelive-ed to Czar Nicholas seen
rears ago This prophet v and the Czar's
fear of some vague dange- account for
the tremcnd-'Us Influences which Gregorj
Rasputin a reputed holv man and mvs
tic. possesses over the Emperor to at
least declare those very near his imperial
majesty equallv Jealous with the mem
bers of the Pouma of Rasputin's powr
ful hold on the ruler's mind. Jinn- In
dined to religious mjstlclsm ami rr
uallsm
Rasputin, whose antecedents .11 ob
scure, and whose origin. It is lei'eveci
Is most humble, is now li still., 1 u
private apartments in the Winter 1'alioe
He Is busv consulting oracles th. stirs
cards, summoning spirits, gazing into
crystals, pretending to seek to learn
what this vear of fate holds f.ir his
credulous master Rasputin receives an
ample salarv and costlv gltts when the
Czar is pleased by his necrom imci
As these dispatches have told the
Douma has made Rasputin s control an
affair of national Importance vet this
mjstlc is onlj the last of a succession
of more or less holy men who have
plaved on the Czars fear and dread of
the occult
srrki lomfort of VI; sties.
In his youth Nicholas was fonder or
lifting a vil from a pretty race tlnn
of attempting to tear aw-iv the curtain
that hides the future But when he as
cended the throne he sought the help ot
a church of which he became the titular
head and of certain of Its theatric ex
ponents First came Father John, "the miracle
working priest" of Cronstadt. and Nich
olas really began his reign ruled bv the
advice of this village priest Father
John was regarded abroad as an ig
norant charlatan and a famtic The
Russian faithful looked upon him as a
aim.
Next Pobledonostzcth. Ihe famous pro
curator general of the Holy Sj nod
twisted the Czar around his thumb and
diverted him from the Mljerali-m he hoi
Imbibed in his vouth. Philippe Sundard
son w of a shepherd and born in the
French Alps, iuceeeded. then othe-rs
"dlvinel; inspired" Bishop Henegcnes.
Hellodarus. Abbot of Tsarltsvn. and the
rest of them.
Csnr Rnleil by ltniulln.
To-dav Rasputin is reigning over him
who reigns over Russia. Rasputin pre-The pol
sides nearly every evening at spiritist
seances which the Czar attends, and
often the Czarina, who-e nervous tem
perament has alwavs been highlv ex
ailed. The Imperial pair seem enrap
tured by the seer's solemn hocus-pocus
Often Rasputin Is commanded to call
up the spirits of former czars from
Peter the Great down. It Is scud Meh-.
olas believes his son and heir Is .1 rein
carnation of Peter, for the bov like so
many other boys not vet eight vear old.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045433/1913-05-24/ed-1/?sp=10&q=Gregory+Rasputin+russian+czar+peasant+romanoff+alexis+guseva+yusupov+heliodorus+trufanoff+monk
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Gregory Rasputin, one of the brightest
stars of the Russian court circles. Is the
son of a poor peasant and belongs to
the "Chlysty" order of austere preach
ers who flagellate their bodies and
preach privation as the only method of
expiating sins. Seven J cars ago he ob
tained the patronage of a Russian
countess, and with her aid he rose to
his present position by a very clever
ruse Complaining to the countess that
his name, Rasputin," which means
"rake." was not befitting so holy a man,
he begged her to get him an audience
with the Czar to obtain permission, to
change It The audience was granted,
and so was his request the ruler of
all the Russlas ordering that he should
henceforth be known as "Gregory JJovj."
Rasputin made a deep Impression upon
both the Czar and Czarina on account
of his marvelous memorj. He can re
cite whole chapters of the Bible by
heart and lnvarlajilj answers questions
addressed to him by apt quotations from
the Scriptures.
His success aroused Jealousy In the
Holy Sjnod. of which the Czar Is the
head, and a famous archbishop preach
ed agalnt his appointment as a priest
The prelate was banished and Ras
putin s triumph was complete He now
edits a paper, for the acquisition of
which the minister of finance oted him
a special grant of 300 000 roubles.
To the astonishing feats of micro
scopical writing should be added those
of an Englishman, near Manchester,
who claims to have produced the finest
examples of minute writing In the world
and the feats which he has accomplish
ed will take great effort to beat
In 18). In open competition, he wrote
the Lords Prajer nineteen times and a
few words oer within the space cov
ered bj a three penny bit every letter
being distinct He ultimately improved
on this effort by writing the Lord s
Prayer twenty-three times and forty-
nine words over within the space cov
ered by a three penny-bit this being
his record Equally remarkable was his
feat In writing the word Easter with
a capital "E" 57,11 times on the back
of an ordinary post card, the time occu
pied being twenty-one dajs This was
performed In connection with a compe
tition at Folkstone, and he won the
prize by some 21,000 words.
</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025316/1914-07-14/ed-1/?sp=5&q=Gregory+Rasputin+russian+czar+peasant+romanoff+alexis+guseva+yusupov+heliodorus+trufanoff+monk
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>14, WZAR'S ADVISER, BE- R(
c. ns AAIN THE .SUBJECT
F SPECU LATION.
irk St. Petersburg, July 13.-The mystic
lgq ay mmnk, Gregory Rasputin, a notable m
,hd fgurq, in the emperor's court, was Ti
lts stabbed recently by a woman named ar
G. d.seva, at his native village, Pekrov- se
to sky, in the province of Togolsk,' Si- co
:he beria. One report has it that he died, to
he another that his. Wound was not Si
is- mortal. ra
a The attack upon Rasputin has ex
m- cited intense interest in court and of- e,
the ficial circles here. He was recently in
tle recalled to the emperor's household vt
to after an absence of several months, to
re- and was credited with exercising an T,
influence over the emperor far more B
potent than any of the ministers. He sc
was regarded in some quarters as the in
eet siprete power behind the throne. pt
in- The woman Guseva had been track
eet inhg him for a long time. She finally
d- approached him in the guise of a beg
as gar and stabbed him in the abdomen
ere with a dirk. She was prevented from
her stabbing the monk a second time as
ige he lay on the ground by his son, who
seized her and held her until the po
lice arrived,
ton When arrested the woman declared
his she wanted to avenge one of Raspu
cal tin's girl victims, who is now In a con
ght vent. After being lpdgcd in a cell the
wtor woman attcmpttd to conmiot suicide
ion. by cutting her wrist with a piece 'of
the ilass.
The
the A Mysterious Man.
.did Ldndon, July 13.-Commenting on
the attack on Radmlutln, the Daily Mail
says:
"It will be a grilm irony of fate if
this mysterious monk meets death at
ro- the hands of a woman, for it was by
ad- his uncanny asCendancy over womltenl
the of every class, from the highest to the
be- lowest, that he raised himsnlf from oh
°ers scurity to the iiosition of implicitly
or- trusted councillor of the .Russian elm
ave peror.
na- "'The names of an almost endless 0
are series of the best known women in St.
in- Petersburg social circles have been c
idi- linked with that of this nmysterious
ials peasant's son. Women of ulblemislled
the reputation have fallen tinler Ihe un
ave explained but irresistible spell whicht e
Rasputin seemed to exerise."'
The Daily Chronicle's St. Peters- a
burg correspondent says it is believed
the attack on Rasputin was the out
come of a plot by adherents of the I
monk lIeliodorus, abbotl of Tsaritsyn
andt reactionary leader. Iloliodorus t
was banished fromtn St. Peterslurg hbe
cause tie censured Rasplltin's mode of
"liilng. -ie was also finfrmlcked by the
holy synod, tin action whtich ithrealened
to split the Russian orthodox church.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn87062268/1914-07-26/ed-1/?sp=16&q=Gregory+Rasputin+russian+czar+peasant+romanoff+alexis+guseva+yusupov+heliodorus+trufanoff+monk
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>RUSSIAN
THE ABSOLUTE
MS RO FCZAR
CLAIMED THAT NO GREAT EU
ROPEAN COURT IS NOW UNDER
SUCH MYSTIC SWAY AS IS EM
PEROR NICHOLAS.
BY ASSOCIATED PRESS.
London. July 26. The mystic pea-
sant-born Russian monk Gregory Kas
Putin, on whom a murderous attack
was made by a woman while he was
visiting hU home in a Siberian village
recently. Is described by the St. Iet
ersburflr correspondent of the Dally
Chronicle as "the absolute master of
the Russia It Is certain that no
great European court today Is under
such a mystic sway as that which
Rasputin has been reputed to have
over Emperor Nicholas of Russia and
the whole imperial household. It has
been the concern of Russia for three
years back.
The rise of Rasputin has been as
enigma to all the nobles of the court
who have not fallen under his in
fluence. His absence from St. Peters
burg', during which the attack upon
him came, was hoped to mean that he
had fallen into disgrace, but just pre
vious to the news of his being stab
bed, the announcement was made that
he had been recalled to the emperor's
palace.
This modern Richelioi?, is the son
of a fairly wealthy peasant of To
bolsk. He had but little schooling
and led an uneventful life until about
thirty years old, when he developed
religions fervor, became a lay monk
and went on a pilgrimage. At the
monasteries he visited, he picked up
some learning and also managed to
receive a letter of introduction to
Bishop Theofan at St. Petersburg.
This was In 1900. Through the in
fluence of the bishop, the peasant be
gan to meet the influential people of
the city and court. His mystic phil
osophy created interest, ami lie nad
the gift of repartee and polite con
versation. At first Rasputin stuck to his pea
sant garb, in which he made a pic
turesque figure. But soon lie took up
an elegant style of dressing and liv
ing, which excited the envy of Bish
op Theofan. Tho bishop obtained an
order to exile Rasputin to Siberia. But
not only did Rasputin's appeal to the
Tsar save him, but caused the bishop
to be dismissed to Poltowa without
even time to see his dying father.
Other powerful officials tried to
check the advance of Rasputin only
to find themselves in disfavor. Ras
putin become the intimate of Use royal
family, gave orders to the ministers
and conducted himself as the supreme
power.
Tho only successful attempt to in
duce the court to send Rasput in away
resulted disastrously for the plotters.
Before leaving, Rasputin warned the
empress that misfoioine was bure to
follow. When the heir to the throne
fell ill, the frightened empress recall
ed the favorite in haste.
Since his return. Rasputin's power
has continued to grow. His counsel
is called for in deciding every ques
tion of Importance. It is said on high
authority that he brought about t!ic
ministerial change last year that saved
Russia from a war with Australia. He
lived as a prince, with a magnificent
vilia at Yalta, in Crimea. Ore of his
daughters by his peasant wife id be
ins; educated sn an aristocratic girls'
college in St. Petersburg and is chief,
companion of the emperor's daugh
ters. Rasputin is even reported to
address the Tsar as "tnou" ard "thee"
a freedom denied even the errand
dukes.
A month agi Rasputin was ordained
SB .J"
1 TL
rrs
o-in-i
USE IT
For Babies. Fornrlekl'r
neat. After Bhairinor. Artr
ine Mtn. JKm a rm nnwriar. A
a foot powder. Really Indispensa
ble. In sifter top cans. At drug
gists, 15 cents.
V
2.
a priest by a minor bishop of his na
tive district. This act had aroused
the antagonism of the powerful heads
of the church. It is with these big
ecclesiastics that Rasputin will now
have to deal in holding his position.
HERESYCASE
OE WIDE NOTE
TO BE REVIVED
THE FAMOUS "KIKUYU CONTRO
VERSY WILL BE REOPENED
AT MEETING OF CONSULTIVE
BODY ANGLICAN CHURCH.
BY ASSOCIATED PRESS.
London, July 26. The heresy case
of some months ago, known as the
"Kikuyu controversy,' is to be re
vived at the meeting here of the Cen
tral Consaltive Body of the Anglican
church. It was to this body that the
Archbishop of Canterbury referred the
charges brought by the Bishop of
Zanzibar against the missionary
Bishops of Uganda and Mombasa, Af
rica, for administering communion to
non-conformists.
The controversy 4s largely one of
church discipline, but involves the se
rious question of high and low church.
The low churchmen defend the Afri
can bishops in holding service with
and giving commanion to members of
the Presbyterian, Methodist and otner
n on -conformist sects, since they look
forward to amalgamating with these
bodies. But the high church party
says that such, communion is impos
sible because of differences in doctrine
and therefore stands in the way of a
union of the Church of England with
the Greek and Roman Catholics in a
single Christian church.
The consultive body will place its
findings with the Archbishop, as pri
vate of England, who will pronounce
judgment later.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn84026925/1914-08-14/ed-1/?sp=4&q=Gregory+Rasputin+russian+czar+peasant+romanoff+alexis+guseva+yusupov+heliodorus+trufanoff+monk
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>DOOM OF THE ARISTOCRACY
One of the Promised Results of Great
War in Europe.
Speculation as to the effect of the
war upon the European monarchies is
most fascinating, especially to Americans
who have an ingrained suspicion
of every form of government save theix
own. There are many who maintain
that it is a war of dynasties, entered
upon for territorial greed or because
of animosities of the reigning houses.
The Hapsburgs are fighting to extend
their boundaries toward the Aegean, the
Hohenzollerns have dreams of world
dominion and the greater glory of their
name; the Romanoffs are seeking to
maintain their hold upon the loyalty of
the Slavs outside of their empire and
to bind them more closely to St. Petersburg
so that the ultimate extension
of the Russian frontier to the Mediterranean
may be facilitated.
There is no doubt that these are
among the potential reasons for the
conflict. Hut they are not all the reasons.
The German army is not merely
the kaiser's lighting machine. It is
Germany in arms. When 5,000,000 men
respond to the call to the colors, or
stand ready to respond, to carry out
the plans of the kaiser, it is pretty safe
to assume that the cause of the kaiser
is the cause of Germany, and that national
as well as dynastic reasons lie
behind the great enterprise. The same
reasoning will apply to Russia and to
Austria only to a lesser degree. Germany
and Austria are in alliance because
of their common interests. They
both seek an outlet to the Aegean and
to the markets of the east. The dynastic
policies are supported by the
commercial interests of the two em
|J1IC8( (IIIU 111 i(u^r iavuoc iuv aiuii* i.
zollerns and the Hapsburgs art- the
spokesmen for and leaders of their
people and are leading in the direction
in which they would go.
There is no dynasty in France to be
glorified, but the French people have
been arming for forty-four years for
this great conflict. The Frenchmen
who took their hoardings from their
stockings to help their government pay
the indemnity to Germany in 1870 have
been waiting for the opportunity to get
it back again, and their children have
inherited the same relentless purpose.
They have watched and waited nearly
half a century for this one great,
over-whelming, all-absorbing opportunity
of "revanche!"
Despite the fact that the ambitions
of the people and the dynasties are in
accord, the effect of the war upon monarchical
institutions will be momentous.
The spirit of democracy is
abroad. It has practically abolished
the British house of lords. It has forced
the establishment of a parliament
in Russia. It is so active and alert in
Germany that the Social Democratic
party is the largest and most powerful
political organization in the empire.
In France it overturned the monarchy
nearly half a century ago, and is now
so firmly established that only the
wildest dreamers ever imagine that republican
institutions can be displaced.
It is regnant in Portugal and nearly so
in Spain. A nation in arms, as Germany
now is, will not long be content
to remain a nation without a ministry
responsible to its parliament. The
democratization of German institutions
is inevitable after the war, whatever
the result. The people, even in Russia
are no longer driven serfs. They think
they reason and a demonstration ot
the power of 5,000,000 men on the battlefield
will not be lost on the patriots
who wish also to demonstrate the power
of the same number of millions in
deciding at first hand the causes for
which they will take up arms. Whether
the kings and the emperors remain
on their thrones matters little. Great
Britain, though it retains the fiction of
a monarchy, is as democratic as the
United States, and its parliament responds
with greater precision to popular
sentiment than the American congress.
The war means the end of autocracy
whether the kings remain or
not ?Philadelphia Ledger.
IS RUSSIA'S REAL RULER
Illiterate Siberian Monk Said to be
Power Behind the Throne in Czar's
Realm.
While Rasputin was visiting his
family recently in his native town of
Krekovksy, province of Tobolsk, Si
beria, a woman named Guseva plunged
a dagger into his abdomen. She wished,
she said, to put an end to the awful
evil wrought by this man in Russia by
his impostures and intrigues under the
guise of prophet.
Rut Rasputin will recover. And when
lie does, woe to his enemies! He
blames it all on Heliodorus, abbot of
Esaritsyn, whom Rasputin, by his inlluence,
drove from the imperial court.
Rasputin will live, he declares, in spite
of Heliodorus; and he will take a terrible
reckoning.
Since the spring of this year keenest
watchers of the Russian skies have
taken a second long look at Gregori
Rasputlin. This strange, quiet personality,
unobtrusive and yet conspicuous,
used to be the target mainly for scandal
mongers and for the vast number
of Russians who are disgusted at the
character of the dominant intluence
in the czar's household. Rut recently
people of harder liber?ambitious men
high in the councils of the empire?
who are struggling and scheming
against one another, and the ablest
members of the foreign embassies, who
are seeking to trace the motive springs
for the working of the czar's will, tind
in Rasputin their most absorbing problem
The politically ambitious ay him
court by sending their wives to the
receptions arrangi d by his devoted followers.
The diplomats must glean
what they can from the outside, for he
does not cultivate the acquaintance oi
foreigners. None of them but would
admit that the half illiterate Siberian
peasant exercises greater sway over
the mind of the czar and his sovereign
decisions than did the austere and exalted
l'obedonostzoff, procurator of the
Holy Synod, over the stern policy of
Alexander III.
Middle sized, middle aged?he is
about 48 years old?of spare, wiry
frame, letting his light brown hair and
beard grow freely in peasant fashion,
Cregori Rasputin holds attention til
lirst sight by his remarkable nose and
eyes. His gait and his dress are those
of the devout, humble lay brother and
Scripture reader, which is the Russian
social type to which lie approximates.
Rut his large, strong, well-set nose is
that of a man of commanding will and
authority, and he has the large, bluegray
eyes of the seer who will not be
drawn into discourse on the plane of
ordinary mundane affairs.
Some men have a kind of magnetism
other than that which manifests itself
on the intellectual or spiritual side of
the personality. It may be exerted,
physically, in the form of animal magnetism,
in the "laying on of hands" to
allay nervous torture, and even in such
healing processes as osteopathy or
bone setting. The most competent objective
psychologists who have studied
Rasputin declare that he possesses this
animal magnetism to quite an amazing
degree, and that as a dynamic human
organism he is a phenomenon.
Much in Russian tradition favors the
periodic appearance of some such wizard
and soothsayer. These may be
charlatans for the most part, but now
and again they prove to be something
more. To say that the world has outgrown
them is quite erroneous as regards
Russia.
Among the scattered pastoral villages
around Tomsk, where Rasputin
lirst began to exercise his strange
power nearly twenty years ago, the
conditions of daily life and the vocabulary
in which the people exchange their
thoughts are not essentially different
from what they were two or three centuries
ago, nor so very different from
the early ages when a Peter the Hermit
could inspire a crusade.
None of Rasputin's followers thus
far, whether dupe or devotee, has come
fooiirnivl in hie hniir of L'rcnlnpsS to de
nounce him as an impostor. Such a
one would assuredly run no risk if he
did, for Rasputin is most cordially
hated both by the police and the press
censorship. To people familiar with the
habits of Russian life it would have
sounded incredible a year ago had they
been told that the government bureaucracy
and the radical intelligence
would ever agree on anything. Yet today
they are as one in their antagonism
to Rasputin.
In a recent Duma debate a much-respected
leader of the Liberals, Mr.
ICphremoff, declared "that the highest
affairs are settled in the highest
spheres by an obscene charlatan." The
press censorship allowed this to be
published broadcast, and the crown
prosecutor has taken no action. The
campaign against Rasputin is allowed
to proceed publicly on lines which
among decent Russians are far more
Biilnrarolvn i,f povepencp fur t h*> throne
than anything that is secretly circulated
from the revolutionary printing
presses.
The political hatred directed against
Rasputin is based on the fact that he
is the incarnation of irresponsible, oneman
power, the result being the absolute
repudiation not only of constitutionalism.
but of the actual administration
and bureaucratic system, or indeed
of any system at all. He has
checked, nonplussed and baffled the
clever men in the governmental machine
and the wily men in the Holy
Synod. In the duma, some weeks ago,
Mr. HilinkofT read a letter of the present
procurator of the Holy Synod, Mr.
Tabler, in which the latter thanked
Rasputin for allowing him to retain his
high office! Tabler denounced this as
malicious tattle, but he did not deny
the specific allegation.
The only minister of the czar who
showed open enmity to Rasputin was
Kokovtzoff, and Kokovtzoff had to go.
Wandering about the corridors of
Tsarkoe-Selo palace in felt slippers,
like the most intimate member of the
household, Rasputin waited for Prime
Minister Kokovtzoff to come out from
an audience in the czar's cabinet, and
said to him quietly:
"Well, how much hast thou stolen
today?"
KokovtzefT flushed angrily and moved
off, but he could neither say nor do
anything.
A few weeks ago a governess of the
czar's youngest daughters was standing
at their chamber door at bedtime.
Their father had gone into bid them
good night. Rasputin was about to
follow when the governess barred his
way, saying that the young grand
duchesses were retiring for the night.
Rasputin made no reply, but forbore to
enter. The czar, when he came out,
thanked the governess for her watchfulness
over his daughters, but in less
than a week she was given notice that
her services were no longer required.
Each step of Rasputin's progress has
been taken with the help of women
devotees. He has a quiet, well-modu
luted, "warm" voice, and uses at all
times the archaic "thee," "thou"
phraseology of the Bible?which sacred
book, except for a few simple devotional
works of the old Orthodox
church, is the only literature he has
ever read. First in western Siberia,
and later along the Volga, he used to
sojourn as Scripture reader in the
houses of the provincial merchants*
and others of the peasant class who
had prospered in a worldly way. These
men would often have money enough
to be able to indulge their wives in any
luxury, but the simple elementary
life in those remote districts provided
no means of relaxation. The women
would frequently drop into the state of
nervous depression which is the common
malady of idle rich womankind
the world over.
'I'lw.n frnm htillsolinli] til household
spread the rumRasputin.
the Scripture reader, had the marvelous
secret of dispelling this restless,
nervous feeling. Kastward from Moscow
he attained some fame as a "healer"
anion? bourgeois religious circles.
It was part of Rasputin's practice to
use absolute patriarchial directness in
his talk with his women followers, no
matter what the subject discussed
might be. The simple words he used
in relation to the elementary facts in
human life would sound coarse to cultured
ears. He believed, moreover, in
the "laying on of hands," and practiced
it literally. This reputation proved
nothing in his disfavor, and he advanced
into the more select circles as
the center of religious assemblages.
A lady of the Karnovitch family,
whose sister is now Countess Hohenfelsen,
murgantic wife of the Grand
Duke Paul, first brought Rasputin to
St. Petersburg. There was not much
pretense of religious pietj about her
salon, but the "healer" was cultivated
as a new diversion in a blase existence.
In fact, the guests looked on
him somewhat in the light of a spiritual
medium, although Rasputin has
always repudiated any suggestion of
"seances" or of hypnotism. His absolute
sway over many people, especially
women, and notably the empress,
and their passiveness under the spell of
his personality undoubtedly partake in
the broad sense, of hypnotism. Hut
Rasputin practices none of the hocuspocus
of the craft.
Rasputin's enemies charge that he
holds and makes silent use of certain
ambiguous messages from the empress
indicating his complete dominion at
the palace of the czar. He was introduced
there by iMme. Vyrbova, the wife
of a naval officer and the most intimate
of the empress' ladies-in-wait
ing. He goes two or three times a week
to the palace, remaining from morning
till night, and is sent for by telegram
whenever the court moves from one
place to another. In every direction
his influence is felt. The dowager em
press, however, is an avowed antlRasputinite,
and since the "monk's"
sway set in she has rarely seen her son
the czar, or her daughter-in-law except
at public ceremonies.
The crowning miracle of Rasputin is
this: He has moved the empress, who
for nearly twenty years that she has
shared the Russian throne has cared
for nothing outside of her domestic affairs
and who has not shown the
slightest intellectual curiosity about
anything, into an ardor of political interest
sympathetic to that in which the
czar is acting and working, neither
through his ministers nor the people,
hut through a Siberian peasant who
can scarcely write his own name?an
avowed mystery man who represents
absolutism incarnate. Neither the imperial
bureaucracy nor the elected legislature
has been able as yet to bring
Nicholas II., into definite light as a
reigning sovereign. And now, under
the will of a human enigma, behold
this same sovereign autocrat emerging
and asserting the authority that bewilders
alike the defenders and the
enemies of his throne!</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058396/1914-08-15/ed-1/?sp=19&q=Gregory+Rasputin+russian+czar+peasant+romanoff+alexis+guseva+yusupov+heliodorus+trufanoff+monk
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE STANDARD MAGAZINE SECTION OGDEN, UTAH, AUGUST H
TiW'.-C.ar of .,11 ih. Russia is
onli-tlie first lieutenant in tho ruK-i -sKlp
jot"K usui. i The ponor behind
thlItCCn1' of the greatest of all ab-
soqJejrL'ui opcan monarchies. Is a
iSlberjan and that .Siberian Is only
a fWWint monk who until l v.
year a?u ministered t" the lowly
of His. province and two women
who .came under the spell of his re
ligious teachings
The story ot" this strand- author
Hlty of the most despotic nation of
the Cauca.cion o ld i a me out w Ih :i
ia few weeks ago Czar Nicholas or
dered his court physh Lan, I rof.
Sergius. -Pet rov itch Kederoff to Tyu-
men, Siberia, to attend the monk.
On th $ame trnin rode the lad in
waltinjj to the Lmpn The monk,
t Gregory- Rasputin, is suffering from
ft severe' wound inflicted by a wom
an v hc tried to kill him.
Till- (soman Gusc-va. the would-
aas4fUnj declared to the police
Lnd newspaper orrespondentl 1 1 I
-ehe h.ul lout, uo dilated killing Ras
Hputln and thus put an end to "the
awful evil wrought by him In l:us
Hsla by his Impostures under the
jguise of a prophet."
She declared "he hail shaken
H Christianity, was sowin,- tempta
tion anl was blasphemously mock-
it is all that cursed Heliodprus,
Abbot of Tsaritsyn. Hut to the on
fusion of himself and all my ene
mies I will live and they will h i
nooses put around their necks.
Heliodorus was a great rival of
Rasputin in the Russian capital,
whence he was reiently banished,
owing tfi Rasputin's influence with
the Emperor.
Rasputin is recovering from his
wound.
CZ iRTN IMPRESSED
Bl OCC1 Ut POM ERS
It is a curious story, that of the
monk Rasputin, and one which has
been told only In scraps. Two
years ago hi- bobbed up in sudden
prominence because his prophecies
and spiritualistic seances had
ome to the attention of the Czar.
Not only dlil Nicholas take much
stock In him, but the Czarina was
Impressed by his occult powers, ami
uulte like the obscure hero of the
Cairy books. Gregory Rasputin
found grand dukes and cabinet
mlnlateve kowtowing to him. He
had free access to the royal fwmlly,
and the Czar of all the Russia
asked his, advice on all sorts of im
portant affairs of State. So great
is his Influence that he has been
styled the real ruler of Russia.
A .-k ten of the monk whi. h wa-
prlntcd In the Novoc Vrcmya, the
semi-official Russian newspaper.
and suppressed before It rained
general Circulation, aives an Inter
esting insight into the man's char
acter. T l;nw Rasputin," declared the
wi id r, "and 1 can speak about! him
from toy own Impressions. SasOtlOV
brought this 'saintly old monk' to
me at the height of his glory about
two years ago. The old monk aiued
with me and W bad a long discus
sion. 'At flrt he appeared to me as a
rather youthful peasant about
10, neatly dressed His face was
that of a drunkard and his Vest less
Attempted Assassination
of the Peasant Monk
Rasputin, Reveals dBi
the Fact the Czar P
Goes to Him for Di- lfc-i-" m
rection As to Affr
ssfB? EasH
V
f y'-i log- trie most hob fi elln ;a of true
nehesers." and she added that 'he
v enjoyed a!. .-oii.t.' immunltj and had
openly a nd 1 1 houi con ciencc
i j rulin;,l II,.- lives ot ourin' girls."
r I. as a simple Christian, could
j, j not suffer this abuse of the church,
l I vant'-d to kill him In I ea I
fWent. to Yalta, bul could not ap
l j proach him becausi In was so
closely surrounded bj urlstoci itic
women followers
"I regret that I failed to kill him.
n '-ll the same, he will not live. The
Rusi-i.in peopb v.. ii nol end such
1,1 Kdlsgracc
jjB a-'-putln. In nn inter lew, said:
JKisiaL cRviler
e.N'es, his low voice, resembled those
of a monastery servant or a psal
mist. His speech win abrupt and
he used at times mjflterlous expres
sions. "At first i surprised lhat
sinh a half suae peasant from
Siberia could not only find his way
to st. Petersburg, but that he could
find a welcome reception at the
homes of the very highest society.
After having spoken t" Rasputin,
i convinced mysell that he. knew
how to produce an Impression. He is
a natural philosopher, coming from
th- depth.-, almost Illiterate, but
well learned In Soripturei a man
who a Iks about religion like a
grn mophone record and endowed
with natural enthusiasm.
"Some of his rayinps Im
pressed me for their orljrinalitv
nnl -ven for their depth. Thus the
oracles of old spoke in a stats
of delirium there was some
thing absurdly wise in his enig
matic words. Some of Rasputin's
ideas seemed to me to be near the
ai etic and stole philosophy, and
his hara terlxatlon of some priests
and dignitaries struck me as very
keen and correct. The first Im
pressdon made upon me was a Kuod
one I thought he was a cunning
peasant, but naturally religious,
capable of makinc: people wake
from their lethargic sleep as far
as faith was concerned. Rut I did
not like so much his fancy boots
and the fait that he was going
from my house to call on a certain
1 n d
REQUIRED TO CAM,
n t I KTAIN LADY.
should very much like to re
maln In mir house.' he said to me.
but I hove been invited to go there
a nd I must go.'
"1 was also surprised that Ras
pulln kissed ladles' hands ou bid
ding them good-bye. A rathfr
Strange saint. I thought, one of
those that occasionally make their
appearance in fashionable drawing
rooms. 1 had heard some ot my
friends praising Itasputln, but soon
strange stories about Rasputin be
gan to reach me.
"Then Rasputin lost the confi
dence ,,f ths Well known Bishop
Toy fan win. bad hrst patronized
him. A certain prominent lady
even went to Siberia for the pur
pose of Investigating the stories
about his mode of life and found
evidence to corroborate them. The
Left newspapers branded him as
a swindler and a tharlutun such as
tho world had not seen before, and
fit one time It seemed as though
bin Influence had waned. Suddeuly
he came back to me last summer
from Jerusalem
"This time he was no longer
dressed quite so neatly as before.
He told mo about a tree that Lot
had planted and aided that tho
cross upon which Christ was cruci
fied was made from that same tree.
"Gregory needed the legend of
the tree of Lot to pro e to me that
although Lot was a sinner, his sin
w.i- lorgiven. as Christ was crucified
for us and thus redeemed all of the
Sins of the world Crcgory needed
this in order to answer my ques
tion: is it true. Gregory, that you do
not lead a very pure life
"He answered evasively, 'The
people arc slandering me. They
are telling many falsehoods ahou
me.'
lie added that perhaps he was
a sinner, that all people were sin
ners, but that It was necessary to
understand things properly
BISHOP C U.I.n IIIM
ENUI T Vt 9ERPENT.
ne day Bishop Oermogen said
to ',regor Rasputin. So you know.
Gregory, 1 used to look upon you
as upon a holy man; now I regard K:
you as an enticing serpent! I for- IS,
bid you to enter the home of an IE
orthodox family.' nf
"Grecory felt offended at this.
but paid no heefl to the nlshop's Blm
word? When the question arost at
the holy synod as to having 'ircsrory fig,,
ordained as a priest Bishop Ger- fflfc"
nioL-cn rose up against hltn, rnri it S.
was at this point that the Bishop
had his downfall. I
"The almost Illiterate, dissolute I
monk proved to be a great power in
these days of the twentieth century. i-
When we are entertalnlnR lords and I
eentlemen. scientists and authors t
in St. Petersburg''
The monk's affairs with women
seem to have been Innumerable. I
and he wielded preat Influence over I
the wives and daughters of nobles S
and officials high in the Russian c.v
court. Stories of midnight prayer Wy
meetings, to which only young worn- EV;
im
en were admitted, are told, and now 11
Kasputln turned out all the lights IH
and the "services" continued until
morning. Rasputin is said to have II
been the avenging power behind the IM
ritual murder'' case at Kief. nh n
except for worldwide publicity, the J
Innocent Jew Mendel Bellis. would
in all probability have been done to HH
death as a victim of religious HHJ
hatred.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045462/1916-12-03/ed-1/?sp=37&q=Gregory+Rasputin+russian+czar+peasant+romanoff+alexis+guseva+yusupov+heliodorus+trufanoff+monk
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>WHO IS RASPUTIN?
O.v VT r? By LUCIAN SWIFT KIRTLAND K.
LJIX niftnthsairn. tt'hnn \lr. kirthum J ?nnnur?. hi?? TKm?
left for Russia, we asked him to
find out and write for us the real
truth about Rasputin, the mysterious
monk who is said to be the power
behind the Russian throne. Mr.
Kirtland was granted exceptional
facilities for securing information:
we believe his article to be the first
really authoritative statement of the
facts published in America. It is a
story of fascinating interest a figure
out of the fourteenth century influencing
the destinies of a twentiethcentury
nation. We shall see in the
next decade a mighty conflict between
the forces of progress in Russia,
strengthened by the present war, and
the forces that in the past have been
responsible for Rasputin and the
medievalism which he represents.
The Editor.
I MISSISD having dinner with Rasputin
by one day. Every intricate
detail had at last been arranged. Although
reported to lie visiting friends
in Siberia, Rasputin had come to Petrograd,
and was to have been motored in a
closed car to a private apartment for the
dinner. Since the attempt on his life, last
spring, in one of the exclusive eating
places of fashion, ho now never appears in
a restaurant.
For six weeks I had manceuvered,
reaching for this wire and theu for that,
ill U II T l__ 1I...1 T 1 J il. _ A
uiuu iinany 1 Knew iiun i null me rigm
one?for in Russia every one ean be
readied by some wire. The point was,
to find the man whom Rasputin could not
deny, and then to find the man who could
bring pressure on that man. Fortuitously,
1 found that third man, and then I knew
that I was well ou my way to Rasputin.
And then, with the last detail completed,
1 was called away t wenty-four hours too
soon. By the space of that one day I
missed meeting the most interesting character
in Russia?the great, towering
monk, Gregory Rasputin, who from behind
the throne of Muscovy for the past
decade lias held in the mercy of his
power the dictation of the weal of the
Empire.
It is neither necessary nor discreet to
say who my acquaintance was, nor who
it was that knew Itaspntin. Emphatically
it is necessary to omit tolling the intrigue
of the pressure that was brought to
hear. But the man who knows Rasputin
1 is perhaps the only man who has ever
really known the monk intimately, and
who has ever been his confidant. He
promised to toll me, as a prelude to the
dinner, tho secret of just who Rasputin is,
and to reveal the mystery of how he arose
to his power.
To get to my informant's house I was
led from tho sunshine of the broad, roughly
cobbled street into a court-yard, and there
we found a door leading to a long tlight of
dark stairs. We climbed until just under
the roof, and nressed a hell. Ktons enme
and a door was unlocked. Wo slipped in
quickly, as if there were furtive eyes
watohing. Where the trail of Rasputin
reaches there is always clandestine slyness.
The man himself came to thedoor.
He pushed open a door and led us through
some rooms until we came to an inside of
f i i i
I^Bmi
ji..
m
mm
flee, a musty place crowded with heavy, sa
rich furnishings. as
A hove the desk hung a picture of Rasputin.
Our host reached up his hands to ar
each side of the frame and looked into the kt
eyes. yc
"The eyes are of fire,'' he said, "living yt
fire!" in
Most men hate Rasputin, hut many or
obey his commands, as do almost all sh
women. ne
"Look at those lips," he continued? in
"the thin lips of a master. No; you see, be
they are not thick, stupid, sensual lips.
And now look at his eyes. Look deeply, di
and maybe you will understand something ht
of tlwi t?ni?
Hp sat down at thp desk and talked th
across it toward me. be
"How eould a moujik," he began, "an wi
ignorant peasant born in the heart of sw
Siberia?how do you suppose that such sp
a man could rise in proud Russia to be a 111
1 >owpr greater even than the throne? I lei
tell you again: it was his tire, his sensuous loi
bursting passion of life. He can dissipate av
the enn ni of a jaded court and not be ye
drained. He has wits, but so have thou- rii
""""I;
HMMggraHr
^Hhh
nds. His presence rekindles dea
hes. They are subjugated by his powe
"Yes, Rasputin was a moujik, a pea
it. Everybody knows that; but tht
low little more. They think he
>ung. He is not. He was born fifty-tw
>ars ago, born in the province of Tobols
a little village, tie uvea in a nouse i
le room, where they all slept in reekii
eepskins on the stove in winter, and
iw-cut hay above the cattle in the sur
er. Was that a beginning for sleepii
'tween silken sheets in a palace?
"Rasputin was big and strong, but 1
dn't like to work. He liked to talk at
liked to quarrel, and he stirred up h
spiration for talking and quarreling i
e vodka shop. Are thinking heads
found in such a village to match one
its against? There was nobody to ai
er his questions. And, in his hig
irits, he rebelled and wrangled an
ade trouble. Everybody for miles aboi
trued who Rasputin was. including sue
:'al noblesse as is mustered in such a fa
ray province. At first he amused the:
ikt'l aristocrats by his boisterous rove
>s and strange moods, but they couldn
iiuuugv U?1? iuuj nuuicu 111111 w uc a
buffoon, but he was too much their master.
He made a mockery of his superiors,
and victims of the women. When the
village grew too narrow a field for his
adventures,howandered awayas a pilgrim.
"Rasputin had never had a day of
schooling, and he had the direst ignorance
of anything that he might find in the
outside world, except what his priest had
told him of big cities with great churches,
and of monasteries and convents and holy
places. It was the betrinnine of an eduea
tion to make his way from village to village,
trying tho mettle and temper of strangers
with his questions and high spirits. You
can picture him when ho reached Moscow,
tramping around and around the great
churches and palaces with open mouth
and staring eyes.
"He saw that men had done bigger
things in the world than he had ever
dreamed of. He docided that reading and
writing must have had something to do
with this power. A Rasputin does not
have to look long in this world for teachers.
He has had many. Amidst various hotblooded
ud ventures he found time to watch
fair fingers point out the letters of the
alphabet.
"Rasputin's development seems always
tn hnvfi nrlvnnpoH inmnc Maoaaw ?_
ceived him uncoutli, uneducated, and
untamed. He had had only the most
shadowy ideas of the power and organization
and the dogma of the great Russian
Church. Something in the refinement of
the city and the art of the wonderful
churches began to smooth away the outside
of his uneouthness. The paradox of
it all was that Moscow was now a disappointment
to his new moods. Incredible
?yes; but this central Siberian moujik
was demanding something from the great
Moscow churches that they could not
give. Rasputin told his friends that the
church lacked passion. Their answer
was that the materialism and commercialism
of a great city had engulfed the church
?that he should go to Kief if he wished to
finH linlinpsa iinonntA?ninnt.AH
"Again he picked up his pilgrim staff.
At Kief he found another great city; but
the atmosphere was narrow and bigoted.
For a time he thought that this bigotry
meant life. But a man of Rasputin's keen
senses can not long be fooled by the specious,
and he was soon angered by the
corruption that he found. Possibly?who
d can deny??this hot-blooded, intemperate,
r. riotous, desirous wanderer was honestly
s- seeking some unfaltering purity of relig>y
ion as a salvation outside himself against
is the raging fires within, the very fires which
o later were to carry him to the pinnacle
k, of power and might,
of "He heard of Holy Mount Athos, and
lg again he took up his wanderings. Again
in he found pettiness. Pilgrims were going
t ?f
11- liU UWUSttlClU. Xi.%3 JUIUCU IUOI11. a oaiu
lg that Rasputin was impressionable. Xow
came the second great evolution in his
lie life. It came from the sea. To this child
id of the steppes, the expanse, the colors, the
is storms, the peace, the majesty, the power,
?t and the mystery affected him as someto
thing new and revolutionary from Qod's
i's hand. The effect upon his life was treii
mendous. He ceased being a simple
;h mottjik upon a quest, he himself not half
i,l L-nnu'inor whnt ho u-whod to find. He had
it been struck with the conviction, the reve h
lution. that if lie could feel this inspiration
r- of the sea, which others could not feel
so until his words and his fire discovered the
1- treasures for them, he must then l>e |>os't
sessed of powers which they did not</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030214/1917-01-03/ed-1/?sp=3&q=Gregory+Rasputin+russian+czar+peasant+romanoff+alexis+guseva+yusupov+heliodorus+trufanoff+monk
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Rasputin Lured to Death
in Palaee, London Hears
CaUaT*l Aid Involved by Story of Assassination?\ loir in
Ice Door ot Priest's Tomb, Dispatches from
Petrograd Declare
...n. .Ian. l'he morn me ne*??
papers in their I -UsBBtehel
itature BtariSS Sf th(. rrpurtril
..??Ht)'. Raapatia, i'
sian monk who BSareisatJ su?-h inllu
er Eau pe? 01 n ici o as. The r<
b? fie death p( RasatiUi
ut'iitly are niukin?; ;i stir in llusnia. not
.iily OB ?iccout.t
tira relions
well known for?
mer member of the DasBS Sran
ikJBg o'T.
umption in the stones
is that Rasputin whs murdered, .uni
some of tho BCCOBflta SB] unqualifiedly
that 1 one story,
.lr..\e in an su
toinoH. Korok
hoTBTS bere bibb, h
to here bei n Rai
which in YusjuipotT Palace,
Il owned h\- the young Pi BCB
YussupofT, ?ericrHl Prince
YasSBpoff, aiii to K-nperor Nicholas.
Shsrta and Crie?* Heard
Afterward the r?o!u*e heard ?hot?
and cries comii-j*; from the Palace Gar?
den. Hastening there to make inquir-'
kB !?!..?d BS t? i in the
?Ti i. ihoB "?s? of
B h ich I haj were t o i ?i bad 1" SB
it ?a? mad.
MeB irditt*" to another ver
bodi of m tu
placad m
an aut<.ni(.,>' le. 11: erial
ear si d droi s to Petroasky
Inland, m th.- Neva. Invest i ?rat ion Snt
illl.l 8 llld.iv ltd to I:
of a fresh!;: made hole in the ire.
blood nii.l aBBB* footprlnti
bj D rers isaeaadad lata ths
??nil found the body nf RaspatiB.
Name- of Suspect? Veiled
?he aaasss of ths perron? BBspactsd
being concerned In the alleged mur?
der Hie no* printed, li.it it i i -luted that
jronng Pi ipoff, after ths
of the week end, quit Petrograd
mean estates, bul that he
quentl** returaed t.. the eapital.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045211/1917-01-03/ed-1/?sp=2&q=Gregory+Rasputin+russian+czar+peasant+romanoff+alexis+guseva+yusupov+heliodorus+trufanoff+monk
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>RASPUTIN'S DEATH
ENDS INTRIGUES
Slaying of Monk Closes Life
of Conspiracy and
Mystic Power
NOBLEMEN ASSASSINS
Act Believed to Be Connected
With Treachery of Pro-
Germans
LONDON, Jan. 3.
All detnlla contlnuo tn romo Hi from I'd
..fcgrad nbout tho vlolrnt tlonth of the Tttis
Han monk Haniiutln. tlioy wpnvr HipmRPlvM
Into a tnlo which rivals the moat fantastic
f-lcco of fiction.
Uasputln, who Is pnlil to bp Iho ennfoxnr
of both tho Hii'sl.in ("inr nml Ui Cznrinn,
li now reported to have boon ulnln by n
Kusslan notilemnli to hide rt ncnriitat In
VolvltiB powerful members of the UMIntt
ccurt.
The body win hidden In tlit Nnva tllvcr
tut was later recovered
On Friday night two young men, both
members of the highest circles of Husslnn
tioblllty. accompanied by another, whoso
r.amo Is said to be notorious throughout
tho nusslan Kmplre for his Intrlguos. drovo
In n limousine to a house owned by Prince
Yusupoff-SuninrokofC IJIston. About 3
o'clock on Saturday morning shots were
lieard in tho garden of tho house. Soon
rftcrward two big motorcars drove up to
tho house, one pnsslng into tho gnrden.
Tho authorities, having been Informed of
2
tho shooting, went to tho pln.ro anil upon in
vestigation found blood upon tho snow. No
body wns found, hnwever.
Another version stated that two men were
seen entering ono of the automobiles sup
portinr a Ubii-p between them that was
wrappid In a fur coat.
Prlnro Yussupnff Is married to a second
cousin of the I'zar. Ills wife. Princess
Irene. Is a daughter of Urnnd Diitto Alex
ander. WIKLDKD OURAY POWHIl
Kasptitin. who regarded himself a mystic
with divine powers, wielded greater Influ
ncc al tho itusalsin court than any other
man. Ho was feared even by the most
powerful nobles. It has been Bald that lie
was consultnl by tho f'zar on matters of
lato and that he was In the highest coun
cils on th.! evo of war.
This is tho third time that report has
coma out of Itussla announcing tho as
sassination of the notorious mystic and
adventurer, flrcpory Rasputin, who Is sup
posed to have exercised such an Intluenco
for evil upon the mind of tho Czar of
Itussla. The first time was In July, 1911.
when, exiled from Petrograd. he wns
stabbed by Julia Humva at Tyumen, Si
beria; then on May 11. lUlfi, his death wus
reported from Iiucharst.
It has been stated by those who have
been In a position to penetrate tho do
mestic surroundings or the Russian Im
perial family that the Interest of tho I'znr
In Rasputin wus purely that of an In
vestigator, who used the mnk us a means
to gather information from and at times
to communicate with the m.iss of the people
from whom his exalted birth and rank
separated him. Kruni Itasputln. It Is said.
Nicholas learned of the horrors of vodka,
and Immediately set about to eliminate
them.
When Rasputin lay wounded In Tyumen
In 1914 his Majesty sent to him the court
physician, Professor Serglus Pctrovltch. It
was then that Rasputin mudo this startling
accusation against Illlodor, "the mad monk,"
who Is now In Now York:
"It Is all that cursed Illlodor. Hut, to
the confusion of hlmsolf and my enemies,
I will live, nnd they will have nooses put
round their necks."
When Interrogated, the Gusevu woman
declared that she had attempted to kill
Rasputin because ho had spread tempta
tion among the Innocent. No connection
could be established between her and
Illlodor.
SUSPECTED AS PRO-GERMAN
The attempted assassination of last
spring Is supposed to have been duo to
political causes. Rasputin had been well
autualnted with lit-neral W. A. Souk
homllnoff, who was Russian Minister of
War during the fatal campaign In East
Prussia, when traitors were believed to
have betrayed the Russian armies In the
field anil left them without reserves of
munitions at home. In Juno, 116, Souk
homllnoff resigned and was later arrested
end lodged in the fortress of Peter and
Paul.
Among the witnesses sought was Ras
putin, who wus known for his pro-German
sympathies. It was said that he
had been discovered by the secret po
litical police and would create u Bensu
tion at the trial. Ueforo lie had a chanco
to tesllfy, however, ho disappeared. Then
came tho news of his assassination from
Bucharest, which, however, proved false.
His long immunity from arrest as a wit
ness Is said to have been duo to a certuln
clique of the Ministry, who, if not actually
pro-German, were nevertheless working for
a separate peace looking to a desertion of
Kngland and France and a subsequent
treaty with Germany.
The completo reorganization of the Min
istry under pressure of the Czar nnd'-'Duma
alike, a month ago. changed all that. The
trial of SoukhomllnolT was ordered, nnd
Itasputln waa brought to Petrogrud. whero
he lived under police surveillance, ready,
It has been reported, to tell all he knew.
Tho Czar first met Rasputin in 1805
through tho Countess Ignatieff, wife of a
former Governor of Hlberla, and much In
terested In tho cult of the Chylsty's sect of
flaggellants. which Rasputin was trying to
revive. In the Countess's circle, where tho
Czar waa then an occasional visitor, wcro
the Montenegrin Princess Mllitza, wife of
the Grand Duko Peter N'ikulalevltch Prlnco
Putjatln. Court Marshal Count fieticken
dorff. Prince Orloff, and. finally, General
Soukhomlinoff.
It has been said that when tho wur began
the genuine Muscovites gradually droppt.il
away from tho rlrrlii, leaving only Ilaltto
Russians, with German IdeaB, behind, nnd
that the circle then became the center of
German propaganda to which tlrussilux re
ferred in April. 19 m, when he took com
mand of the southern Russian armies und
said to the war correspondents:
J I "Not a line can you wrlto from here
vj.uct a message will go forth till something
vfiappens- In Petrograd they have a switch-
board with connections with lierlln."</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83030431/1917-01-07/ed-1/?sp=55&q=Gregory+Rasputin+russian+czar+peasant+romanoff+alexis+guseva+yusupov+heliodorus+trufanoff+monk
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>MYSTIC PEASANT
BOOSE. SAID TO
HAVE BEEN BUILT
FOR RASPUTIN By
THE CZAR AND TO CONTAI
PICTURES and $TATUAl?y
GREAT VALUE.
Gregory Rasputin, the
Latest and Strangest
of the Fortune Tellers,
Fanatics and Charla
tans Who Have Swayed
the Destinies of the
Russian Empire at
Home and Abroad Dur
ing the Reign of Nich
olas II.
By HERMAN BERNSTEIN.
A
KV sensation has come from
Russia.
Itussla has long been fur
nishing new sensations to the world,
weird happenings In mcduevnl set
tings, grotesque and grim tragedies.
While the rest of the world kept nd
Tanclng Russia stood still. While tho
Russian people, yearning for light and
liberty, have prodyced works which
constitute the pride of Russia, the
Russian autocracy, even though It had
a constitution and parliament forced
upon it, has clung to medievalism
with all Its plcturesqucness, Its qualnt
tess, Its cruelties and Its horrors.
For the third tlmo in the last few
rears the story of the death of Ras
putin has reached America. This time
It is apparently true.
The story of Gregory Rasputin is
tinlque even among the strange stories
f the monks, mystics and fortune
tellers who surrounded the Czars of
Russia and Influenced their decisions
In matters of vital Importance to the
Russian people.
To the average Intelligent American
reader It may be Inconceivable that a
ereat empire like Russia, 'a people that
has Riven to the world great men and
women In literature, In art, in sclcncu
and In music, that has brought forth
some of the noblest and bruvest
martyrs for freedom, should bo ruled
In this age through tho Influence of
tharlatans, fortune tellers, weather
prophets, mad monks and Illiterate
peasants. But when it Is recalled that
only a few years ago the mcdlan-al
fi'ual murder myth was staged In tho
ancient city of Kiev In the form of tho
WIN affair, when It Is recalled that
wly a few years ago pogroms wore
WKamzed in many cities and towns In
ItUfHia mi the s:iini dnv. It ceases to
1 surprising that the ruler of '.ho
Umpire- should be Influenced
'nj Raided by oil sorts of "saints" and
prophets, charlatans and madmen,
dealers and soothsayers, who appeal
tu him upon religious grounds.
Those who know anything nt nil
alout Itussla to-day are a ware of tho
'act that some of these powers behlrd
tie throne have made and unmade
Members of the Rurlnn Cabinet and
I"'a'ls f the Holy Synod, and havo
"allied the downfall of premiers.
The list soothsayers und fortune
tellers and healers who havo directed
a great extent tho homo policies of
'ho Russian Umpire nnd even lntlu
tnced the courso of Russia's attitude
'oward foreign nffalrs during tho
feign of Nicholas II. Is long Indeed.
Tho most conspicuous among these
ere Klopov, nn Insignificant function
ary whom the Czar entrusted with spe
1 Investigations; Dcmchlnsky, tho
father prophet, who was discredited
5 dentists and branded as a charla-
SECTION 5
TWELVE PAGES
NEW YORK, SUNDAY,
JANUARY 7. 1917.
OF
SE&GIUS MICHALOFF TRUFANOFF
CALLED I LI ODOR. THE "MAD MONK."
tan: Ukhtomsky-Aslatt-ky, who fired
the Czar's Imagination with Ideas of
his great historical mission: Pero
Philippe, the hairdresser of Marseilles,
spiritualist and healer; a girl named
Gulatzky, who was tho Czar's favorite
ndviser for a time; Bezobrnzov, who
was raised from titter obscurity and
mado Secretary of State; Father John
of Cronstndt, the mad monk Illodor
and Gregory Rasputin.
The strangest of them all was un
doubtedly Philippe, the barber of Mar
seilles, who used to call for the Czar
the spirits of his ancestors and ask
their advice concerning family mat
ters and affairs of state. As long as
he remained In the palace of the Czar
Thllippo was the most powerful man
In Russia, and his Influence In nffalrs
of the gravest Importance was greater
than that of the Premier or other
members cf the Cabinet. Without his
approval nothing was dono by the
Czar.
nnf ThlMnn prpn' tnn bold in his
deceptions one day nnd he was re-
placed by the Gu'ntzky girl. During
the Russo-Japanese war she predicted
that Russia would meet with defeat i
unless
is the Czar himself went to the
Th. rv.ir was on the nolnt of 1
front
taking the girl's advice, but Count
Wltte, Kuropatkln nnd Pobyedonost
seff dissuaded him with great dllllculty
and he remained at home.
Bezobrnzov and Alexeyev, the latter
'gestlon, were practically responsible
for the outbreak of tho war between
Russia and Japan, j
Father John of Cronstndt appeared
upon the scene nt a time when Intrigues I
were helntr engineered for the purpose
of causing the Czar to dlvorco Alexan-
dra Feodorovna because she had
brought him no male heir to the Rus
sian throne. Father John told the
Car of n newly discovered saint in the
de.ert of Sarov and suggested n royal
procession to the desert. The head of
the Synod approved tho suggestion nnd
a royal procei-slon was organized to
visit the testing place or St. serapntm.
Suddenly, after a few years of se
crecy as to tho real Influences control
ling the Czar, tho name of Illodor, the
"Mad Monk," was mentioned.
This young monk became notorious
for his daring harangues against tho
progressive elements In Russia, against
the revolutionists and the Jews, whom
he denounced with vitriolic venom,
ca'.ling upon the populace to start ma
meres. Stories of his attacks upon
high dignitaries of the State and tho
Church reached thlu country at tho
time.
He defied the Holy Pynod nnd ip
no red the commands of the Procura-
tor; he travelled about Russia preach
ing arrogantly against the Church, nnd
nt the same time Incited the mob to
riots and to massacres. Liberal Rus
sia was puzzled. No one could under
stand why this firebrand was per
mitted to carry on his propaganda of i
anarchy.
Victor Obnlnsky, a prominent mem-1
ber of the first Duma, one of tho ablest
men In tho Constitutional Democratic
party, In his Important book, entitled
"The New Order In Russia," published I
in Moscow In 1909, said this of Illodor;
"Tho events of 1905 did not separate i
the State from tho CJiurch. In the
practical twentieth century life did not
bring forth In Russia any clergy who
were not afraid of Independent views,
nnd the types of Nikon and Philippe 1
havo degenerated Into the Illodors and
the Vostorgovs.
"After the dispersion of the first
Duma the Synod prohibited tho clergy
from touching In their sermons upon
any question relating to the political t
condition of the country. Tho circular
of the Synod on this subject stated
that In case the people desired to hear
from their priest as to whether the
conuttions oi too peasants wuum im
ameliorated, the priests should arrange
private discussions, pacifying tho pop
ulatlon, telling tho peasants that the
Czar understood tho needs of the peas
antry and would Improve their condi
tion before long. The manifesto an
nouncing the dispersion of the Duma
was to be read with an appropriate
explanation.
"Nevertheless, the churches were
turned into political arenas. Bishop
Nazary of Nizhni Novgorod ordered
the tolling of tho bells In nil the
churches of that city on tho day tho
Duma was closed, and sermons were
delivered In which the Jews were at- i whero a massacre of. Jews occurred
tacked. In tho town of Kllya, Govern- I Immediately after his sermon on Bep
ment of Bessarabia, the priest Cera-1 tember 14, 1907."
fihonko in his sermon declared that i when Illodor commenced to attack
the JewB organized the revolution, j
lure organizing the assassinations and
nro pinnning to muraer mo neui uu-1
slun Doputles. The Union M the Renl
Russlans will adopt harsh measures
and will destroy tho Jewish Govern
ment.' "Another notorious priest, the
founder of a sect, lectured In St, Peters,
burg on '.The Jows in general n,nd po
groms in particular.' In that lecture
he made the point that tho Jews were
making pogroms against themselves
nnd lie Baw In such progroms tho
finger of God, who punished the Jowa
for their sins against the Government,
"But the record of fanaticism and
bigotry was broken by tho notorious
Illodor, the Idol of the .lanctimonlous
salom of Bt. Petersburg, who was
RASPUTIN, MIS SON MISHKA, HIS DAUGHTER MATRIUSHKA
axd THE BABY VERA. Courtly cf Miltri Wkfy.
feared by the governors nnd police in
spectors of the regions in which this
turbulent Instigator of massacres ap
peared. Finally the archbishops them
selves began to nsk for the removal
of tho fanatic, but In vain, Instead,
Illodor was placed In tho very home
of the man who complained against
him, Anthony of Volhynla. Then
Illodor went to Rostov on tho Don,
the dlgnlturles of the Church who en
deavored to Interfere with his propa-
ganda the only bishop who upheld him
wna Germogcn, another' reactionary
who also becamo notorious In connec
tlon with pogrom propaganda. No ono
understood how tho young monk In
the face of such powerful opposition
was received by tho Czar. The press
of Russia devoted much space to Illo
dor's weird, eccentric talk, but no ono
knew at that tlmo that Gregory Ras
putin, the Illiterate Siberian peasant,
the new favorito of the Czar, was be
hind Illodor.
Rasputin und Illodor became Inti
mate friends. Rasputin had hoped to
make his influence over the Czar
permanent through his relations wtth
the "Mad Monk." He was Illiterate
SStttt
WHO
and he wanted some one who could
write out what he regarded as his re
ligious philosophy of life. Ho also
wanted Iliodor's assistance In his plans
to become the official father confessor
to tho Czar,
For some time Rasputin and Illodor
were close friends. Through Rasputin's
efforts tho "Mad Monk" was received
in audience by tho Czar and by the
Empress. Ho met them only once, for
a brief time, and they spoke to him
mainly about Rasputin.
The struggle for power and the de
slro to replace Rasputin In the favor of
tho Czar turned Illodor into Rasputin's
arch enemy. Knowing of a number of
Rasputin's escapades, Illodor resolved
to expose the "mint" Rasputin in
tho hope that he would be called to
take his place as spiritual adviser to
the Czar.
But Rasputin was the abler and the
cleverer of the two, and notwithstand
ing tho assistance of Bishop Ger
mogen Illodor failed in his efforts to
fhake the confidence of the Czar and
the Czarina la Rasputin. Illodor was
thrown Into prison. He escaped from
Russia on the day of the outbreak
of the war, clad as a' woman, and thus
saved himself from the hand of Ras
putin which" was 'stretching out to
crush him completely,
RULED CZAR
Gregory Rasputin, who reigned In
the ixalace of tho Czar about thirteen
years, was a mnn of powerful phys
ique, of extraordinary will power,
cunning and daring. All his acts, how
ever Immoral, he defended from a re
ligious point of view.
In his youth ho wns known as a
drunkard. He hnd a criminal record
nnd served n term in Jail many years
ago. After that he left his home and
disappeared for n long time. He come
back "reformed."
He said that religion had changed
his life. Ho became a pilgrim. He
walked through various parts of the
Russian empire begging for bread and
for shelter.
Tho story of the reformed Siberian
peasant spread through Russia and
finally reached the Czar through some
of the ladles of the court who had met
him. Rasputin was Invited to the pal
ace. Ills quaint religious viewpoints
made n profound Impression upon tho
Czar and the Cznrlna and his Influence
commenced little by little to dominate
the Russian empire.
M. Paul Mllukov, the leader of the
Constitutional Democratic party in the
Duma, mado the following statement
several years ago from the tribunal of
the Duma:
"Gregory Raspttttn, ths 'new one,' is
SPECIAL FEATURE
SUPPLEMENT
btpyrigM, HIT. by fne Sun Printing suit
PubHiftlnp itatocfatton.
the same man who recommends
Premiers and removes Procurators of
the Synod, who helped illodor ngnlnfit
the Synod nnd the Synod against Illo
dor, and the man who Is helped by
Rasputin always wins."
One of the most characteristic in
stances hhowing to what extent tho
Czar was influenced by this corrupt
and Illiterate pensant "saint" occurred
In connection with the deoth of Count
Leo Tolstoy and the resolution of tho
church on that occasion. Tho Czar
mado public tho resolution prepared
for him, praying God to be merciful
to tho Chrlstaln Just departed. The
reactionary press of Russia song tho
Czar's praises, hut somehow the Czar
was not pleased with the order Issued
by the Holy Synod forbidding tho tra
ditional religious service at the Tolstoy
funeral.
Ho was not quite sure that the
rhti'ch haJ ih:-mi the light -ouiso In
tho matter. Instead of consulting the
foremost dig. iMtie.s o' the church or
the synod, he sent for his friend Ras
putin, who was In Siberia at the tlmo
In his homo village.
Gregory Rasputin, who not only
preached immorality but who was at-
tacked on several occasions by women I
ho had deceived, was summoned to
TsnrsUoe Kelo (n ndvlse the Czar with j
regard to lhe attitude of tho Russlon
Church toward the ex-communlcntlon
of Leo Tolstoy. A fellow passenger of
Rasputin's In the Siberian train relates 1
tho following conversation which took
place whllo Rasputin was hastening to
tho Czar. I
"This Is not my first visit to Tsar
skoe Solo," said Rasputin. "It Is truo
the members of the court party do not i
like me. But I pay no nttentlon to1
them. I am supposed to visit .the man
nurse or tutor of tho Czarevitch, but l
I nm ushered Into the Czar's room.
"I drink tea with the Czar and Czar
Inn, and we always talk n great deal.
Tho Czar has now sent for mo tq dis
cuss whether tho priests have acted
properly In prohibiting n religious cere
mony nt the Tolstoy funeral. The
Cznr thinks it was foolish."
Later, when this passenger became
better acquainted with Rasputin, he
asked:
"Tell me, Is It true that you are do
ing all the nasty things wo hear about
you nnd rend In the newspapers?"
Rasputin smiled nnd said:
"About hnlf of it, of course, Is le,
but then we are nil human, wo are
only human." i
And he laughed again,
Tho nbleht ond at the same time the
most reactionary publicist In Russln,
M, Mentililkov, chnraclxilited Uiifputln
In the following account of his career,
1
j3
4
Je CZA5? oF T?USSIA.
By Some Acclaimed as
Saint, bv Others
Accused of Evil Liv
ing, the Mystery of
His Murder Supplies
a Fitting Climax to a
Career Begun in a
Peasant's Hut in Si
beria which was suppressed by the Russian
Government:
"I know Rasputin, and I can speak
nbout him from my own impressions.
Zazonoff, the Minister for Foreign Af
fairs, brought 'this 's-alntly old monk'
to me when ho was at tho height of
lis glory a few years ago. Tho 'old
monk" dined with me, and wo had a
long discussion about tho nffalrs. In
Russia In general and about himself
In particular.
"At first ho appeared to me as a
rather youthful peasant of about 40,
neatly dressed. Ills face wns that of
i drunkard and his restless oyes, his
low voice resembled those of a mon
astery servant or a psalmist. His
speech was abrupt nnd ho used at
times mysterious expressions.
"At tlrst I was surprised that such
a half savage peasant from Siberia
could not only find his way to St.
Petersburg but that ho could And a
welcome reception at the homes of tho
very highest society. After having
spoken to Rasputin I convinced my
self that ho knew how to produco an
impression. Ilo is a natural philoso
pher coming from tho depths, almost
Illiterate, but well learned In Scrip
ture, a man who ta'ktt about religion
like a gramophone record and endowed
with natural enthusiasm.
"Some of his sayings Impressed mo
for their originality nnd oven for
their depth. Thus the oracles of old
spoko In a ftato of delirium thero
was something absurdly wise In his
enigmatic words. Some of Rasputin's
Ideas seemed to me to bo near the stolo
and ascetic philosophy and bin char
acterizations of somo priests and high
dignitaries struck mo as very keen
and correct.
"Tho first Impression made upon
me wns a good one. I thought ho
wns a cunning peasant, but naturally
religious, cnpnblo of making people
wake from their lethargic sleep as
far as faith was concerned. But I
did not like so much his fancy boots
nnd tho fact that ho was going from
my houso to call nn a certain lady.
"'I should very much llko to re
main In your house,' ho said to me,
'but I havo been Invited to go there
nnd I must go.'
"I was nlso surprised that Rasputin
kissed ladles' hands on bidding them
good-by, A rather stinnge saint, I
thought, ono of those that occasion
ally make their appearance in fash
ionable drawing rooms.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85058393/1922-05-14/ed-1/?sp=37&q=rasputin</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>1 anger Than Fiction, the Fascinating True Story of What She j Til I
Saw With Her Own Eyes of the Thrilling Events rf' I
That Followed the Overthrow of the Czar's I
Power Now Told for the First fgAi T I
Iti from prrctdmg page)
uch more. You have been
yill make you his tyrant,"
n. And quite in the manner
icnt Roman Emperor who,
:lls us, when atTected by
f on of the Roman wives
i tt his feasts, took her im
,way with him, Rasputin
of the studio with the
ifter them, wondering if I
dreaming. No one else
y any attention. They went
The sculptor came to mo
ive a cup of tea after the
did you excite the Father
1 your resistance?"
t him. He was in earnest,
ceased their chattering to
reproachfully as though
ed some saint; I did not
to say. The whole mat
uring. Some one tact
the subject and we dis
id the theater as we sipped
in hour Rasputin and the
returned. She glanced
rather apprehensively, I
en the uncouth priest and
ir seats at the table and
wit on talking as though
lordinary had happened,
fnored me, but began to
to another of the court
ve of anger and repulsion,
e no other subject to talk
I asked,
fti" glared at me grimly
know that love is life's
I fives me the energy
4 the power to nccom
Ru4ia by that magic only,
sible hand of the throne to
j of civilization and make it
be in olden times a sira
Mtion, with one heart and
I then made this truly
0 tke the Empress out
land place her in a simple
together with the Czar,
ree only will rule Rus
I Palaces, but from the
Be of a peasant. All
lnd democracy is noth
mt the masses with
ted sweetmeats. And only
thought, "Lu8t you mean!.
JJJW to darc to gpcak j broke
4 thf' ('rvl""-'t '"inisten
tmT, ,functionanes f,f vai-
KTn'. How about our edu
art mvtjtutioi,
ZMr lth hi hand in the air, he
fa stand 8 they are. The
1
photo- SL, 1
graph
ever
taken j
Czarevitch, showing him practicing
archery in his Siberian place of exile r
point is, that the Czar and Czarina and
I shall dominate. We will curb the
power of the bureaucracy and the
Church. We will bring back the simple
things of life, but, most of all a real
teaching of the art of love. We need
thousands of priests and priestesses, men
and women, for Russia is too large for
two men to rule."
"But how about Sister Anna Viru
bova?" I could not help asking sardoni
cally. Rasputin became confused and stam
mered, afraid that I knew too much.
"Oh, well, he is the invisible angel be
hind us all! She is supreme. You see,
to rule an empire like Russia is rather
complicated for two men," he said at
last.
I burst out laughing. The "slarretz"
glared at me. Then he resumed
fiercely:
"Don't laugh! The time of judgment
is very near. We are facing great
changes. I must be strong to accomplish
all the work. I get my strength from
women women and more women! Give
me a woman and I am young, strong and
wise. Take away the woman and I col
lapse and die. 1 drink women and eat
women. Russia will become great
through my women women who know
how to love but not women who know
how to talk. I want silent women, wom
en full of passion, women who know
how to love. 1 know it. I speak of my
experience, of my vision, of my divine
conviction." For a second he paused,
then said solemnly:
"Cursed be the woman who ever dares
to oppose me, for it is not I she starves
and denies, but the soul of Holy Russia,
who feeds through me!"
This appalling revelation of vampir
ism was interrupted by a telephone call
from the Grand Duchess Anastasia to
Rasputin.
"What do you want?" asked Rasputin
brusquely.
'The Czarevich is feeling badly and
his nose is bleeding," Anastasia replied.
"bring him to the telephone," com
manded he.
This was evidently done at the palace,
for Rar.putin spoke to him:
"There is nothing the matter with your
nose. Go and sleep on the chair until I
come. Let your sister keep ice on the
noae. My little dove, I am yonv guard
ian saint, so don't worry. Tell the
Czarina that I :m coming to keep my
hand on your head. The fairy will pla
-1- m i rjTf
Wm
ff yaw
rffcjBLaw-

ty
I
The Czarevitch in the uniform of a
Russian army officer
with you in sleep. The name of your
fairy is Nightingale. Now kiss the re
ceiver and be a good boy,"
After this telephone conversation he
turned to us, smiling.
"Now I have to leave and I will
continue my discussion about the role
thut love plays in our life when I sco
you aguin."
He shook hands with everybody; then
addressed me.
"You need a spanking, because you
are nothing but a child in your views of
lifi-. You think me a monster and charla
tan. Never mind. 1 know your father. He
has been trying to ruin me with his
printer's ink and paper at the court and
in the eyes of the people, but in vain. I am
still alive and 1 am stronger than he is!"
He nodded slightly, crossed himself
and left. I felt as if a heavy pressure
"ifr-TiT rmB" ''mm ii
had been lifted from the atmos
phere and everybody seemed to
breathe, relieved.
I did not see him for a long time
He evidently avoided meeting me,
and Vinibova. his friend, grew cold
toward me. My father renewed his
bitter articles in denouncing Raspu- r
tin as an impostor. But it was practi
cally impossible for Virubova or Raspu
tin to put me out or do me any harm,
especially as I had the public opinion
on my side.
Some time passed and the incident
with Rasputin at the studio of Aronson
was almost forgotten. Mme. Virubova
had arranged ar elaborate charity ball
for the benefit of the wounded and the
Red Cross and I was among the invited
guests. Here I saw Rasputin the second
time. I was dressed in the Russian
peasant costume of the Volga provinces
and danced a folk dance for the audi
ence. Rasputin walked toward me and
extended his hand for greeting, quite as
if nothing had happened, and exclaimed:
"Ah, Asta, my little dove! You must
dance with me!"
Without any hesitation I answered
that I would be pleased to dance with
him, provided the hostess was able to
collect an extra ten thousand rubles for
tho charity. The announcement that
Rasputin and I would dance a number
of folk dances for the gathering brought
double the ar,ked amount of money.
Everybody was curious to see Raspu
tin dancing with Suvorina. The nvjnk
danced well, and the audience cheered
and applauded us wildly. During the in
termission I told him:
"Rasputin, this a function which you
can perform much better than ruling
Russia."
He pulled his red beard and glanced
at me slyly, grunting:
"That's all right, my dear lady It
makes no difference whether the medium
is a dance or a drink, if there is only
the woman. I make all women of
Russia to dance. Now you dance with
me; to-morrow you may drive or elope
with me. Who knows?"
"F think you wou! I I e'ter forget wom
en and think of more important things,"
I replied. For a long moment he did
not speak, then:
"If I am separated from a woman
Russia will perish! If Russia forgets mo
and forgets the woman she will perish
in less than a year!" he said. I felt a
shudder go through me. There was
V
His arms seized me in an iron grip while
his hot, gray eyes never left mine.
"Dear child," he said, "don't crush the
magic pearl am offering you! You
will hiss my shadow and clamor
for my return if you do."
y something uncanny some-
thing inhuman about the
It was really strange what
influence Rasputin had over
the Czar and the Czarina, yet, I be
lieve, that behind his influence was still
that very slirewd lady. Mme. Virubova.
Just as much as he was hated by the
people and the intellectuals of Russia
was he loved by the rojal family and the
court; and as he was loved so he domi
nated those who loved him and turned
their lives to serve his own purposes.
First of all, he was, above all, a virile
man of instinct, a "naturmensch," as
Nietzsche would have said. He fell like
a masculine meteor into the most de
cadent society of women tho world has
ever known. They loved him by the
scores and hundreds.
Woman, whatever may be said by the
poets, is a more monotonous and more
uniform being than man; the chromatic
.;ile of her characteristics is not so far
extended, for she is a being nearer to
nature than man is. The forgetfulness
of this fact has caused much bitterness
to the idealists who have set her In the
clouus.
Woman is less moral than, and really
much more shameless, because she
has almost always been idle which
is the fault of man, who, since the
feudal era developed her as an instru
ment of pleasure. This moral aspect of
the psychology of woman being granted,
it at once explains her preference and
her affinity for those men who represent
the primitive animal type. Such a man
was Rasputin.
Besides that, he had acquired on his
extended pilgrimage from one monas
tery to another a tinge of mystic incli
nation, which, with natural Intuition, he
knew how to exploit most effectively in
his dealings with women. He knew the
psychology of women better than the
best psychologists and poets, and he
played on them accordingly. This, my
view of him, was corroborated by his in
timate friend, Anna Virubova, in one of
her conversations with me, when she
said:
"Brother Gregory dominates all his
women friends, including the Czarina.
He is a wise man of the East, and
knows that an average educated man
is a moralizing animai, which is his
weakness in lii:J relation with woman. It
would be better if he were to make up
his mind and find out which is the mora
ign I ible to hint: the woman who is vo
luptuous, beautiful and fascinating, tho
instrument of pleasure, or the woman
m the higher and more noble sense of
the word. Instead of eitl or of thcae, he
chooses the proud woman, charming and
playful, and would like to teach her
morality, instead of pro iding him;elf
with a whip, a i'- wise old woman ad
vised Zarathustra; he longs for the vo- H
lupiuous woman aud forgets that fhe has
poisonous teeth and finger nails." H
I douijt that Rasputin could have ex- H
erciied tho power at the court as he did H
had he dot been oacked up and manipu-
lated bo by silent Anna. But what her H
motives wera in doing so is a mystery.
Either she was ttnxious to ruin the H
zari::3 through Rasputin's infiuenca H
and take her place or she was an agent H
of dark powers. H
There have been ugly rumors that
she was a tool of the Geirnan General
Staff and the Kaiser. It has been hint-
ed that a certain German baroness, who H
visited her frequently during the rule of
the Czar, called on her with Mme.
Trotzky. when th. Bolsheviks appeared
in Petrograd. and assured her that she
would remain immune in her private S
illa und no one would touch her per-
ional property, jewels and money.
Such generous immunity was not
granted to any other favorite of the court fl
and it would seem as if she could have H
obtained it only through some such meads I
as gossip hints at.
One of Rasputin's tricks of controlling
the Czarina and other women of position
was his doctrine of "hlysticism"
a "religion," which emphasizes the fact
tnat sensualism is the main point cf a
religious ritual and sensuous symbols
are to be considered as sacred Bigns of
devotion. I was told that he had a real
Hlysty chapel in the house of Mme. Vi
rubova, where special services were cele
brated frequently for her and a
few of her intimate friends, but I nevr
saw it.
In these pages next Sunday I will
give some surprising details about thla
strange doctrine of "Hlysticism" and
the very ingenious way Rasputin hid a
disgusting sensualism behind the solemn
symbols of religion. It was very largely
through his preaching and practice of
this doctrine that the monk became the
sinister figure he did under Russia's old
regime.

https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn88063294/1944-10-01/ed-1/?sp=67&q=rasputin
1
Th** II (Miotic Rasputin, Who, Just Preowl
ing Ills Own Murder, Wm Amusing Himself
by Writing About Jack, the Ripper.
“Such are the true facts of the Jack, the Rip
jH*r mystery, which may ever puzzle those who do
not read my book.”
Unless Uodachenko’s eventual incarceration in
an asylum be taken to indicate that he W’as raving
mad at the height of his terrible career, this amaz
ing account leaves wide open the whole question
of his motivation.
Even supposing he w-as mad, one still wonders
what sort of madness could have spurn'd him to
such extremes of bestiality and. at the same time,
have left him enough cunning wholly to escape
detection by Scotland Yard.
The condition of his victims made it obvious
that immediately after each crime he must have
tK*en covered with blood. Rasputin says he lived
with his sister far from his hunting field How
then, in his gory state, did he get home undetected?
Moreover, what of this same sister, who must
known something of his activities and “the
woman?” To have helped in the grue
some work, they must have been as mad as he.
And is it likely that a whole menage of lunatics
would have failed to attract attention?
Yet, silent as Rasputin remains on these signif
icant points, sketchy as his story is, he never
theless writes with an accent of truth—an accent
which becomes even more pronounced when it is
recalled that, through his friendship with Proto*
I*>poff, the wily Minister of the Interior, he had
THK AIHKRMAX WKKKLY
free access to the files
of the Secret Police.
Also, on the affirmative side is
the fact that Scotland Yard sus
pected that the cards, with which
they were playfully kept informed
of forthcoming murders, were
w-ritten by a woman. If Mrs., or
Miss, Win berg played the role Ras
putin assigns her, their suspicion
would seem to be confirmed.
And Pedachenko’s former em
ployment on the staff of a mater
nity hospital is illuminating, too,
for it explains the considerable
skill which the killer displayed in
the art of evisceration.
In all. Jack, the Ripper, com
mitted six murders in a little less
than a year. Each took place in
the same quarter of London and
in each case the victim was a wo
man of the streets.
Following the second, police re
ceived the following card, signed
with this pseudonym:
“Dear Boss: I keep on hearing
the police had caught me but they
won’t fix me yet. I love my work and
want to start again. You will soon
hear of me and my funny little game.
The next job I shall clip the body’s
ears off and send to police officers,
just for jolly, wouldn’t you?”
Four days later, the mutilated
body of Elizabeth Stride, known as
l>ong Liz, was discovered in an alley,
her throat cut, a bunch of grapes in
her hand. While the shopkeeper, who
had sold the grapes to her, and “a dark
man with a moustache” were Identifying
the body, another woman's corpse was
found in another alley, close by.
The other victim, Catherine Eddowes,
also had her throat cut. In addition, her
eyelids had been slit and one of her
kidneys removed. The kidney subsequently
reached the police, through the mails, along
wdth this message:
“I wasn’t codding, dear old Boss, when I gave
you the tip. You’ll hear about saucy Jack’s work
tomorrow. Double event this time. Number one
squealed a bit. Couldn’t finish straight off. Had
no time to get ears for police. Thanks for keeping
last letter back till I got to work again.”
Meanwhile, London was in an uproar. Women
feared to appear alone on the streets after dark.
The police combed Whitechapel, made numerous
arrests and even
dressed members of
the force as women.
The only effect
was a fifth murder,
this one a master
piece of brutality.
Young, good looking
Jeanette Kelly was
heard singing in her
room on the evening
of November ft, 1898.
On the morning of
November 10, she
was found by a rent
collector, hoi body
scattered all ovci the
same room.
In the scv o•'
months bid ween t' n
and the following
July no more Jocose
In the Bom bod
ICulns of This, Ills
Workroom, W a s
Found Rasputin's
Secret Kook on
Great Russian
Criminals.
fk v\
H I H |Knß££|Rf|flgHHHHH
communications troubled the police, no more
murders bore Jack’s peculiar trademark.
But the panic kept up.
Then, on July 18, the killer took his sixth
and last victim. Her body, like those of the
first four, was found in an alley. After that
the case of Jack, the Ripper, was consigned
to the pages of history, detective stories and
Rasputin’s book.
It is not unlikely that the monk w-as at
work on his manuscript on the fateful De
cember night in 1916, when he was sum
moned to the Palace of Prince Yussopov.
The first World War was then in prog
ress, and Russia was at the breaking point.
Rasputin, son of a poor peasant (whose
name meant “debauchee") had by means of
his hypnotic powers and lure of the evan
gelistic gospel he preached, raised himself
to a position of tremendous influence at the
court of Nicholas 11.
Believing him their ow n and their coun
try’s evil genius, four members of the aris
tocracy, Yussopov, Vladimir Puriskevitz.
Grand Duke Dmitri and Sukhotin, resolved
to liquidate him. They baited their trap by promis
ing him the favors of a titled beauty, and Raspu
tin rushed to an expected conquest.
It w-as, but not the beauty’s. In fact, there was
no beauty. But before the monk suspected trick
ery he had. been persuaded to partake of cakes
and wine, containing cyanide of potassium.
Following the repast, he confessed to a slight
burning sensation In the stomach. Otherwise he
seemed to suffer no discomfort.
Despairing of the effects of poison on such a
constitution, one of the conspirators shot him.
“There was a roar as from a wild beast,” Yus
sopov wrote later, “and Rasputin fell backward.”
After concluding that their victim was dead,
three of the conspirators retired upstairs, leaving
the Prince alone in the murder room.
“I cannot explain why,” Yussopov’s account of
the night continues, “but suddenly I seized him by
both arms and violently shook him. The body
rose, leaned sidewise and fell backward into its
former position, the head hanging lifelessly to
one side.
“I stood over him for a little while and was
on the point of going away when my attention was
arrested by a slight trembling of the left eyelid. I
bent down and attentively examined his face. It
began to twitch convulsively. The movement be
came more pronounced. Suddenly the left eye
half opened. A moment later the right lid trem
bled and lifted. And both eyes, the eyes of Ras
putin, greenish and snake-like, fixed themselves
on me with an expression of devilish hatred.
“My blood froze in speechless horror. I wanted
to run, to call for help, but my feet would not
move and no sound came from me. I stood riveted.
“Then the incredible happened. With a violent
movement, Rasputin got to his feet. I was horror
stricken. The room resounded with a wild roar.
His fingers convulsively knotted, flashed through
the air. Like red hot irons they gripped my
shoulder and tried to grip me by the throat. His
eyes were crossed and protruded terribly. He was
foaming at the mouth, and inla hoarse whisper he
constantly repeated my name.
“I tried to tear myself away, but a terrible
struggle ensued. This poisoned and wounded crea
ture, raised by the powers of darkness, inspired me
with a feeling so terrifying, so ghastly, that the
memory of it haunts me to this day.”
Finally he managed to shake off the monk,
rushed upstairs and called to his friends, “He’s
alive!” He seized a loaded stick when he saw
Rasputin making his way to the door and bellow
ing like a wounded animal. He reached the street,
and there the conspirators closed in again.
Four more shots from Puriskevitz’s revolver,
and a vigorous beating with the loaded stick were
required to finish the business the poison had
begun. Yussopov fainted. His three companions
threw- the dead monk into the Neva River, and
thus ended the almost indestructible Rasputin.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045211/1917-10-22/ed-1/?sp=19&q=rasputin&st=text
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>(Copyright. 1917. Tuhllo Lcdter Company. All rlnhtii rrervr
German Intrigue, Ever Present Throughout the
Vorldj Has Linked Rasputin's Name Vith
the Fairest and Highest of Russia's Court
Circles But These Rumors Are False, the
Princess Radziwill Insists
h 2$e "Black Monk" Appeared on the Scene at a
m w f- F m r f If till titi II7 m J- W, j F)m
rSyClluiuymuv iTxviiiviti, w ncii iiiu ivuvtjiail
People Had Drifted Away From the Church
and Were Ready for Any Strong Appeal to
the Mystical Side of Their Character
KAft SUI.41UV
rfVTTT me
1AY, OCTOBER 23, 1917
asputin is that he was not murdered sooner.
aivcrsally detested all over Russia, that it wai
ain alive so long a time after it had been found
scene by other than violent means."
S
S A rule the general public knows very little concerning these
A gects, but I shall quote here a passage out of a book on Russia by
Sir Donald Mnckenzio Wallace, which is considered to this day as a
itandard work in regard to its subject. "Among the 'Khlysty, he
writes, "there are men and women who take upon themselves the
calling of teachers and prophets, and In this character they lead a
itrict, ascetic life, refrain from the most ordinary and innocent
pleasures, exhaust themselves by long fasting and wild ecstatic reli
ious exercises and abhor marriage. Under the excitement caused
If their supposed holiness and inspiration, they call themselves not
only teachers and prophets, but also Saviours, Redeemers, Christs,
Mothers ,of God. Generally speaking, they call themselves simply
I ods and pray to each other as to real gods and living Christs and
jjtdonnas. When several of these teachers come together at a
i meeting they dispute with each other in a vain, boasting way as to
which of them possesses most grace and power. In this rivalry they
lometimes give each other lusty blows on the car, and he who
bears the blows the most patiently, turning the other cheek to the
miter, acquires the reputation of having tho most holiness.
"Another sect belonging to the same category and which indeed
claims close kindred with it is the Jumpers, among whom the erotic
element is disagreeably prominent. Hero is a description of their
religious meetings, which are held during summer in a forest and
during winter in some outhouse or barn. After due preparation
prayers are read by the chief teacher, dressed in a white robe and
itanding in the midst of the congregation. At first he reads in an
ordinary tone of voice and then passes gradually into a merry chant.
When he remarks that the chanting has sufficiently acted on tho
(hearers he begins to jump. The hearers, singing likewise, follow
hi example. Their ever-increasing excitement finds expression in
the highest possible jumps. This they continue as long as they can
men and women aliko yelling like enraged savages. When all are
thoroughly exhausted the leader declares that he hears the angels
ringing, and then begins a scene which cannot be here described."
I have quoted this passage in full because it may give to tho
reader who is not versed in the details of Russian existence and
Russian psychology tho key to the circumstances, that helped Ras
putin to absorb for such a considerable number of years the attention
of the public in Russia, and which, in fact, made him possible as a
great ruling, though not governing, force in the country. In some
ways he had appealed to the two great features of the human char
acter in general and of the Russian character in particular mys-
ticism and influence of the senses. It is not so surprising as it might
I leem at first sight that he contrived to ascend to a position which
no one who knew him at first ever supposed he would or could attain.
At the same time I must, in giving a brief sketch of the career
of this extraordinary individual, protest against the many calumnies
I .which have associated him with names which I will not mention here
i out of respect tnnd feelings of patriotism. It is sufficiently painful
to)we to say-so, but German calumny, which spares no one, has
used its poisoned arrows also where Rasputin came to be discussed.
I It lias tried to' travesty maternal love and anxiety into something
quitdifferent, andft has attempted to sully what it could not touch.
There have bce.fi many sad episodes in this whole story of Rasputin,
(but some of ttlcTeRple who have been mentioned in connection with
i .them were commeiely innocent of the things for which they have
"been reproaenecr. Finally, the indignation which these vile and
unfounded accusations roused in the hearts of the true friends and
J servants of t5o people led to the drama which removed forever from
t the surface of Russian society the sectarian who unfortunately had
Kmtrived to glide into its midst.
Rasputin a Master of Corruption
The one extraordinary thing about Rasputin is that he was not
t iiurdered sooner. He was so entirely despised and so universally
tyeated all over Russia that it was really a miracle that he could
remain alive so long a time after it had been found impossible to
remove him from the scene of the world by other than violent means.
It;was a recognized fact that ho had had a hand in all kind of dirty
1 $ny matters and that no business of a financial character con-
oecfed with military expenditure could be brought to a close with
l out his being mixed In it. About this, however, I shall speak later
I fto fn trying to explain how the Rasputin legend spread and how it
k ya's exploited by all kind of individuals of a 'shady character, who
5f.J VI. -j! iL.! ml.- J-1 l.J
u ins numo ior purposes 01 tneir own. xne ucanuai tuuucvieu
with the shameless manner in which he became asspciated with
Innumerable transactions more or less disreputable was so enormous
that unfortunately it extended to people and to names that should
I .neyer, have been mentioned together with him.
It must never be forgotten, and I cannot repeat this suffi
ciently, that Rasputin was a common peasant of the worst class
of the Russian mougiks, devoid of every kind of education, with
out any manners and in his outward appearance more disgusting
jhan nn thing else. It would be impossible to explain the
influence which he undoubtedly contrived to acquire "upon some
persons belonging to the highest social circles if one did not take
into account this mysticism and superstition which lie at the
bottom of the Slav nature nnd the tendency which the Russian
character has to accept as a manifestation of the power of the
divinity all things that touch upon the marvelous or the uncx
plainablc. Rasputin in a certain sense appeared on the scene of
Russian social life at the very moment when his teachings could
become acceptable, at the time when Russian society had been
shaken to its deepest depths by the revolution which had fol
lowed upon the Japanese war and when It was looking every
where for a safe harbor in which to find a refuge.
At the beginning of his career and when he was introduced into
the most select circles of tho Russian capital, thanks to the caprices
and the fancies of two or three fanatic orthodox Indies who had
imagined that they had found in him a second Savonarola and that
his sermons nnd teachings could provoke a renewal of religious fer
vor, people laughed nt him and at his feminine disciples, and made
all kinds of jokes, good nnd bad, about him and them. But this sort
of thing did not last n long time and Rasputin, who, though devoid
of every kind of culture, had a good deal of the cunning, which is one
of the distinctive features of tho Russian peasant, was the first to
who made I nat nt last Rasputin himself
deemed it advisable i. native village of Pokrowskoie,
in "Siberia. A few days after his departure the little Grnnd Duke fell
soriously ill nnd his mother became persuaded that this was a pun
ishment for her having allowed tho vngrant prenchcr to bo sent
nwny. Rasputin was recalled, nnd after this no one ever spoke
again of his being removed anywhere. From that time all kind of
adventurers began to lay siege to him and to do their utmost to gain
an introduction.
Rasputin and the "Fair Ladies"
Russia was still the land where n court favorite was all-powerful,
and Rasputin was held ns such, especially by those who had some
personal interest in representing him ns the successor to Menschl
kolT under Peter the Great, Diren under the Empress Anne nnd
Orloff under Catherine II. He acquired a far greater influence out
side Tzarskoie Selo than he ccr enjoyed in the imperial residence
itself, and he made the best of it, boasting of a position which in
reality he did not possess. The innumerable state functionaries, who
in Russia unfortunately nlwnys have the last word to say every
where and in everything nnd whose rapacity is proverbial, hastened
to put themselves nt the service of Rnsputln and to grant him every
thing which he asked, in the hope that in return he would make him
self useful to them.
NsiiiiiiiiiV j iiiiiiH iiiiiVsiiHBBHiiiiiiifliSE&aiiiHBBQiHH 111111111119
VHHr HiB Tr9iaiiHsiiiHsw IKKr iiiiiHE9sH9sv!S8alH!nKSr9i9 liniiiiiiiH
I'V'uVl t- H aK. iiiiS?9k..L I 1 wiTv x iiiiiiBatiiiHBBiiiiiiiiw lifliiiiiiiiiiiiZf
ibiiiiiiS iHHHsBiHaSiBKVf&sMt wnHHlQHliiBaBiBiVBsflliiiiB p- jpBc i JiVR
X B g&V lllB HiBllKHtakR$Ste. iwRuiH?4t"& 1
Rasputin (in the center with his hnnd on his chest) surrounded by a group of admirers in a fashionable Pctrograd home.
guess all the possibilities which this sudden "engouement" of influ
ential people for his person opened out before him nnd to what use it
could bo put for both his ambition and his inordinate love of money.
He began by exacting a considerable salary for all the prayers which
he was supposed to say at the request of his worshipers, and of all
the ladles, fair or unfair, who had canonized him in their enthusiasm
fQr all the wonderful things which he was continually telling them.
He was eloquent in a way and at the beginning of his wonderful
thaumaturgic existence had not yet adopted the attitude which he
was to assume 'nter on of an idol, whom every one had to adore.
t IIe was preaching the necessity to repent of one's sins, to
make due penance for them after a particular manner, which
he described as being the most agreeable to God, and to pray
s constantly and with unusual fen or for the salvation of orthodox
Russia. He contrived most cleverly to play upon the chord of
patriotism which Is always so developed in Russians, and to
speak to them of the welfare of their beloved fatherland when
ever he thought it advantageous to his personal interests to do so.
He succeeded in inspiring in his adepts a faith in his own person
and in his power to save their souls akin to the one which is to
be met in England and in America among the sect that preach
mental heading. A few hysterical ladies- who were addicted to
neuralgia or headaches, suddenly found themselves better after
having conversed or prayed with him, and they spread his fame
outside the small circle which had adopted him at the beginning
of his career. One fine day a personal friend of the reigning
Empress, Madame W.r introduced him at Tzarskoie Selo, under
the pretext of praying for the health of the small heir to the
Russian throne, who was occasioning some anxiety to his par
ents. It was from that day that he became a personage.
His success at court was due to the superstitious dread with
which he contrived to inspire the Emprpss in regard to her son. She
was constantly trembling for him, and being very religiously inclined,
with strong leanings toward mysticism, she allowed herself to be
persuaded more by the people who surrounded her than by Rasputin
himself. She believed that the monk, of whose holiness she was
absolutely persuaded, could by his prayers alone obtain the protec
tion of the Almighty for her beloved child. An accidental occurrence
contributed to strengthen her in this conviction. There were per
sons who were of the opinion that the presence of Rasputin at
Tzarskoie Selo was not advantageous for many reasons. Among
them was Mr. Stolypine, then Minister of the Interior, and he it was
A kind of bargaining established itself between people desirous
of making a career nnd Rasputin, eager to enrich himself no matter
by what means. He began by playing the intermediary in different
financial transactions agninst n substantial consideration, and at
last he thought himself entitled to give his attention to matters
of state. This was the saddest side of his remarkable career
as a pscudo-Cagliostro. He had a good deal of natural intelligence,
and while being tho first to laugh at fair ladies who clustered
around him, he understood at once that he could make use of them.
This he did not fail to do. He adopted toward them the manners
of a stein master, and treated them like his humble slaves. At
last he ended by leading the existence of a man of pleasure, denying
himself nothing, especially his fondness for liquor of every kind.
At that time there was ,no prohibition in Russia and, like all
Russinn peasants, Rasputin was very fond of vodka, to which
he never missed adding a substantial quantity of champagne when
ever he found tho opportunity.
I shall abstain from touching upon the delicate point of the
orgies to which it is related that Rasputin was in the habit of
addicting himself, the more so because I do not really believe these
ever took place in those higher circles of society where it was
said they regularly occurred. That strange things may have
happened among the common people, who in far greater numbers
than it has ever been known used to attend the religious meetings
which he held, I shall not deny. It must nlways be remembered
that Rasputin belonged iO the religious sect of the Khlysty, of
whose assemblies we have read the description, and it is quite likely,
and even probable, that the assemblies of these sectarians nt which
he presided were not different from the others to which these
heretics crowded. But I feel absolutely convinced thnt as regards
the relations of the ndventurcr with the numerous Indies of society
silly enough to believe in him and in his gifts of prophecy, these
consisted only of superstitious reverence on one side and exploitation
of human stupidity on tho other.
I must once more insist on the point that the apparition of
Rasputin in Russian society had nothing wonderful about it, and
thnt the only strange thing is that such a fuss was made. Before
his time people belonging to the highest social circles had become
afflicted with religious mnnias of one kind or another out of that
natural longing for something to believe in and to vvoiship which
lies hidden at the bottom of the character of every Russian who
has the leisure, or the craving, to examine teriously tho difficult
RASPUTIN AND THE RUSSIAN, CHARACTER
TT WOULD be impossible to explain the influence which Rnsputln
undoubtedly contrived to acquire upon some persons belong
ing to the highest social circles if one did not take Into account
this lnvsticlsm nnd superstition which lie at the bottom of the
Slav nature and the tendency which the Russian character hM
to accept as a manifestation of the power of the divinity all
things that touch upon the marvelous or the uncxplainablc.
and complicated problems of n future life and of the faith one
ought to follow and to believe in.
In 1817 there was discovered in the very heart of St. Petersburg,
holding its meetings in an imperial residence (the Michael Palace),
n religious sect of most pronounced mystical tendencies, presided
over- by n lady belonging to the best circles of tho capital the
widow of u colonel, Mndamo Tntarinoff. In her apartments used
u gnther officers, State functionaries, women and girls of good
fnmily nnd excellent education who, with slight variations, practiced
all tho religious rites of the Khlystys. One of the Minister! of
Alexander I, Prince Galitzyne, was suspected of having honored
these assemblies with his presence. Thanks to a letter which
accidentally fell into the hands of the police, the Government became
iiware of what was going on, and Madame Tatarinoff, this Russian
Madame Guyon, expintcd in exile in a distant province of Siberia
the ecstasies which she had practiced nnd which she hnd allowed
others to practice under her roof. Some of her disciples were
prosecuted, but the greater number escaped scot free. The authorities
did not care to increase the scnndal which this affair hnd aroused
in the capitnl.
Uplifting the Cab Drivers
Much later, in 1878, after the Russo-Turkish war, which, like
the Japanese affair, had been followed by a strong revolutionary
movement in the country that culminated in the assassination of
the Czar, Alexander II, another prophet, this time of foreign origin,
nppenred on the social horizon of St. Petersburg society, where he
made a considerable number of converts. This was the famous
Lord Raditock, whose doctrines were taken up by a gentleman who
up to thnt time had been known as one of tho gayest among the
gny, a colonel in the Gunrds Mr. Bnsil Paschkoff. He was
enormously lich, and put all his vnst fortune nt the service of the
religious craze which had seized him. He used hls best efforts
to convert to tho doctrino of salvation through faith only not alone
hia friends and relatives, but also the poorer classes of the popu
lation of tho capital, devoting in particular his attention to the
cab drivers. All these people used to meet at his house, where
they mingled with persons of the highest rank and standing, such
ns Count Korff, nnd a former Minister, Count Alexis Bobrinsky.
Later on the whole Tchertkoff family, to which belonged the famous
friend, of Count Leo Tolstoy, associated itself with them, and,
indeed, displayed the greatest fanaticism in regard to its par
ticipntion in the doctrines of the new sect.
The Paschkowitcs, as they came to be called, had nothing at
all in common with tho Khlystys. Their morals were absolutely
unimpeachable, and what they preached wa3 simply the necessity
to conform one's existence to the teachings of the Gospel, which
they explained nnd commented upon, each person according to his
own light. They were Protestnnts in a certain sense, inasmuch
as their views were distinctly Protestant ones. But they had much
more in common with the nonconformists than the real followeis
of Luther or of Calvin. They were a kind of refined Salvation
Army, if this expression can be forgiven me; though they never
acquired the importance, nor did the good which the latter has done,
perhaps because they could never make any practical application
of the principles and of the idens which animated them. But at
one time the Paschkowist craze was just ns strong as the Rasputin
one became later on, and Lord Radstock and Mr. Paschkoff wero
considered just as much prophets among their own particular circle
as was Rasputin nmong the fanatical ladies who had-taken him up.
These crises of religious mania are regular occurrences in Rus
sian higher social circles when unusually grave circumstances arrive
to shake their equanimity. Seen from this particular point of view,
the apparition of Rasputin nnd the importance which his personality
acquired in the life of the Russinn upper classes present nothing
very wonderful. Before him other so-called prophets had kept tho
attention of the public riveted upon their doings and their actions.
What distinguished his short passage was the fact that it was
made the occasion by the natural enemies of the empire, consisting
of the discontented at home and of the Germans outside the frontier,
to discredit the dj nasty as well as those whose life was spent in its
immediate vicinity and to present this figure of the vagrant half
monk and half-layman. He preached a new revelation to those
foolish enough to listen to him, representing himself as of almost
gigantic importance, who could at his will and fancy direct the
course of public affairs and lead them wherever he wanted.
My object in this study will be to show Rasputin for what he
really was, and in retracing the different vicissitudes of his strange
career not to give way to the many exaggerations, which, in familiar
izing people abroad with his person and with his name, have made
out of him something quite wonderful, and almost equal In power
with the Czar himself. It is time to do away with such legends and
to bring Rasputin back to his proper level a very able and cunning,
half-cultured peasant, who owed his successes only to the fanaticism
of the few, and to the interest which many had in dissimulating
themselves behind him, in order to bring their personal wishes to a
successful end. It Is not Rasputin who performed most of the
actions put to his credit. It was those who influenced him, who
pushed him forward and who, thanks to him, became both rich and
powerful. He has disappeared. I wish wo could be as sure that
they have disappeared along with him.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83025316/1917-04-08/ed-1/?sp=5&q=rasputin
</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>CZAtt NICHOLAS AND GREGORY RASPUTIN. WHOSE POWEIt OVER
the WEAK .MONARCH LED TO THE LATTKITS DOWNFALL AND
New Volk. I;>■ MuilA—To the in
fluence of Gregory Rasputin, Siberian
monk and mystic, the former czar of
Russia cap attribute thé revolt which
has brought into.being a new Russia.
Gregory'Rasputin it is a name that
Russian progressives hate with the
utmost vigor. Rasputin is dead, a
victim of -assassination, but the whirl
wind he sowed did not die with him.
The whirlwind overturned a rock
ribbed dynasty that the efforts of
patriots had been unable to shake in
the slightest.
The rodk foundation of the Ro
manoffs owes its disintegration to the
teachings and "rituals" of Raspulin,
the most '>powerful man in Russia in
recent years, the "power behind the
throne" and the "confidant of the
czarina."
No one knows Rasputin better than
Sergius Mlchaelow Trufanoff, who but
a few years ago as Iliador, the Mad
Monk of Russia, was a factor himself
in Russian court affairs and who re
cently wrote a serial of his life for
the Jewish newspaper, the Wahrheit.
Russia Before the "Deluge."
In hla serial Iliador has drawn a
striking picture of the Russia "before
the deluge." It is a picture that de
picts the degeneracy of the Russian
court, of the unheeded voices of the
people asking for food and justice, of
graft and license on every side, of a
czar—weak-kneed, foolish, pitiful, the
tool of his sycophants, believer in mys
ticism—and in the center of this most
dramatic stage of centuries stood Ras
putin, the untutored, unkempt, re
ligious mystic from Siberia, who by
his hypnotic power over the czar and
czarina. Was able to make and un
make ministers, laugh at the holy
synod, force Russia into war and all
böt succeed in making a separate peace
with Germany.
Iliador, first favored by Rasputin,
"discovered the real monster Rasputin
was" and then fought him to the fin
ish. But Rusputln won, and Iliador
fled to this country.
Probably the most surprising tiling
about the overturning of the Romanoff
dynasty was the ease with which it
was accomplished. Hut a peep behind
the scenes with Iliador into the court
life of the czar, into the degeneracy of
the nobles, and to the czar himself, de
scribed by Iliador as a "man without a
tongue, nervous, weak, phlegmatic,
hardly able to articulate, an abrupt
voice, emitting muffled sounds like
those fron} the grave, eyes dull, misty
and filled with tears"_rnay help to ex
plain. It was the French revolution
repeating itself.
Wielded Terrible Influence.
For years the czar had listened to
the "teachings" of religious mystics
and the hist anil the greatest of these
was Rasputin. Iliador said lie pos
sessed almost hypnotic powers and this
power first exerted itself on women
and through them to the court Itself,
One of those first to fall under his in
fluence was the czarina and ttie
soon succumbed.
How strong the
mystics was on the
czar
influence of the.
zar is illustrated
b.v the fact that Iliador relates that
when his ministers had finished giving
him their opinions of weighty matters
tlie mystics would sweep in and get
the last moments of the czar's atten
tion, often reversing all that the min
isters had said. Rasputin, the.greatest
of these, was able to use this weakness
to great personal advantage and many
efforts to overthrow him were defeated
by the czar himself.
It was shortly after Rasputin was
introduced to court by the wife of
fainous general tliAtJiii revolutionier
1905 tool! place, cjMot aid
court. fr$shtenedcwjy)
the populace, pi-epSOm to flee, "rm
putin, however, presented such a firm
and from that moment Rasputin held
roll sway.
Many serious charges were made
concerning Rasputin's personal sway
over the czarina, Iliador said, but it
was alwavs the czar who quashed
these charges. What were the prac
tices of Hm cult Rasputin led In the
innermost circles of the court Iliador
never wrote, but lie hinted that the
so-called cult practiced the most re
volting rites.
Assassination of Stolypin.
mi:
j 1 nited Statt
canal.
The assassination of Stolypin, Itia
dor laid directly to Rasputin and the
czar, stoloypln had got in Rasputin's
way and his elimination was an easy
matter: Iliador said -also that it was
Rasputin who prevented Russia going
to war with Austria when Austria took
over Bosnia and Herzegovina. Count
Witte was a favorite of Rasputin's and
was prat finally made premier through
Rasputin's offices.
Russia's entering the present war
was due. Iliador said, to another dream
Of Rasputin. He became an ardent
supporter of the idea of a separate
peace with Germany. It was only the
scandai inL-d by the duma and bis
subsequent assassination that pré
vint ed it.
on one occasion his life w
tempt'd by a young woman. Iliador
d. whom Rasputin had wronged.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
        <id>https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn83045211/1917-10-23/ed-1/?sp=19&q=rasputin</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>(Coprlht. 1017, Publlo Ledger Compny. All rlchta reserved.)
fjte Characteristic Feature of Rasputin's Domi
nance as a Holy Mystic Is That It Was Made
Use of by Conspirators in the Government to
Farther Their Own Ends It Was This
Duplicity Which Was the Principal Harm
Done by the "Monk"
It Was Not Long Before the Siberian Peasant
Wearied of the Limited Field Offered His
"Religious" Powers at Home and He Turned
Uis Steps Toward Russia Proper There He
Won Many Converts to His Sect, Which
Observed Objectionable Doctrines
CHAPTER II
THE beginnings ui mc mrecr oi uregory itasputin arc shrouded
with a veil of deep mystery. He was a native of Siberia, of a small
f 11im in the government of Tobolsk, called Pokrowskoie. Some
L pMpl "to tnat wncn qu'to a yutl1 nc was compromised in a crime
JUch attracted some attention at the time the murder of a rich
I merchnt who was traveling from Omsk to Tobolsk to acquire from
I is inhabitant of Tobolsk some gold diggings, of which the latter
j, planed to dispose. This merchant was known to carry a large sum
ef money, and as he never reached his destination inquiries were
itarted. At last his body was found, with the head battered by
t!ow. hidden in a ditch by the high road, together with that of tho
f coachman who had driven him. The murderers were never discov
ered, but dark rumors concerning the participation of the youth
Euputin in the d,ccd spread all over the village.
Rasputin's Start as a "Prophet"
Whether it was the desire to put an end to them, or remorse for
in action of which ho knew himself to bo guilty, it is difficult to
Ity, but the fact subsists that suddenly Gricha, as he was called,
t developed mystical tendencies and took to attending some relirrious
settings at which a certain wandering pilgrim used to preach. The
Utter used to go from place to place in Siberia predicting the end
cf the world and the advent of the dreaded day of judgment when
Christ would once again appear to demand from humanity an
iccount of its various good or bad actions. For something like two
years Rasputin followed him, until at last he began himself to
I usame the character of a lay preacher, to apply himself to the study
f the Scrintures and to trv to nstnhlUfc n nrwf nt fcio i
j v. r wi.vv v ...a Wt11 UIU
f principles of which he exposed to his followers in these terms:
"I am possessed of the Holy Spirit, and it is only through
me that one can be saved. In order to do so, one must unite
oneself with me in body and soul. Everything which proceeds from
nt is holy and cleans one ,from sin."
On the strength of this theory Rasputin declared that he could
it whatever he liked or wished. He surrounded himself with wor-
iWpers of both sexes, who believed that by a close union with
him they could obtain their eternal salvation, together with divine
I forgiveness for any sin3 they might have committed during their
I previous existence.
Strange tales began to be related concerning the religious as
1 itmblies at which the new prophet presided. But, nevertheless, tho
I whole village of Pokrowskoie, whither he had returned after his
few years' wanderings, accepted his teachings and submitted to his
j decrees with scarcely any exceptions. These unbelievers were looked
jj upon askance by the majority of tho inhabitants, who had succumbed
to the "monk's" power of fascination and hypnotism. It was with
nothing else that Rasputin kept his "flock" subjugated. He intro-
duced among them the cult of his own person, together with certain
t rites which he called "sacrifice with prayer."
j According to the narratives of some people, who out of curiosity
j lad attended these ceremonies, this is how they proceeded: In the
L night, as soon as the firBt stars had become visible in the skies,
j Rasputin, with the help of his disciples, dragged some wood into
a deep ditch dug for the purpose and lighted a huge bonfire. tOna
tripod placed in the midst of this fire was put a cup full of incense
l and different herbs, around which people began to dance, holding
themselves by the hand all the while and singing ina voice which
became louder and louder as the wild exercise became more and
more accelerated different hymns, which always ended with the
pirase: "Forgive us our sins, 0 Lord, forgive us our sins."
The dance went on until people fell exhausted to tho ground
and groans and tears replaced the former singing. The fire died
out slowly and. when the darkness had become comnlete. the'
Tolce of Rasputin was heard calling upon his disciples to proceed
to the sacrifice which God required them to perform. Then .followed
a icene of general orgy.
As one can see by this tale, tho strange practices introduced
hy the seer, about whom people were already beginning to talk,
differed in no way from those generally in use among the Khlysty,
f and. indeeH. Pflftnutin mnrln Tin cnrif nt Tia nllffrrinnpn in this nnr-
1 ticular form of heresy, in which, however, he had introduced a few
alterations. For instance, he did not admit that the souls of his
j followers could be saved by a general prayer, but only thanks to
I
My TheDiriricfessRadziwiiL
"I am possessed of the Holy Spirit, and it is only through mc that one can b saved.
In order to do so one must unite oneself with me in body and soul. Everything which
proceeds from mc is holy and cleans one from sin." Creed of Gregory Rasputin, the
'Prophet.'
"Around this fire people began to dance, singing in a voice
which became louder and louder as the wild exercise became
more and more accelerated, 'Forgive us our sins, 0 Lord;
forgive us our sins
Hffl
one uttered in common with him, and by a complete submission to
his will. Some persons have alleged that during tho early wander
ings of Rasputin he had gone as far as China and Thibet, and thorc
learned some Buddhist practices, but this is hardly probable, as in
that case his instruction would have been more developed than it
was. It is far more likely that during his travels he had mot with
exiled sectarians belonging to the different persecuted religious
Russian communities, of which there exist eo many in tho whole
Oural region, and that they initiated him into some of their rites
and customs. They also made him attentive to the hypnotic powers,
which he most undoubtedly possessed, teaching him how to use
them for his own benefit and advantage.
Rasputin Wins Converts
Very soon Rasputin found that Pokrowskoie was not a field
wide enough for his energies, and he took to traveling, together
with a crowd of disciples that followed him everywhere over tho
eastern and central Russian provinces. There ho coptrived to win
every day new ad.herent3 to the doctrines in which free lovo figured
so prominently. Among the towns where he obtained the most
success can be mentioned those of Kazan, Saratoff, Kieff and
Samara.
Concerning his doings in Kazan, people became informed
through a letter which one of his victims addressed to the bishop of
that diocese, Monsignor Feofane, who had shown at the beginning
of Rasputin's career a considerable interest and who had protected
him with great success. In this letter, which later on found its way
into the press, the following was said among other things:
Your Reverence, I absolutely fail to understand how it la
possible that you continue to this day to know and see Gregory
Rasputin. He is Satan in person and the things which he docs
arc worthy of those that the Antichrist alone is supposed to
perform, and prove that the lattcr's advent is at hand.
The writer then proceeded -to explain that Rasputin had com
pletely subjugated the mind of her two daughters, one of whom was
aged twenty, whilst the second had not yet attained her sixteenth
year.
One afternoon, writes this unfortunate mother, I met in
tho street, coming out of a bathhouse, Rasputin, together with
my two girls. One must be a mother to understand tho feelings
which overpowered me at this sight. I could find no words to
say, but remained standing motionless and silent before them.
The prophet turned to me nnd slowly said: "Now you may feel
at peace, the day of salvation has dawned for your daughters 1"
Another woman, who Lad also fallen under tho spell of
Rasputin, wrote as follows about him:
"I left my parents, to whom I was tenderly attached, to
follow the prophet. One day when wo were traveling together
in a reserved first-class carriage, talking about the sajvation of
souls and tho means to become a true child of God, ho sud
denly got up and npproached me, and proceeded to
clean me of all my sins. Toward evening I became anxious
and asked'him: 'Perhaps what we have been doing today was
a sin, Gregoryfimitsch?' 'No, my daughter,' he replied, 'it
was not a sin. Our affections are a gift from God, which we
may use as freely as we like.'
Bishop Feofane finally was obliged to recognize the evil which
Rasputin was constantly doing, and he bitterly repented having
been taken in by him and by his hypocrisy. He reproached himself
especially for having given him a letter of recommendation to the
famous Father John of Cronstadt, through whom Rasputin was
to become acquainted with somo of tho people who were later on
to pilot him in the society of St. Petersburg. The Bishop was not
a clever man by any means, but he had been sincere in his admira
tion for Rasputin, a fact which added to the consternation that
overpowered him when the truth about the famous sectarian became
known to him. He assembled u kind of judicial court, composed
of one bishop, one monk and three well-known and highly respected
civil functionaries, and called upon the prophet to come and explain
himself before this court as to the actions which were imputed to
him. Among these figured his jrenernl conduct in regard to th
women who had enrolled themselves in tho ranks of his disciples
But somehow the adventurer succeeded in dispelling tho suspicions
that had become attached to his namo nnd conduct, nnd ho explained
in a moro or less plausible manner tho things which had been told
about him. His leanings for feminine society, and his Invariable'
custom of bathing himself together with women ho declared to
be quite innocent things, and only a proof of his desire to show that
it wna quite possible for human beings to riso above every kind
of carnal temptation.
In 8pito of this episode, which would have interfered with the
career of any ono but Rasputin, tho famo of the latter grew with
every day that passed. Ho established himself at last in the town
of Tiumen In Siberia, whero ho hired a whole large house for
himself and some of his most favored disciples, and ho began to
turn his activity into another nnd moro profitable channel. He
established reception hours every day, when all his followers,
admirers nnd friends could come to speak with him about any
business they liked. Hundreds of people used to attend those
receptions, among them somo very Influential persons curious to
see nnd speak with the modern Peter the Hermit, who declared
that he had been called by God to save Holy Russia. In some
mystorious manner ho acquired tho reputation of having great
Influence in high quarters, whero (this must bo noticed) ho was
nt tho timo yet qulto unknown. Governors fearing dismissal,
rapacious functionaries whoso exactions had become too flagrant,
aB well ns business men in quest of somo good "geschaft," to use
tho German expression employed before tho war among financial
circles in Russia, crowded round him, waiting sometimes hours for
on opportunity to speak with him, and fully believing in his capaci
ties for obtaining what they required.
Rasputin soon became a kind of business agent and surrounded
himself with a number of secretaries of both scxe3, whose occupa
tion consisted in attending to his correspondence he could hardly
read or write and in receiving the numerous offerings which were
being brought to him dally. These secretaries, among whom figured
a sister of the Bishop of Saratoff, Warnawa, mado an immense
nmount of money themselves because no ono was ever admitted,
into the presenco of Rasputin without having previously paid dearly
for this favor. Very soon they established a tax in regard to tho
audiences granted by their master.
"Spiritual Sisters", of Rasputin
Besides this sister of Bishop Warnawa, Rasputin had another
femalo secretary, and they both accompanied him in all his travels,
calling themselves his spiritual sisters. They constituted, so to s'ay
his bodyguard, and wherever ho went, even in St. Petersburg, they
never loft off attending him and seeing to nil his wants. They
were tho channel th'rough which everything had to go, nnd without
their consent no one was ever admitted into tho presence of the
"Saint," ns they already had begun to call him.
Gregory Rasputin very often used to visit Tobolsk, where ho
was always received with great ceremony and pomp, as if he had
been really the important personage he believed himself. The police
man in the streets saluted him as he passed; the carriage in which
ho drpvo was escorted or preceded by a high police functionary, and
tho governor asked him to dinner. The same kind of thing used to
take place in other Siberian cities. In one of them the staterooms
reserved at the railway station for any high authority on a visit to
the place were thrown open to him. In another triumphal arches
were erected in his honor, while in a third he was met by deputations
in tho midst of which could be seen civil functionaries and religious
dignitaries.
How all this happened no one knew or could explain. In what
consisted the fame of Rasputin and what he had dono to" deserve all
these honors nobody could tell. But fame ho had acquired, honors
he had obtained, and whero another person gifted with a smaller
amount of impudence than he was possessed of would have been put
into prison or sent to a madhouse, Gricha, as he was familiarly
called, had it all his own way, and defied governors and judges with
an equal indifference, sure that nono among them would be daring
enough to try to put a stop to his progress or to his avidity.
Most friendly, not to say Intimate, relations were established
between Rasputin and Bishop Warnawa, especially after the letter's
elevation to the episcopal See of Tobolsk. The first sermon which
Warnawa preached in that town ho dedicated to the wifo o
Rasputin. One need not say that tho whole clergy of the town
and of the diocese trembled before Rasputin, who did not fail to
exact from it large sums of money, which he extorted, thanks to
the promises which he made but never meant in the least to keep.
During the course of the year 1909 complaints about Rasputin's
behavior increased to a considerable extent. He was once more
called before an ecclesiastical court to give explanations in regard
to his general conduct. Among his judges figured again Bishop
Feofane. This time Rasputin could not clear himself of the charges
preferred against him, and he was invited to retire for one year
into a monastery by way of penance. But Rasputin refused to
submit himself to this sentenco and categorically declined to. do as
ho had been told. Ho gave as a reason for his disobedienco to
the commands of his ecclesiastical superiors that his conscience
obliged him to resist because it would be impossible for his "spiritual
sisters and daughters" to accompany him in his retreat and live
together with him in the monastery they wished him to enter.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
